<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" submissionType="IETF" category="info" consensus="true" docName="draft-pti-pen-registration-10" number="9371" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="4" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">

<!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.15.3 -->
<front>

    <title abbrev="PEN Registration">Registration Procedures for Private Enterprise Numbers (PENs)</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9371"/>
    <author initials="A." surname="Baber" fullname="Amanda Baber">
      <organization abbrev="IANA">Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <extaddr>PTI/ICANN</extaddr>
          <street>12025 Waterfront Drive</street>
          <city>Los Angeles</city>
          <code>90094</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>amanda.baber@iana.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Paul Hoffman" initials="P" surname="Hoffman">
      <organization>ICANN</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12025 Waterfront Drive</street>
          <city>Los Angeles</city>
          <code>90094</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>paul.hoffman@icann.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2023" month="March" />

    <abstract>
      <t>
This document describes how Private Enterprise Numbers (PENs) are registered by IANA. It
shows how to request a new PEN and how to modify a current PEN. It also gives
a brief overview of PEN uses.
</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
Private Enterprise Numbers (PENs) are identifiers that can be used anywhere that an ASN.1
object identifier (OID) <xref target="ASN1" format="default"/> can be used. Originally, PENs were developed
so that organizations that needed to identify themselves in Simple Network Management
Protocol (SNMP) <xref target="RFC3411" format="default"/> Management Information Base (MIB) configurations
could do so easily. PENs are also useful in any application or configuration language that
needs OIDs to identify organizations. 
</t>

<t>
The IANA Functions Operator, referred to in this document as "IANA",
manages and maintains the PEN registry in consultation with the IESG.
PENs are issued from an OID prefix that was assigned to IANA. That OID
prefix is 1.3.6.1.4.1. Using the (now archaic) notation of ownership names in the OID
tree, that corresponds to:
</t>
<artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
1   3   6   1        4       1
iso.org.dod.internet.private.enterprise
]]></artwork>
      <t>
A PEN is an OID that begins with the PEN prefix. Thus, the OID 1.3.6.1.4.1.32473 is a
PEN.
</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Uses of PENs</name>
        <t>
Once a PEN has been assigned to an organization, individual, or other entity, that assignee can use the
PEN by itself (possibly to represent the assignee) or as the root of other OIDs
associated with the assignee. For example, if an assignee is assigned the PEN
1.3.6.1.4.1.32473, it might use 1.3.6.1.4.1.32473.7 to identify a protocol extension
and use 1.3.6.1.4.1.32473.12.3 to identify a set of algorithms that it supports in a
protocol.
</t>
        <t>
Neither IANA nor the IETF can control how an assignee uses
its PEN. In fact, no one can exert such control: that is the meaning of "private"
in "private enterprise number". Similarly, no one can prevent an assignee that
is not the registered owner of a PEN from using that PEN, or any PEN, however they want.
</t>
        <t>
A very common use of PENs is to give unique identifiers in IETF protocols. SNMP MIB
configuration files use PENs for identifying the origin of values. Protocols that use
PENs as identifiers of extension mechanisms include
RADIUS <xref target="RFC2865" format="default"/>,
Diameter <xref target="RFC6733" format="default"/>,
Syslog <xref target="RFC5424" format="default"/>,
RSVP <xref target="RFC5284" format="default"/>,
and vCard <xref target="RFC6350" format="default"/>.
</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>PEN Assignment</name>

      <t>
PENs are assigned by IANA. The registry is located at 
<eref target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/enterprise-numbers" brackets="angle"/>, and requests for new assignments 
or the modification of existing assignments can also be submitted at that URL.
</t>
      <t>
IANA maintains the PEN registry in accordance with the "First Come First
Served" registration policy described in <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>.  Values are 
assigned sequentially.
</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requesting a PEN Assignment</name>
        <t>
Requests for assignment must provide the name of the assignee, the name of a 
public contact who can respond to questions about the assignment, and contact 
information that can be used to verify change requests. The contact's name and
email address will be included in the public registry.
</t>

<t>
A prospective assignee may request multiple PENs, but obtaining one PEN and making 
internal sub-assignments is typically more appropriate. (Sub-assignments 
should not be reported to IANA.)
</t>

<t>
IANA may refuse to process abusive requests.
</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Modifying an Existing Record</name>
        <t>
Any of the information associated
with a registered value can be modified, including the name of the assignee.
</t>
        <t>
Modification requests require authorization by a representative of the 
assignee.  Authorization will be validated either with information kept on 
file with IANA or with other identifying documentation, if necessary.
</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Deleting a PEN Record</name>
        <t>
Although such requests are rare, registrations can be deleted. When a 
registration is deleted, all identifying information is removed from the 
registry, and the value is marked as "returned." Returned values will not be 
made available for reassignment until all other unassigned values have been 
exhausted; as can be seen in <xref target="specifics" format="default"/>, the unassigned values
are unlikely to ever run out.
</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="specifics" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>PEN Registry Specifics</name>
<t>
The range for values after the PEN prefix is 0 to 2**32-1. The values 0 and 4294967295
(2**32-1) are reserved. Note that while the original PEN definition had no upper bound for
the value after the PEN prefix, there is now an upper bound due to some IETF
protocols limiting the size of that value. For example, Diameter <xref target="RFC6733" format="default"/>
limits the value to 2**32-1.
</t>
      <t>
There is a PEN number, 32473, reserved for use as an example in documentation. This
reservation is described in <xref target="RFC5612" format="default"/>.
</t>
      <t>
Values in the registry that have unclear ownership are marked "Reserved". These values
will not be reassigned to a new company or individual without consulting the IESG.
</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">

      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
Per this document, IANA has made the following changes to the PEN registry:
</t>
<ul spacing="normal">
<li>Values 2187, 2188, 3513, 4164, 4565, 4600, 4913, 4999, 5099, 5144, 5201,
5683, 5777, 6260, 6619, 14827, 16739, 26975, and the range from 11670 to
11769, which had been missing from the registry, have been listed as
"Reserved." As described in <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>, reserved values can be
released by the IESG.
</li>
<li>
This document has been listed in the registry's "Reference" field.
</li>
<li>
"First Come First Served" has been listed as its registration procedure.
</li>
</ul>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
Registering PENs does not introduce any significant security considerations.
</t>
      <t>
There is no cryptographic binding of a registrant in the PEN registry and the PEN(s)
assigned to them. Thus, the entries in the PEN registry cannot be used to validate the
ownership of a PEN in use. For example, if the PEN 1.3.6.1.4.1.32473 is seen in a protocol
as indicating the owner of some data, there is no way to securely correlate that use with
the name and assignee of the owner listed in the PEN registry.
</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

        <reference anchor="ASN1" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-X.690/en">
          <front>
            <title>Information technology - ASN.1 encoding rules: Specification of Basic Encoding Rules (BER), Canonical Encoding Rules (CER) and Distinguished Encoding Rules (DER)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>ITU-T</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="February" year="2021"/>
          </front>
	  <seriesInfo name='ITU-T Recommendation' value='X.690' />
        </reference>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3411.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6733.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5284.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5424.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5612.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6350.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>
An earlier draft version of this document was authored by <contact fullname="Pearl Liang"/> and
<contact fullname="Alexey Melnikov"/>. Additional significant contributions have come from
<contact fullname="Dan Romascanu"/>, <contact fullname="Bert Wijnen"/>, <contact fullname="David Conrad"/>, <contact fullname="Michelle Cotton"/>, and <contact fullname="Benoit Claise"/>.
</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
