<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" docName="draft-ietf-httpapi-api-catalog-08" number="9727" category="std" consensus="true" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3" xml:lang="en" updates="" obsoletes="">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="api-catalog: A Well-Known URI">api-catalog: A Well-Known URI and Link Relation to Help Discovery of APIs</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9727"/>
    <author initials="K." surname="Smith" fullname="Kevin Smith">
      <organization>Vodafone</organization>
      <address>
        <email>kevin.smith@vodafone.com</email>
        <uri>https://www.vodafone.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="2025"/>
    <area>WIT</area>
    <workgroup>httpapi</workgroup>

<keyword>API</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines the "api-catalog" well-known URI and link
      relation. It is intended to facilitate automated discovery and usage of
      published Application Programming Interfaces (APIs). A request to the
      api-catalog resource will return a document providing information about,
      and links to, the Publisher's APIs.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

<section anchor="introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>An application may publish APIs
to encourage requests for interaction from external parties. Such
APIs must be discovered before they may be used, i.e., the external
party needs to know what APIs a given Publisher exposes, their
purpose, any policies for usage, and the endpoint to interact with
each API. To facilitate automated discovery of this information 
and automated usage of the APIs, this document proposes:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t>a well-known URI <xref target="RFC8615"/>, "api-catalog", that is encoded as a URI 
reference to an API catalog document describing a Publisher's API 
endpoints.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>a link relation <xref target="RFC8288"/>, "api-catalog", of which the target
resource is the Publisher's API catalog document.</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <section anchor="goals">
        <name>Goals and Non-Goals</name>
<t>The primary goal of this document is to facilitate the automated discovery
of a Publisher's public API endpoints, along with metadata that describes the
purpose and usage of each API, by specifying a well-known URI that returns an
API catalog document. The API catalog document is primarily machine-readable
to enable automated discovery and usage of APIs, and it may also include links
to human-readable documentation (see the example in <xref
target="api-catalog-example-rfc8615"/>).</t>
        <t>Non-goals: This document does not mandate paths for API endpoints, i.e., it does not mandate that my_example_api's endpoint should be
<tt>https://www.example.com/.well-known/api-catalog/my_example_api</tt>, nor 
even to be hosted at www.example.com (although it is not forbidden to 
do so).</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="notational-conventions">
        <name>Notational Conventions</name>
        <t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
"<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they
appear in all capitals, as shown here.
These words may also appear in this document in
lower case as plain English words, absent their normative meanings.
        </t>
        <t>The terms "content negotiation" and "status code" are from <xref target="RFC9110"/>.
The term "well-known URI" is from <xref target="RFC8615"/>.
The term "link relation" is from <xref target="RFC8288"/>.</t>
        <t>The term "Publisher" refers to an organisation, company, or
        individual that publishes one or more APIs for use by external third
        parties.  A fictional Publisher named "example" is used throughout
        this document.  The examples use the Fully Qualified Domain Names
        (FQDNs) "www.example.com", "developer.example.com", "apis.example.com", "apis.example.net", "gaming.example.com", and 
        "iot.example.net", where the .com and .net Top-Level Domains (TLDs) and various
        subdomains are simply used to illustrate that the "example" Publisher may
        have their API portfolio distributed across various domains for which
        they are the authority. 
Scenarios where the Publisher "example" is
        not the authority for a given <em>.example.</em> domain are
        made explicit in the text.</t>
        <t>In this document, "API" refers to the specification resources required 
for an external party (or in the case of "private" APIs, an internal 
party) to implement software that uses the Publisher's API.</t>
        <t>The specification recommends the use of TLS. Hence, "HTTPS" and 
"https://" are used throughout.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="usage">
      <name>Using the "api-catalog" Well-Known URI</name>
      <t>The api-catalog well-known URI is intended for HTTPS servers that 
publish APIs.</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t>The API catalog <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be named "api-catalog" in a well-known location
 as described by <xref target="RFC8615"/>.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>The location of the API catalog document is decided by the Publisher. 
The /.well-known/api-catalog URI provides a convenient reference to
that location.</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>A Publisher supporting this URI:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t><bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> resolve an HTTPS GET request to /.well-known/api-catalog and
return an API catalog document (as described in <xref target="api-catalog"/>).</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t><bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> resolve an HTTPS HEAD request to /.well-known/api-catalog
with a response including a Link header with the relation(s) defined
in <xref target="link-relation"/>.</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section anchor="link-relation">
      <name>The api-catalog Link Relation</name>
      <t>This document introduces a new link relation <xref target="RFC8288"/>, 
"api-catalog". This identifies a target resource that represents a
list of APIs available from the Publisher of the link context. 
The target resource URI may be /.well-known/api-catalog or any
other URI chosen by the Publisher. For example, the Publisher
"example" could include the api-catalog link relation in the HTTP
header and/or content payload when responding to a request to
<tt>https://www.example.com</tt>:</t>
      <sourcecode type="http-message"><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: text/html; charset=UTF-8
Location: /index.html
Link: </my_api_catalog.json>; rel=api-catalog
Content-Length: 356

<!DOCTYPE HTML>
  <html>
    <head>
      <title>Welcome to Example Publisher</title>
    </head>
    <body>
      <p>
       <a href="my_api_catalog.json" rel="api-catalog">
        Example Publisher's APIs
       </a>
      </p>
      <p>(remainder of content)</p>
    </body>
  </html>
]]></sourcecode>
      <section anchor="using-additional-link-relations">
        <name>Using Additional Link Relations</name>
            <t>When used in an API catalog document, the "item" <xref target="RFC6573"/> link relation identifies a target resource that represents an
API that is a member of the API catalog.</t>
            <t>Other link relations may be utilised in an API catalog to convey
metadata descriptions for API links.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="api-catalog">
      <name>The API Catalog Document</name>
      <t>The API catalog is a document listing a Publisher's APIs. The
Publisher may host the API catalog document at any URI(s) 
they choose. 
   For example, the API catalog document URI of
   <tt>https://www.example.com/my_api_catalog.json</tt> can be requested directly or
   via a request to <tt>https://www.example.com/.well-known/api-catalog</tt>, which
   the Publisher will resolve to <tt>https://www.example.com/my_api_catalog</tt>.</t>
      <section anchor="api-catalog-contents">
        <name>API Catalog Contents</name>

<t> The API catalog <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include hyperlinks to API
endpoints. It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that the API catalog also includes
useful metadata, such as usage policies, API version information, links to the
OpenAPI Specification <xref target="OAS"/> definitions for each API, etc. If the Publisher does not 
include that metadata directly in the API catalog document, they 
<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> make that metadata available at the API endpoint URIs they 
have listed (see <xref target="api-catalog-example-linkset-bookmarks"/> for 
an example).</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="api-catalog-formats">
        <name>API Catalog Formats</name>
        <t>The Publisher <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> publish the API catalog document in the Linkset
format <tt>application/linkset+json</tt> (<xref section="4.2" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC9264"/>). 
The Linkset <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> include a profile parameter (<xref section="5" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC9264"/>) with a Profile URI <xref target="RFC7284"/> value of "https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9727"
to indicate the Linkset is representing an API catalog document as
defined above. <xref target="api-catalog-example-linkset"/> includes example API catalog documents 
based on the Linkset format.</t>

        <t>The Publisher <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> make additional formats available via 
content negotiation (<xref section="12" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC9110"/>) to their 
/.well-known/api-catalog location. A non-exhaustive list of such 
formats that support the automated discovery and machine (and 
human) usage of a Publisher's APIs is listed at
<xref target="api-catalog-other-formats"/>. If a Publisher already lists their
APIs in a format other than Linkset, but wishes to utilise the 
/.well-known/api-catalog URI, then:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>They <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> also implement a Linkset with, at minimum, hyperlinks to
API endpoints; see <xref target="api-catalog-example-linkset-bookmarks"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>They <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> support content negotiation at the 
/.well-known/api-catalog URI to allow for the return of their existing format.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="nest">
        <name>Nesting API Catalog Links</name>
        <t>An API catalog may itself contain links to other API catalogs by using
        the "api-catalog" relation type for each link.  An example of this is
        given in <xref target="api-catalog-example-linkset-nesting"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="operations">
      <name>Operational Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="multiple_domains">
        <name>Accounting for APIs Distributed Across Multiple Domains</name>
        <t>A Publisher ("example") may have their APIs hosted across multiple 
domains that they manage, e.g., at <tt>www.example.com</tt>, 
<tt>developer.example.com</tt>, <tt>apis.example.com</tt>, 
<tt>apis.example.net</tt>, etc. They may also use a third-party API 
hosting provider that hosts APIs on a distinct domain.</t>
        <t>To account for this scenario, it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>The Publisher also publish the api-catalog well-known URI at each
 of their API domains, e.g., <tt>https://apis.example.com/.well-known/api-catalog</tt>, 
 <tt>https://developer.example.net/.well-known/api-catalog</tt>, etc.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>An HTTPS GET request to any of these URIs returns the same result,
 namely, the API catalog document.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>The Publisher choose one of their
instances of /.well-known/api-catalog as a canonical reference to 
the location of the latest API catalog since the physical location of the API catalog document is decided by the Publisher and may change. The Publisher's other 
instances of /.well-known/api-catalog should redirect to this 
canonical instance of /.well-known/api-catalog to ensure the latest
API catalog is returned.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>For example, if the Publisher's primary API portal is 
<tt>https://apis.example.com</tt>, then 
<tt>https://apis.example.com/.well-known/api-catalog</tt> should resolve to 
the location of the Publisher's latest API catalog document. If the 
Publisher is also the domain authority for <tt>www.example.net</tt>, 
which also hosts a selection of their APIs, then a request to 
<tt>https://www.example.net/.well-known/api-catalog</tt> should redirect
to <tt>https://apis.example.com/.well-known/api-catalog</tt>.</t>

<t>If the Publisher is not the domain authority for <tt>www.example.net</tt>,
   then the Publisher's API Catalog <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> include a link to the
  API catalog of the third-party that is the domain authority for <tt>www.example.net</tt>. For example, the API catalog available 
at <tt>https://apis.example.com/.well-known/api-catalog</tt> may list APIs 
hosted at <tt>apis.example.com</tt> and also link to the API catalog hosted 
at <tt>https://www.example.net/.well-known/api-catalog</tt> using the 
"api-catalog" link relation:</t>
        <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
{
 "linkset": [
  {
   "anchor": "https://www.example.com/.well-known/api-catalog",
   "item": [
    {
     "href": "https://developer.example.com/apis/foo_api"
    },
    {
     "href": "https://developer.example.com/apis/bar_api"
    },
    {
     "href": "https://developer.example.com/apis/cantona_api"
    }
   ],
   "api-catalog": "https://www.example.net/.well-known/api-catalog"
  }
 ]
}
]]></sourcecode>
      </section>
      <section anchor="internal-use">
        <name>Internal Use of api-catalog for Private APIs</name>
        <t>A Publisher may wish to use the api-catalog well-known URI on their 
internal network to signpost authorised users (e.g., company 
employees) towards internal/private APIs not intended for third-party
use. This scenario may incur additional security considerations as 
noted in <xref target="security"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="scalability">
        <name>Scalability Guidelines</name>
        <t>In cases where a Publisher has a large number of APIs potentially
deployed across multiple domains, two challenges may arise:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>Maintaining the catalog entries to ensure they are up to date and
correcting any errors.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Restricting the catalog size to help reduce network and 
client-processing overheads.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>In both cases, a Publisher may benefit from grouping their APIs,
providing an API catalog document for each group and using the main
API catalog hosted at /.well-known/api-catalog to provide links to
these. For example, a Publisher may decide to group their APIs
according to a business category (e.g., "gaming APIs", "anti-fraud
APIs", etc.), a technology category (e.g., "IOT", "networks", "AI",
etc.), or any other criterion.

   This grouping may be implicit where the Publisher has already published
   their APIs across multiple domains, e.g., at <tt>gaming.example.com</tt>,
   <tt>iot.example.net</tt>, etc.</t>
        <t><xref target="nest"/> shows how the API catalog at
/.well-known/api-catalog can use the api-catalog link relation to
point to other API catalogs.</t>
        <t>The Publisher <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> consider caching and compression 
techniques to reduce the network overhead of large API catalogs.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="maintenance">
        <name>Monitoring and Maintenance</name>
        <t>Publishers are <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> to follow operational best practice when
hosting API catalog(s), including, but not limited to:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>Availability. The Publisher should monitor availability of the API
catalog and consider alternate means to resolve requests to
/.well-known/api-catalog during planned downtime of hosts.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Performance. Although the performance of APIs listed in an API
catalog can demand high transactions per second and low-latency
response, the retrieval of the API catalog itself to discover those
APIs is less likely to incur strict performance demands. That said,
the Publisher should monitor the response time to fulfil a request
for the API catalog and determine any necessary improvements (as
with any other Web resource the Publisher serves). For large API
catalogs, the Publisher should consider the techniques described in
<xref target="scalability"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Usage. Since the goal of the api-catalog well-known URI is to
facilitate discovery of APIs, the Publisher may wish to correlate
requests to the /.well-known/api-catalog URI with subsequent requests
to the API URIs listed in the catalog.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Current data. The Publisher should include the removal of stale API
entries from the API catalog as part of their API release lifecycle.
The Publisher <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> decide to include metadata regarding legacy API
versions or deprecated APIs to help users of those APIs discover
up-to-date alternatives.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Correct metadata. The Publisher should include human and/or
automated checks for syntax errors in the API catalog. Automated
checks include format validation (e.g., to ensure valid JSON syntax)
and linting to enforce business rules, such as removing duplicate
entries and ensuring descriptions are correctly named with valid
values. A proofread of the API catalog as part of the API release
lifecycle is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> to detect any errors in business grammar
(for example, an API entry that is described with valid syntax, but
has been allocated an incorrect or outdated description.)</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Security best practice. See <xref target="security"/>.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="integration">
        <name>Integration with Existing API Management Frameworks</name>
        <t>A Publisher may already utilise an API management framework to
produce their API portfolio. These frameworks typically include the
publication of API endpoint URIs, deprecation and redirection of
legacy API versions, API usage policies and documentation, etc.
The api-catalog well-known URI and API catalog document are intended
to complement API management frameworks by facilitating the discovery
of the framework's outputs -- API endpoints, usage policies, and
documentation -- and are not intended to replace any existing
API discovery mechanisms the framework has implemented.</t>
        <t>Providers of such frameworks may include the production of an API
catalog and the publication of the /.well-known/api-catalog URI as a
final pre-release (or post-release) step in the release management
workflow. The following steps are recommended.</t>
        <t>If the /.well-known/api-catalog URI has not been published previously, the framework provider should:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>Collate and check the metadata for each API that will be included
in the API catalog. This metadata is likely to already exist in the
framework.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Determine which metadata to include in the API catalog following
the requirements set out in <xref target="api-catalog-contents"/> and the
considerations set out in <xref target="operations"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Map the chosen metadata to the format(s) described in
<xref target="api-catalog-formats"/>. The structure suggested in                                
<xref target="api-catalog-example-linkset-bookmarks"/> may be followed where only the hyperlinks to APIs are to be 
included in the API catalog. Where 
possible, the API catalog should include further metadata per the 
guidance in <xref target="api-catalog-contents"/>; in which case, the structure
suggested in <xref target="api-catalog-example-linkset"/> can be utilised and
adapted (ensuring compliance to <xref target="RFC9264"/>) to reflect the nature
of the chosen metadata.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Publish the /.well-known/api-catalog URI following the guidance set
out in <xref target="usage"/>.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>If the /.well-known/api-catalog URI has previously been published,
the framework provider should:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>Include a step in the release management lifecycle to refresh the
API catalog following any changes in API hyperlinks or published
metadata. This could include placing triggers on certain metadata
fields, so that as they are updated in pre-production on the API
framework, the updates are pushed to a pre-production copy of the API
catalog to be pushed live when the release is published by the
framework.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="conform-rfc8615">
      <name>Conformance to RFC 8615</name>
      <t>The requirements in <xref section="3" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC8615"/> for defining 
Well-Known URIs are met as described in the
following subsections.</t>
      <section anchor="path-suffix">
        <name>Path Suffix</name>
        <t>The api-catalog URI <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be appended to the /.well-known/
path-prefix for "well-known locations".</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="formats-and-associated-media-types">
        <name>Formats and Associated Media Types</name>
        <t>A /.well-known/api-catalog location <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> support the Linkset
<xref target="RFC9264"/> format of application/linkset+json and <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>
also support the other formats via content negotiation.</t>
      </section>
      
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="the-api-catalog-well-known-uri">
        <name>The api-catalog Well-Known URI</name>
        <t>This specification registers the "api-catalog" well-known URI in
        the "Well-Known URIs" registry as defined by <xref
        target="RFC8615"/>.</t>
        <dl spacing="compact" newline="false">
          <dt>URI Suffix:</dt><dd>api-catalog</dd>
          <dt>Reference:</dt><dd>RFC 9727</dd>
          <dt>Status:</dt><dd>permanent</dd>	  
          <dt>Change Controller:</dt><dd>IETF</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section anchor="the-api-catalog-link-relation">
        <name>The api-catalog Link Relation</name>
        <t>This specification registers the "api-catalog" link relation in the "Link Relation Types" registry by
        following the procedures per <xref section="2.1.1.1" sectionFormat="of"
        target="RFC8288"/>.</t>
        <dl spacing="compact" newline="false">
          <dt>Relation Name:</dt><dd>api-catalog</dd>
          <dt>Description:</dt><dd>Refers to a list of APIs available from the
          Publisher of the link context.</dd>
          <dt>Reference:</dt><dd>RFC 9727</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="the-api-catalog-profile-uri">
        <name>The api-catalog Profile URI</name>
        <t>This specification registers "https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9727" in the "Profile URIs"
        registry according to <xref target="RFC7284"/>.</t>
        <dl spacing="compact" newline="false">
          <dt>Profile URI:</dt><dd>https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9727</dd>
          <dt>Common Name:</dt><dd>API catalog</dd>
          <dt>Description:</dt><dd>A Profile URI to request or signal a
          Linkset representing an API catalog.</dd>
	  <dt>Reference:</dt><dd>RFC 9727</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>For all scenarios:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t>TLS <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be used, i.e., make /.well-known/api-catalog available
exclusively over HTTPS, to ensure no tampering of the API catalog.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>The Publisher <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> take into account the security considerations
from <xref section="4" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC8615"/>.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>The Publisher <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> perform a security and privacy review of the
API catalog prior to deployment to ensure it does not leak personal,
business, or other sensitive metadata, nor expose any vulnerability
related to the APIs listed.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>The Publisher <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> enforce read-only privileges for external
requests to .well-known/api-catalog and for internal systems and
roles that monitor the .well-known/api-catalog URI. Write privileges
<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> only be granted to roles that perform updates to the API 
catalog and/or the forwarding rewrite rules for the
.well-known/api-catalog URI.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>As with any Web offering, it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> to apply rate-limiting
measures to help mitigate abuse and prevent denial-of-service
attacks on the API catalog endpoint.</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>For the public-facing APIs scenario, security teams <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> 
additionally audit the API catalog to ensure no APIs intended solely
for internal use have been mistakenly included. For example, a
catalog hosted on <tt>https://developer.example.com</tt> should not expose
unnecessary metadata about any internal domains
(e.g., <tt>https://internal.example.com</tt>).</t>
      <t>For the internal/private APIs scenario, the Publisher <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> take
steps to ensure that appropriate controls, such as Cross-Origin Resource Sharing (CORS) policies and
access control lists, are in place to ensure only authorised roles
and systems may access an internal api-catalog well-known URI.</t>
      <t>A comprehensive API catalog that is regularly audited may assist
the Publisher in decommissioning "zombie" APIs, i.e., legacy/obsolete
APIs that should no longer be available. Such APIs represent a
security vulnerability as they are unlikely to be supported,
monitored, patched, or updated.</t>
      <t>Note the registration of domain names and associated policies is out
of scope of this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <displayreference target="RFC9110" to="HTTP"/>
    <displayreference target="RFC8288" to="WEB-LINKING"/>
    <displayreference target="RFC8615" to="WELL-KNOWN"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.kelly-json-hal" to="HAL"/>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references anchor="sec-normative-references">
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9110.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8615.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8288.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6573.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9264.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7284.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references anchor="sec-informative-references">
        <name>Informative References</name>


        <reference anchor="OAS" target="https://spec.openapis.org/oas/latest">
          <front>
            <title>OpenAPI Specification v3.1.0</title>
            <author initials="D" surname="Miller" role="editor">
             <organization/>
            </author>
	    <author initials="H" surname="Andrews" role="editor">
	     <organization/>
	    </author>
            <author initials="J" surname="Whitlock" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
	    <author initials="L" surname="Mitchell" role="editor">
	      <organization/>
	    </author>
            <author initials="M" surname="Gardiner" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
	    <author initials="M" surname="Quintero" role="editor">
	      <organization/>
	    </author>
            <author initials="M" surname="Kistler" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
	    <author initials="R" surname="Handl" role="editor">
  	      <organization/>
	    </author>
            <author initials="R" surname="Ratovsky" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2024" month="October" day="24"/>
          </front>
          <annotation>Latest version available at <eref
          target="https://spec.openapis.org/oas/latest.html" brackets="angle"/>.</annotation>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="APIsjson" target="https://apisjson.org/format/apisjson_0.19.txt">
          <front>
            <title>API Discovery Format</title>
            <author initials="K" surname="Lane">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="S" surname="Willmott">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2024" month="November" day="6"/>
          </front>
	  <annotation>Latest version available at <eref
	  target="https://apisjson.org/"
	  brackets="angle"/>.</annotation>     
        </reference>


	<xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.kelly-json-hal.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="RESTdesc" target="https://restdesc.org/about/descriptions">
          <front>
            <title>RESTdesc</title>
            <author initials="R" surname="Verborgh">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="E" surname="Mannens">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="R" surname="Van de Walle">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="T" surname="Steiner">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2025"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="WebAPIext" target="https://webapi-discovery.github.io/rfcs/rfc0001.html">
          <front>
            <title>WADG0001 WebAPI type extension</title>
            <author initials="M" surname="Ralphson" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="N" surname="Evans" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2020" month="July" day="08"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>Draft Community Group Report</refcontent>
        </reference>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8631.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>

    <section anchor="api-catalog-example-linkset">
      <name>Example API Catalog Documents</name>
      <t>This section is informative and provides and example of an API 
catalog document using the Linkset format.</t>
      <section anchor="api-catalog-example-rfc8615">
        <name>Using Linkset with Link Relations Defined in RFC 8631</name>
        <t>This example uses the Linkset format <xref target="RFC9264"/> and the following
link relations defined in <xref target="RFC8631"/>:</t>
<dl spacing="normal">
   <dt>"service-desc":</dt><dd>Used to link to a description of the API that
   is primarily intended for machine consumption (for example, the <xref
   target="OAS"/> specification, YAML, or JSON file).</dd>
            <dt>"service-doc":</dt><dd>Used to link to API documentation that is primarily
intended for human consumption (an example of human-readable
documentation is the IETF <eref target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/api/submission" brackets="angle">Internet-Draft submission API
instructions</eref>).</dd>
            <dt>"service-meta":</dt><dd>Used to link to additional metadata about the API
and is primarily intended for machine consumption.</dd>
            <dt>"status":</dt><dd>Used to link to the API status (e.g., API "health"
indication) for machine and/or human consumption.</dd>
        </dl>
        <t>Client request:</t>
        <sourcecode type="http-message"><![CDATA[
GET .well-known/api-catalog HTTP/1.1
Host: example.com
Accept: application/linkset+json
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Server response:</t>
        <sourcecode type="http-message"><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Date: Mon, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:01 GMT
Server: Apache-Coyote/1.1
Content-Type: application/linkset+json;
    profile="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9727"
]]></sourcecode>
        <sourcecode type="ison"><![CDATA[
{
 "linkset": [
  {
   "anchor": "https://developer.example.com/apis/foo_api",
   "service-desc": [
    {
     "href": "https://developer.example.com/apis/foo_api/spec",
     "type": "application/yaml"
    }
   ],
   "status": [
    {
     "href": "https://developer.example.com/apis/foo_api/status",
     "type": "application/json"
    }
   ],
   "service-doc": [
    {
     "href": "https://developer.example.com/apis/foo_api/doc",
     "type": "text/html"
    }
   ],
   "service-meta": [
    {
     "href": "https://developer.example.com/apis/foo_api/policies",
     "type": "text/xml"
    }
   ]
  },
  {
   "anchor": "https://developer.example.com/apis/bar_api",
   "service-desc": [
    {
     "href": "https://developer.example.com/apis/bar_api/spec",
     "type": "application/yaml"
    }
   ],
   "status": [
    {
     "href": "https://developer.example.com/apis/bar_api/status",
     "type": "application/json"
    }
   ],
   "service-doc": [
    {
     "href": "https://developer.example.com/apis/bar_api/doc",
     "type": "text/plain"
    }
   ]
  },
  {
   "anchor": "https://apis.example.net/apis/cantona_api",
   "service-desc": [
    {
     "href": "https://apis.example.net/apis/cantona_api/spec",
     "type": "text/n3"
    }
   ],
   "service-doc": [
    {
     "href": "https://apis.example.net/apis/cantona_api/doc",
     "type": "text/html"
    }
   ]
  }
 ]
}
]]></sourcecode>
      </section>
      <section anchor="api-catalog-example-linkset-bookmarks">
        <name>Using Linkset with Bookmarks</name>
        <t>This example also uses the Linkset format <xref target="RFC9264"/> and lists the 
API endpoints in an array of bookmarks. Each link shares the same 
context anchor (the well-known URI of the API catalog) and "item" 
<xref target="RFC9264"/> link relation (to indicate they are an item in the 
catalog). The intent is that by following a bookmark link, a 
machine client can discover the purpose and usage policy for each 
API; hence, the document targeted by the bookmark link should support 
this.</t>
        <t>Client request:</t>
        <sourcecode type="http-message"><![CDATA[
GET .well-known/api-catalog HTTP/1.1
Host: example.com
Accept: application/linkset+json
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Server response:</t>
        <sourcecode type="http-message"><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Date: Mon, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:01 GMT
Server: Apache-Coyote/1.1
Content-Type: application/linkset+json;
    profile="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9727"
]]></sourcecode>
        <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
{ "linkset":
 [
   { "anchor": "https://www.example.com/.well-known/api-catalog",
     "item": [
       {"href": "https://developer.example.com/apis/foo_api"},
       {"href": "https://developer.example.com/apis/bar_api"},
       {"href": "https://developer.example.com/apis/cantona_api"}
     ]
   }
 ]
}
]]></sourcecode>
      </section>
      <section anchor="api-catalog-other-formats">
        <name>Other API Catalog Formats</name>
        <t>A non-exhaustive list of other API catalog document formats includes:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>An APIs.json document <xref target="APIsjson"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>A RESTDesc semantic description for hypermedia APIs <xref target="RESTdesc"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>A Hypertext Application Language document <xref target="I-D.kelly-json-hal"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>An extension to the Schema.org WebAPI type <xref target="WebAPIext"/>.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="api-catalog-example-linkset-nesting">
        <name>Nesting API Catalog Links</name>
        <t>In this example, a request to the /.well-known/api-catalog URI
returns an array of links of relation type "api-catalog". This can be
useful to Publishers with a large number of APIs who wish to group
them in smaller catalogs (as described in <xref target="scalability"/>).</t>
        <t>Client request:</t>
        <sourcecode type="http-message"><![CDATA[
GET .well-known/api-catalog HTTP/1.1
Host: example.com
Accept: application/linkset+json
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Server response:</t>
        <sourcecode type="http-message"><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Date: Mon, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:01 GMT
Server: Apache-Coyote/1.1
Content-Type: application/linkset+json;
    profile="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9727"
]]></sourcecode>
        <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "linkset": [
    {
      "anchor": "https://www.example.com/.well-known/api-catalog",
      "api-catalog": [
        {
          "href": "https://apis.example.com/iot/api-catalog"
        },
        {
          "href": "https://ecommerce.example.com/api-catalog"
        },
        {
          "href": "https://developer.example.com/gaming/api-catalog"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}
]]></sourcecode>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>Thanks to <contact fullname="Jan Algermissen"/>, <contact
      fullname="Phil Archer"/>, <contact fullname="Tim Bray"/>, <contact
      fullname="Ben Bucksch"/>, <contact fullname="Sanjay Dalal"/>, <contact
      fullname="David Dong"/>, <contact fullname="Erik Kline"/>, <contact
      fullname="Mallory Knodel"/>, <contact fullname="Murray Kucherawy"/>,
      <contact fullname="Max Maton"/>, <contact fullname="Darrel Miller"/>,
      <contact fullname="Mark Nottingham"/>, <contact fullname="Roberto
      Polli"/>, <contact fullname="Joey Salazar"/>, <contact fullname="Rich
      Salz"/>, <contact fullname="Herbert Van De Sompel"/>, <contact
      fullname="Orie Steele"/>, <contact fullname="Tina Tsou"/>, <contact
      fullname="Gunter Van de Velde"/>, <contact fullname="Éric Vyncke"/>,
      and <contact fullname="Erik Wilde"/> for their reviews, suggestions, and
      support.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
