<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
 <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
 <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
 <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
 <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]> 

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  submissionType="IRTF"  category="exp"      consensus="true" docName="draft-irtf-icnrg-pathsteering-07" number="9531" ipr="trust200902" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="4" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true"  updates="" obsoletes="" version="3">

<front>
    <title abbrev="ICN Path Steering">Path Steering in Content-Centric
    Networking (CCNx) and Named Data Networking (NDN)</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9531"/>    
    <author fullname="Ilya Moiseenko" surname="I. Moiseenko">
      <organization>Apple, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Cupertino</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code/>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <phone/>
        <email>iliamo@mailbox.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Dave Oran" surname="D. Oran">
      <organization>Network Systems Research and Design</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4 Shady Hill Square</street>
          <city>Cambridge</city>
          <region>MA</region>
          <code>02138</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <phone/>
        <email>daveoran@orandom.net</email>
        </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2024" month="March"/>

    <workgroup>Information-Centric Networking</workgroup>
    <keyword>ICN</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>Path steering is a mechanism to discover paths to the producers of
      Information-Centric Networking (ICN) Content Objects and steer subsequent Interest messages along a
      previously discovered path. It has various uses, including the operation
      of state-of-the-art multi-path congestion control algorithms and for
      network measurement and management. This specification derives directly
      from the design published in "Path Switching in Content Centric and
      Named Data Networks" (4th ACM Conference on Information-Centric
      Networking) and, therefore, does not recapitulate the design
      motivations, implementation details, or evaluation of the
      scheme. However, some technical details are different, and where there
      are differences, the design documented here is to be considered
      definitive.</t>
      
      <t>This document is a product of the IRTF Information-Centric Networking
      Research Group (ICNRG). It is not an IETF product and is not an Internet
      Standard.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
 
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
       
      <t>Path steering is a mechanism to discover paths to the producers of
      ICN Content Objects and steer subsequent Interest messages along a
      previously discovered path. It has various uses, including the operation
      of state-of-the-art multi-path congestion control algorithms and for
      network measurement and management. This specification derives directly
      from the design published in <xref target="Moiseenko2017"/> and,
      therefore, does not recapitulate the design motivations, implementation
      details, or evaluation of the scheme. That publication should be
      considered a normative reference as it is not likely a reader will be
      able to understand all elements of this design without first having read
      the reference. However, some technical details are different, and where
      there are differences, the design documented here is to be considered
      definitive.</t>
            
      <t>Path discovery and subsequent path steering in ICN networks is
      facilitated by the symmetry of forward and reverse paths in the Content-Centric Networking (CCNx) and
      Named Data Networking (NDN) architectures. Path discovery is achieved by a consumer endpoint
      transmitting an ordinary Interest message and receiving a Content (Data)
      message containing an end-to-end path label constructed on the reverse
      path by the forwarding plane. Path steering is achieved by a consumer
      endpoint including a path label in the Interest message, which is
      forwarded to each nexthop through the corresponding egress interfaces in
      conjunction with Longest Name Prefix Match (LNPM) lookup in the
      Forwarding Information Base (FIB).</t>
      
      <t>This document is a product of the IRTF Information-Centric Networking
      Research Group (ICNRG). It was supported by the ICNRG participants
      during its development and through Research Group Last Call. It has
      received detailed review by experts in both the CCNx and NDN
      communities.</t>

      
      <section anchor="experimenting">
      	<name>Path Steering as an Experimental Extension to ICN Protocol Architectures</name>
      	<t>There are a number of important use cases to justify extending ICN architectures such as <xref target="RFC8569" format="default">CCNx</xref> or <xref target="NDN" format="default">NDN</xref> to provide these capabilities. These are summarized as follows:</t>

	<ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Support the discovery, monitoring, and troubleshooting of
          multi-path network connectivity, based on names and name
          prefixes. Analogous functions have been shown to be a crucial
          operational capability in multicast and multi-path topologies for
          IP. The canonical tools are the well-known <em>traceroute</em> and
          <em>ping</em>. For point-to-multipoint MPLS, the more recent MPLS <xref
          target="RFC8029" format="default">traceroute</xref> protocol is
          used. Equivalent diagnostic functions have been defined for CCNx
          through the <xref target="RFC9508" format="default">ICN Ping</xref>
          and <xref target="RFC9507" format="default">ICN Traceroute</xref>
          specifications; both of which are capable of exploiting path
          steering, if available.</li>
        	
          <li>Perform accurate online measurement of network performance,
          which generally requires multiple consecutive packets to follow the
          same path under control of an application.</li>
        	
          <li>Improve the performance and flexibility of multi-path congestion
          control algorithms. Congestion control schemes, such as <xref
          target="Mahdian2016" format="default"/> and <xref target="Song2018"
          format="default"/>, depend on the ability of a consumer to explicitly
          steer packets onto individual paths in a multi-path and/or
          multi-destination topology.</li>
        	
          <li>Allow a consumer endpoint to mitigate content poisoning attacks by
          directing its Interests onto the network paths that bypass poisoned
          caches.</li>
      	</ul>

      	<t>The path discovery machinery described here may (and likely will)
      	discover paths with varying properties. <xref target="RFC9217"/>
      	discusses a number of open questions in path-aware networking, among
      	which is how to assess and exploit paths having different
      	properties. Experimenting with ICN path steering may be helpful in
      	further elucidating these questions and perhaps shedding light on
      	which path properties are most useful for the use cases cited
      	above.</t>
      	
      	<t>One nuance compared to other path-aware networking approaches is
      	that ICN path steering piggybacks path discovery on the base ICN data
      	exchange rather than having a separate path advertisement or discovery
      	mechanism. That means when the recorded path comes back in an ICN Data
      	message response, the properties of the path are known only implicitly
      	to the consumer as opposed to being explicitly labeled.  That makes
      	the question of what properties a consumer uses to choose a path one
      	of observation or measurement rather than advance selection based on
      	an explicit, advertised property (e.g., <xref
      	target="I-D.dekater-panrg-scion-overview">SCION</xref>).</t>
      	
      	<t>The utility and overall technical quality of this path steering
      	capability can be assessed by how well it enables the above use cases
      	and what performance and robustness effects it has on the underlying
      	ICN protocols and their use in various applications. A few of the open
      	questions that should be addressed through experimentation with path
      	steering include:</t>
      	<ul spacing="normal">
      	  <li>How much more accurate and useful are measurements of RTT,
      	  packet loss, etc. through ping and traceroute when utilizing path
      	  steering?</li>
      	  <li>How much is the performance and robustness of multi-path
      	  forwarding enhanced by the use of this explicit path steering
      	  capability?</li>
      	</ul>

	  </section>
	        
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
        NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document
        are to be interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref
        target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they
        appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section>
      	<name>Terminology</name>
      	<t>This document uses the general ICN terms that are defined in <xref
      	target="RFC8793"/>. In addition, we define the following terms
      	specific to path steering:</t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
            <dt>Path Discovery:</dt>
            <dd>The process of sending an Interest message requesting discovery of a
            path and, if successful, receiving a Data message containing a path label
            for the path the corresponding Interest traversed.</dd>
            
            <dt>Path Steering:</dt>
            <dd>The process of sending an Interest message containing the path
            label of a previously discovered path so that the forwarders
            use that path when forwarding that particular Interest
            message.</dd>
            
            <dt>Path Label:</dt>
            <dd>An optional field in the packet indicating a particular path
            from a consumer to either a producer or a forwarder cache that
            can respond with the requested item. In an Interest message, the
            path label gets built up hop by hop as the Interest traverses a
            path. In a Data message, the path label carries the full path
            information back to the consumer for use in one or more subsequent
            Interest messages.</dd>
            
            <dt>Nexthop Label:</dt>
            <dd>One entry in a path label representing the next hop for the
            corresponding forwarder to use when a path-steered Interest
            message arrives at that forwarder. A sequence of Nexthop Labels
            constitutes a full path label.</dd>
        </dl>

    </section>

    </section>
    <section anchor="design" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Essential Elements of ICN Path Discovery and Path Steering</name>

      <t>We elucidate the design using <xref target="RFC8569"
      format="default">CCNx semantics</xref> and extend its <xref
      target="RFC8609" format="default">CCNx Message Formats</xref> defined in Section
      <xref target="RFC8609" section="3.2" sectionFormat="bare"/>. While the terminology
      is slightly different, this design can also be applied to NDN by
      extending its bespoke <xref target="NDNTLV" format="default">packet
      encodings</xref> (see <xref target="NDN-encoding"
      format="default"/>).</t>

      <section anchor="discovery" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Path Discovery</name>

        <t><em>End-to-end Path Discovery</em> for CCNx is achieved by creating
        a <em>path label</em> and placing it as a hop-by-hop TLV in a CCNx
        Content (Data) message. The path label is constructed hop by hop as
        the message traverses the reverse path of transit CCNx forwarders, as
        shown in the first example in <xref
        target="pathsteeringoverview"/>. The path label is updated by adding
        the Nexthop Label of the interface at which
        the Content (Data) message has arrived to the existing path label. Eventually, when the
        Content (Data) message arrives at the consumer, the path label
        identifies the complete path the Content (Data) message took to reach
        the consumer. As shown in the second example in <xref
        target="pathsteeringoverview"/>, when multiple paths are available,
        subsequent Interests may be able to discover additional paths by
        omitting a path steering TLV and obtaining a new path label on the
        returning Interest.</t>


          


        <figure anchor="pathsteeringoverview">
          <name>Basic Example of Path Discovery and Steering</name>
          <artwork name="Path Discovery 1" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
          Discover and use first path:

               Consumer                  Interest 1  ___  Interest 2
                  |                          |        ^       |
                  |                          |        |       |
                  |                          |        |       |
             Forwarder 1                     v        |       V
                  | (nexthop 1)          (nexthop 1)  ^   (nexthop 1)
                  |                          |        |       |
                  |                          |        |       |
             Forwarder 2                     v        |       v
     (nexthop 3) / \ (nexthop 2)         (nexthop 2)  ^   (nexthop 2)
                /   \                        |        |       |
               /     \                       |        |       |
              /       \                      |        |       |
             /         \                     |        |       |
            /           \                    |        |       |
      Forwarder 4    Forwarder 3             v        |       v
(nexthop 5)\             / (nexthop 4)   (nexthop 4)  ^   (nexthop 4)
            \           /                    |        |       |
             \         /                     |        |       |
              \       /                      |        |       |
               \     /                       |        |       |
                \   /                        |        |       |
                 \ /                         v        |       v
               Producer                     ___     Data 1   ___
                 or
            Content Store
      ]]></artwork>

	  <artwork name="Path Discovery 2" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
	  
          Discover and use second path:

               Consumer                  Interest 3  ___  Interest 4
                  |                          |        ^       |
                  |                          |        |       |
                  |                          |        |       |
             Forwarder 1                     v        |       V
                  | (nexthop 1)          (nexthop 1)  ^   (nexthop 1)
                  |                          |        |       |
                  |                          |        |       |
             Forwarder 2                     v        |       v
     (nexthop 3) / \ (nexthop 2)         (nexthop 3)  ^   (nexthop 3)
                /   \                        |        |       |
               /     \                       |        |       |
              /       \                      |        |       |
             /         \                     |        |       |
            /           \                    |        |       |
      Forwarder 4    Forwarder 3             v        |       v
(nexthop 5)\             / (nexthop 4)   (nexthop 5)  ^   (nexthop 5)
            \           /                    |        |       |
             \         /                     |        |       |
              \       /                      |        |       |
               \     /                       |        |       |
                \   /                        |        |       |
                 \ /                         v        |       v
               Producer                     ___     Data 2   ___
                 or
            Content Store
	    ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
		
	</section>

      <section anchor="steering" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Path Steering</name>
        <t>Due to the symmetry of forward and reverse paths in CCNx, a
        consumer application can reuse a discovered path label to fetch the
        same or a similar (e.g., next chunk, next Application Data Unit, or
        next pointer in a <xref target="I-D.irtf-icnrg-flic"
        format="default">Manifest</xref>) Content (Data) message over the
        discovered network path. This <em>path steering</em> is achieved by
        processing the Interest message's path label at each transit ICN
        forwarder and forwarding the Interest through the specified nexthop
        among those identified as feasible by LNPM FIB lookup (<xref
        target="pathsteeringdataplane"/>).</t>

        <figure anchor="pathsteeringdataplane">
          <name>Path Steering CCNx/NDN Data Plane</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
----------------------------------------------------------------------
                              FORWARD PATH
----------------------------------------------------------------------

Interest +---------+  +-----+ (path label) +--------+ (match) Interest
-------->| Content |->| PIT | ------------>| Label  |---------------->
         |  Store  |  +-----+              | Lookup |
         +---------+   | \ (no path label) +--------+
          |            |  \                    |\(path label mismatch)
Data      |            |   \                   | \
<---------+            v    \                  |  \
                  aggregate  \                 |   \
                              \                |    \
                               \               |     +-----+  Interest
                                +--------------|---->| FIB | -------->
                                               |     +-----+
InterestReturn (NACK)                          v        | (no route)
<----------------------------------------------+<-------+


----------------------------------------------------------------------
                              REVERSE PATH
----------------------------------------------------------------------

InterestReturn(NACK)  +-----+(update path label)  InterestReturn(NACK)
<---------------------|     |<----------------------------------------
                      |     |
Data   +---------+    | PIT |  (update path label)                Data
<------| Content |<---|     |<----------------------------------------
       |  Store  |    |     |
       +---------+    +-----+
                         |
                         | (no match)
                         v
      ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="error-processing" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Handling Path Steering Errors</name>
        <t>Over time, the state of interfaces and the FIB on forwarders may
        change such that, at any particular forwarder, a given nexthop is no
        longer valid for a given prefix. In this case, the path label will
        point to a now-invalid nexthop. This is detected by failure to find a
        match between the decoded nexthop ID and the nexthops of the FIB entry
        after LNPM FIB lookup.</t>
        
        <t>On detecting an invalid path label, the forwarder
        <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> respond to the Interest with an
        InterestReturn. Therefore, we define a new <em>invalid path
        label</em> response code for the InterestReturn message and include
        the current path label as a hop-by-hop header. Each transit forwarder
        processing the InterestReturn message updates the path label in the
        same manner as Content (Data) messages so that the consumer receiving
        the InterestReturn (NACK) can easily identify which path label is no
        longer valid.</t>
        
	<t>A consumer may alternatively request that a forwarder detecting the
	inconsistency forward the Interest by means of normal LNPM FIB lookup
	rather than return an error. The consumer endpoint, if it cares,
	can keep enough information about outstanding Interests to determine
	if the path label sent with the Interest fails to match the path label
	in the corresponding returned Content (Data) and use that information
	to replace stale path labels. It does so by setting the FALLBACK_MODE
	flag of the path label TLV in its Interest message.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="Interest-Aggregation">
      	<name>Interactions with Interest Aggregation</name>

      	<t>If two or more Interests matching the same Pending Interest Table
      	(PIT) entry arrive at a forwarder, under current behavior, they will
      	be aggregated whether or not they carry identical path label
      	TLVs. This may or may not be appropriate. For example, multiple
      	Interests with different modes (e.g., one with DISCOVERY_MODE and one
      	without) will get aggregated; therefore, the behavior of the forwarder
      	might be dependent on the arrival order of those Interests. In
      	particular:</t>
      	<ul spacing="normal">
      	  <li>If the DISCOVERY_MODE Interest arrives first, it will be
      	  forwarded and potentially discover a new path, while the other
      	  Interest will be aggregated.  If that Interest carried no path
      	  label, its behavior is essentially unchanged, but if it carried a
      	  path label without specifying DISCOVERY_MODE, the consumer's intent
      	  for the Interest to traverse the specified path will be ignored, and
      	  it is indeterminate if the chosen path will actually be used.</li>
      	  <li>If the two Interests arrive in the reverse order, the DISCOVERY
      	  MODE Interest will be aggregated, and the consumer issuing it will
      	  not achieve its desire to discover a new path.</li>
      	</ul>

      	<t>Multiple Interests intended to discover paths (i.e., by carrying
      	the DISCOVERY_MODE flag defined in <xref target="Path-label-types"/>)
      	might also be aggregated by a forwarder. This limits the ability to
      	discover multiple paths in parallel and, instead, must be discovered
      	incrementally in subsequent exchanges. In other words, aggregated
      	Interests will all discover only one single path carried by one single
      	Data packet. This has implications for management applications, like
      	<xref target="RFC9507">traceroute</xref>, which would likely perform
      	much better if they discover paths in parallel. Hence, when employing path steering, it is
      	<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that such
      	applications craft their Interests with unique name suffixes in order
      	to avoid being aggregated.</t>

	<aside><t>While path steering still operates correctly if DISCOVERY
	MODE Interests are aggregated, after further experimentation, it may be
	appropriate to advise that a forwarder:</t>
	<ul spacing="normal">
	  <li><bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> aggregate Interests carrying different
	  path labels and</li>
	  <li><bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> apply a rate limit to DISCOVERY_MODE
	  Interests in order to limit redundant traffic.</li>
	</ul>
	</aside>

	  </section>

      <section anchor="label-encoding" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>How to Represent the Path Label</name>

        <t><xref target="Moiseenko2017" format="default"/> presents various
        options for how to represent a path label, with different trade-offs in
        flexibility, performance, and space efficiency. For this
        specification, we choose the <em>polynomial encoding</em>, which
        achieves reasonable space efficiency at the cost of establishing a
        hard limit on the length of paths that can be represented.</t>
        <t>The polynomial encoding utilizes a fixed-size bit array. Each
        transit ICN forwarder is allocated a fixed-size portion of the bit
        array. This design allocates 12 bits (i.e., 4095 as a <em>generator
        polynomial</em>) to each intermediate ICN forwarder. This matches the
        scalability of today's commercial routers that support up to 4096
        physical and logical interfaces and usually do not have more than a
        few hundred active ones.</t>

        <figure>
          <name>Fixed-Size Path Label</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
+------------------------------------------------------------------+
|                      path label bitmap                           |
+----------+-----------------+-----------------+-------------------+
|   index  |  Nexthop Label  |  Nexthop Label  |                   |
+----------+-----------------+-----------------+-------------------+
|<- 8bit ->|<---- 12bit ---->|<---- 12bit ---->|<----------------->|
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>A forwarder that receives a Content (Data) message encodes the Nexthop Label in the next available slot and increments the label index. Conversely, a forwarder that receives an Interest message reads the current Nexthop Label and decrements the label index. Therefore, the extra computation required at each hop to forward either an Interest or Content Object message with a path label is minimized and constitutes a fairly trivial additional overhead compared to FIB lookup and other required operations.</t>
        
        <t>This approach results in individual path label TLV instances being
        of fixed pre-computed size.  While this places a hard upper bound on
        the maximum number of network hops that can be represented, this is
        not a significant practical problem in NDN and CCNx, since the size
        can be preset during Content (Data) message encoding based on the
        exact number of network hops traversed by the Interest message. Even
        long paths of 24 hops will fit in a path label bitmap of 36 bytes if
        the Nexthop Label is encoded in 12 bits.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="encoding" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Mapping to CCNx and NDN Packet Encodings</name>
      <section anchor="Path-label-types" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Path Label TLV</name>
        <t> A path label TLV is the tuple: {[Flags], [Path Label Hop Count],
        [Nexthop Label], [path label bitmap]}.</t>

        <table anchor="pathlabelflags" align="left">
          <name>Path Label Flags</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="center">Flag</th>
              <th align="center">Value (hex)</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">DISCOVERY_MODE</td>
              <td align="center">0x00</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">FALLBACK_MODE</td>
              <td align="center">0x01</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">STRICT_MODE</td>
              <td align="center">0x02</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
            	<td align="center">Unassigned</td>
            	<td align="center">0x03-0xFF</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>The Path Label Hop Count (PLHC) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be incremented
        by NDN and CCNx forwarders if the Interest packet carries a path label
        and the DISCOVERY_MODE flag is set. A producer node or a forwarder with a
        cached Data packet <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the PLHC in calculation of a
        path label bitmap size that is suitable for encoding the entire path to the
        consumer. The PLHC <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero in newly created
        Data or InterestReturn (NACK) packets. A consumer node
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reuse the PLHC together with the path label bitmap
        (PLB) in order to correctly forward the Interest(s) along the
        corresponding network path.</t>
        
        <t>If an NDN or CCNx forwarder supports path labeling, the Nexthop
        Label <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be used to determine the correct egress
        interface for an Interest packet carrying either the FALLBACK_MODE or the
        STRICT_MODE flag. If any particular NDN or CCNx forwarder is
        configured to decrypt path labels of Interest packets (see <xref
        target="security" format="title"/>), then the forwarder
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>:
        </t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
          <li>decrypt the path label with its own symmetric key,</li>
          <li>update the Nexthop Label with outermost label in the path
          label,</li>
          <li>decrement the PLHC, and</li>
          <li>remove the outermost label from the path label.</li>
        </ol>
        
        <t>If any particular NDN or CCNx forwarder is NOT configured to
        decrypt path labels of Interest packets, then path label decryption
        <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be performed.</t>
        
        <t> The Nexthop Label <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored by NDN and CCNx
        forwarders if it is present in Data or InterestReturn (NACK) packets. If
        any particular NDN or CCNx forwarder is configured to encrypt path
        labels of Data and InterestReturn (NACK) packets (see <xref
        target="security" format="title"/>), then the forwarder
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> encrypt the existing path label with its own symmetric
        key, append the Nexthop Label of the ingress interface to the path
        label, and increment the PLHC. If any particular NDN or CCNx forwarder is
        NOT configured to encrypt path labels of Interest packets, then path
        label encryption <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be performed.</t>
        
        <t>NDN and CCNx forwarders <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> fall back to Longest
        Name Prefix Match (LNPM) FIB lookup if an Interest packet carries an
        invalid Nexthop Label and the FALLBACK_MODE flag is set.</t>
        
        <t>CCNx forwarders <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> respond with an InterestReturn
        packet specifying a T_RETURN_INVALID_PATH_LABEL code if the Interest
        packet carries an invalid path label and the STRICT_MODE flag is set.
	This is a new InterestReturn code defined herein (see <xref target="IANA"/> for the value allocation).</t>
        
        <t>CCNx forwarders <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> respond with an InterestReturn packet specifying the existing T_RETURN_MALFORMED_INTEREST code if the Interest packet carries a path label TLV with both the FALLBACK_MODE and STRICT_MODE flags set.</t>
        
      </section>
      <section anchor="CCNx-encoding" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Path Label Encoding for CCNx</name>
        <t>Path label is an optional hop-by-hop header TLV that can be present in CCNx Interest, InterestReturn, and Content Object packets.</t>

        <figure>
          <name>Path Label Hop-by-Hop Header TLV for CCNx</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+---------------+---------------+---------------+---------------+
|         T_PATH_LABEL          |          Length + 4           |
+---------------+---------------+---------------+---------------+
|     Flags     |  Path Label   |        Nexthop Label          |
|               |  Hop Count    |                               |
+---------------+---------------+---------------+---------------+
/                                                               /
/               Path label bitmap (Length octets)               /
/                                                               /
+---------------+---------------+---------------+---------------+
      ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="NDN-encoding" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Path Label Encoding for NDN</name>

        <t>Path label is an optional TLV for NDN Interest and Data packets.
        It is carried in the <xref target="NDNLPv2">NDN Link Adaptation
        Protocol</xref>, which is used to wrap NDN packets for carriage over
        various link layer protocols. NDNLPv2 was chosen over the NDN packet
        itself since it can carry hop-by-hop information that potentially
        mutates at each hop and, therefore, cannot be included in the secured
        hash computation or the signature of NDN packets. Further, it can be
        used instead of the existing <tt>NextHopFaceId</tt> TLV since it not
        only can specify the single outgoing face for a consumer but manages
        the selection and forwarding over an entire path. The path label TLV
        in NDNLPv2 is defined below:</t>
       
        <figure>
          <name>Path Label TLV for NDN</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
PathLabel         = PATH-LABEL-TYPE TLV-LENGTH
                    PathLabelFlags
                    PathLabelBitmap

PathLabelFlags    = PATH-LABEL-FLAGS-TYPE
                    TLV-LENGTH ; == 1
                    OCTET

NexthopLabel      = PATH-LABEL-NEXTHOP-LABEL-TYPE
                    TLV-LENGTH ; == 2
                    2 OCTET

PathLabelHopCount = PATH-LABEL-HOP-COUNT-TYPE
                    TLV-LENGTH ; == 1
                    OCTET

PathLabelBitmap   = PATH-LABEL-BITMAP-TYPE
                    TLV-LENGTH ; == 64
                    64 OCTET
      ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <table anchor="pathlabelTLVs" align="left">
          <name>TLV-TYPE Number Assignments for NDN</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="center">Flag</th>
              <th align="center">(Suggested) Value (hex)</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">T_PATH_LABEL</td>
              <td align="center">0x0A</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">T_PATH_LABEL_FLAGS</td>
              <td align="center">0x0B</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">T_PATH_LABEL_BITMAP</td>
              <td align="center">0x0D</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">T_PATH_LABEL_NEXTHOP_LABEL</td>
              <td align="center">0x0E</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">T_PATH_LABEL_HOP_COUNT</td>
              <td align="center">0x0F</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>
    </section>

<section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>IANA has made the following assignments:</t>
      
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
        <li>The value 0x000A has been assigned to
        T_PATH_LABEL in the "CCNx Hop-by-Hop Types" registry,
        established by <xref target="RFC8609"/>.</li>
        <li>The value 0x0A has been assigned to
        T_RETURN_INVALID_PATH_LABEL in the "CCNx Interest Return Code
        Types" registry, established by <xref target="RFC8609"/>.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="security"><name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>A path is invalidated by renumbering one or more Nexthop Labels. A malicious
      consumer can attempt to mount an attack by transmitting Interests with
      path labels that differ only in a single now-invalid Nexthop Label in
      order to <em>brute-force</em> a valid Nexthop Label. If such an attack
      succeeds, a malicious consumer would be capable of steering Interests
      over a network path that may not match the paths computed by the routing
      algorithm or learned adaptively by the forwarders.</t>
      
      <t>When a label lookup fails, by default, an <em>invalid path label</em>
      InterestReturn (NACK) message is returned to the consumer. This
      contains a path label identical to the one included in the corresponding
      Interest message. Therefore, a malicious consumer can analyze the
      message's Hop Count field to infer which specific Nexthop Label had
      failed and direct an attack to influence path steering at that hop. This
      threat can be mitigated by the following countermeasures:</t>
      
      <ul spacing="normal">

        <li>A Nexthop Label that is larger in size is harder to crack. If Nexthop
        Labels are not allocated in a predictable fashion by the routers,
        brute-forcing a 32-bit Nexthop Label requires on average O(2<sup>31</sup>)
        Interests. However, this specification uses Nexthop Labels with much
        less entropy (12 bits), so depending on computational hardness is not
        workable.</li>
        
        <li>An ICN forwarder can periodically update Nexthop Labels to limit
        the maximum lifetime of paths. It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that
        forwarders update path labels at least every few minutes.</li>
        
        <li>A void Hop Count field in an <em>invalid path label</em>
        InterestReturn (NACK) message would not give out the information on
        which a specific Nexthop Label had failed. An attacker might need to
        brute-force all Nexthop Labels in all combinations. However, some
        useful diagnostic capability is lost by obscuring the hop count. For
        example, the locus of routing churn is harder to pin down through
        analysis of path-steered pings or traceroutes. A forwarder
        <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> choose to invalidate the hop count in addition to
        changing Nexthop Labels periodically as described above.</li>
      </ul>

      <t>Because ICN forwarders maintain per-face state and forwarding state
      for Interest messages, state inflation attacks are a general
      concern. The addition of path steering capabilities in Interest and Data
      messages does not, however, constitute a meaningful increase in
      susceptibility to such attacks. This is because:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
	
	<li>The labels that identify each forwarding face is state O(number of
	faces) and constitutes a small increase to the existing state needed
	to represent a face.</li>
	<li>Interest message data is placed in the PIT. The path steering
	header does, in fact, inflate the size of the Interest message and,
	hence, the PIT state but not by an amount that is a concern. The
	forwarder needs to protect against state inflation attacks on the PIT
	in general, and an attacker can mount one just as or more easily by
	issuing Interests with long names and/or by including Interest payload
	data.</li>
	  </ul>
      
      <t>ICN protocols can be susceptible to a variety of cache poisoning
      attacks, where a colluding consumer and producer arrange for bogus
      content (with either invalid or inappropriate signatures) to populate
      forwarder caches. These are generally confined to on-path attacks. It is
      also theoretically possible to launch a similar attack without a
      cooperating producer such that the caches of on-path routers become
      poisoned with the content from off-path routers (i.e., physical
      connectivity but no route in a FIB for a given prefix). We estimate
      that, without any prior knowledge of the network topology, the
      complexity of this type of attack is in the ballpark of
      Breadth-First-Search and Depth-First-Search algorithms with the
      additional burden of transmitting 2<sup>31</sup> Interests in order to
      crack a Nexthop Label on each hop.  A relatively short periodic update
      of Nexthop Labels, together with heuristics implemented in the ICN
      forwarder to foil <em>label scans</em>, may successfully mitigate this
      type of attack.</t>
	
      <section anchor="encryptpathlabel">
        <name>Cryptographic Protection of a Path Label</name>
        <t>If the countermeasures listed above do not provide sufficient
        protection against malicious mis-steering of Interests, the path label
        can be made opaque to the consumer endpoint via hop-by-hop symmetric
        cryptography applied to the path labels (<xref
        target="pathlabelcryptoprocess"/>). This method is viable due to the
        symmetry of forward and reverse paths in CCNx and NDN architectures
        combined with ICN path steering requiring only reads and writes of the
        topmost Nexthop Label (i.e., active Nexthop Label) in the path
        label. This way, a path-steering-capable ICN forwarder receiving a
        Content (Data) message encrypts the current path label with its own
        non-shared symmetric key prior to adding a new Nexthop Label to the
        path label. The Content (Data) message is forwarded downstream with an
        unencrypted topmost (i.e., active) Nexthop Label and the remaining
        encrypted content of the path label. As a result, a consumer endpoint
        receives a Content (Data) message with a unique path label exposing
        only the topmost Nexthop Label as cleartext. A path steering forwarder
        receiving an Interest message performs label lookup using the topmost
        Nexthop Label, decrypts the path label with its own non-shared
        symmetric key, and forwards the message upstream.</t>
        
        <t>Cryptographic protection of a path label does not require any key negotiation among ICN forwarders and is no more expensive than Media Access Control Security (MACsec) or IPsec. It is also quite possible that strict hop-by-hop path label encryption is not necessary and path label encryption only on the border routers of the trusted administrative or routing domains may suffice.</t>
        
        <figure anchor="pathlabelcryptoprocess">
          <name>Path Label Protection with Hop-by-Hop Symmetric Cryptography</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                            Producer
                            |      ^
                            |      |
     Path Label TLV         |      |           Path Label TLV
+-----------------------+   |      |     +-----------------------+
|nexthop label=456      |   v      |     |nexthop label=456      |
|encrypted path label={}|  Forwarder 3   |encrypted path label={}|
+-----------------------+   |      ^     +-----------------------+
                            |      |
path label is encrypted     |      |     path label is decrypted
with Forwarder 3            |      |     with Forwarder 3
symmetric key               |      |     symmetric key
                            |      |
                            |      |
                            |      |
                            |      |
                            |      |
     Path Label TLV         |      |           Path Label TLV
+-----------------------+   |      |     +-----------------------+
|nexthop label=634      |   v      |     |nexthop label=634      |
|encrypted path label=  |  Forwarder 2   |encrypted path label=  |
| {456}                 |   |      ^     | {456}                 |
+-----------------------+   |      |     +-----------------------+
                            |      |
path label is encrypted     |      |     path label is decrypted
with Forwarder 2            |      |     with Forwarder 2
symmetric key               |      |     symmetric key
                            |      |
                            |      |
                            |      |
                            |      |
                            |      |
     Path Label TLV         |      |           Path Label TLV
+-----------------------+   |      |     +-----------------------+
|nexthop label=912      |   v      |     |nexthop label=912      |
|encrypted path label=  |  Forwarder 1   |encrypted path label=  |
| {634, encrypted path  |   |      ^     | {634, encrypted path  |
| label {456}}          |   |      |     | label {456}}          |
+-----------------------+   |      |     +-----------------------+
                            |      |
path label is encrypted     |      |     path label is decrypted
with Forwarder 1            |      |     with Forwarder 1
symmetric key               |      |     symmetric key
                            |      |
                            |      |
                            |      |
                            |      |
                            v      |
                            Consumer
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

<back>

<displayreference target="I-D.irtf-icnrg-flic" to="FLIC"/>
<displayreference target="I-D.dekater-panrg-scion-overview" to="SCION"/>

    <references><name>References</name>
      <references><name>Normative References</name>

   <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8569.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8609.xml"/>


        <reference anchor="Moiseenko2017" target="https://conferences.sigcomm.org/acm-icn/2017/proceedings/icn17-2.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>Path Switching in Content Centric and Named Data Networks</title>
            <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/3125719.3125721"/>
            <author surname="Moiseenko" initials="I."/>
            <author surname="Oran" initials="D."/>
            <date year="2017" month="September"/>
          </front>
	  <refcontent>Proceedings of the 4th ACM Conference on
	  Information-Centric Networking, Pages 66-76</refcontent>
	  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/3125719.3125721"/>
        </reference>


      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

   <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8029.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8793.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9217.xml"/>

<reference anchor="RFC9508" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9508">
<front>
<title>Information-Centric Networking (ICN) Ping Protocol Specification</title>
<author initials='S' surname='Mastorakis' fullname='Spyridon Mastorakis'>
<organization />
</author>
<author initials='D' surname='Oran' fullname='David Oran'>
<organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Gibson' fullname='Jim Gibson'>
<organization />
</author>
<author initials='I' surname='Moiseenko' fullname='Ilya Moiseenko'>
<organization />
</author>
<author initials='R' surname='Droms' fullname='Ralph Droms'>
<organization />
</author>
<date year='2024' month='March'/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9508"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9508"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC9507" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9507">
<front>
<title>Information-Centric Networking (ICN) Traceroute Protocol Specification</title>
<author initials='S' surname='Mastorakis' fullname='Spyridon Mastorakis'>
<organization />
</author>
<author initials='D' surname='Oran' fullname='David Oran'>
<organization />
</author>
<author initials='I' surname='Moiseenko' fullname='Ilya Moiseenko'>
<organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Gibson' fullname='Jim Gibson'>
<organization />
</author>
<author initials='R' surname='Droms' fullname='Ralph Droms'>
<organization />
</author>
<date year='2024' month='March'/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9507"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9507"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="I-D.irtf-icnrg-flic">
<front>
<title>File-Like ICN Collections (FLIC)</title>
<author fullname="Christian Tschudin" initials="C." surname="Tschudin">
<organization>University of Basel</organization>
</author>
<author fullname="Christopher A. Wood" initials="C. A." surname="Wood">
<organization>Cloudflare</organization>
</author>
<author fullname="Marc E. Mosko" initials="M." surname="Mosko">
<organization>PARC, Inc.</organization>
</author>
<author fullname="David Oran" initials="D." surname="Oran" role="editor">
<organization>Network Systems Research &amp; Design</organization>
</author>
<date day="22" month="October" year="2023"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-irtf-icnrg-flic-05"/>
</reference>

	
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.dekater-panrg-scion-overview.xml"/>
        
        <reference anchor="Mahdian2016" target="http://conferences2.sigcomm.org/acm-icn/2016/proceedings/p1-mahdian.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>MIRCC: Multipath-aware ICN Rate-based Congestion Control</title>
            <author surname="Mahdian" initials="M."/>
            <author surname="Arianfar" initials="S."/>
            <author surname="Gibson" initials="J."/>
            <author surname="Oran" initials="D."/>
            <date month="September" year="2016"/>
          </front>
	  <refcontent>Proceedings of the 3rd ACM Conference on
	  Information-Centric Networking, Pages 1-10</refcontent>
	  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2984356.2984365"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="Song2018" target="https://conferences.sigcomm.org/acm-icn/2018/proceedings/icn18-final62.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>SMIC: Subflow-level Multi-path Interest Control for Information Centric Networking</title>
            <author surname="Song" initials="J."/>
            <author surname="Lee" initials="M."/>
            <author surname="Kwon" initials="T."/>
            <date month="September" year="2018"/>
          </front>
	  <refcontent>Proceedings of the 5th ACM Conference on Information-Centric Networking, Pages 77-87</refcontent>
	  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/3267955.3267971"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="NDN" target="https://named-data.net/project/execsummary/">
          <front>
            <title>Named Data Networking: Executive Summary</title>
            <author>
	      <organization>NDN</organization>
	    </author>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="NDNLPv2" target="https://redmine.named-data.net/projects/nfd/wiki/NDNLPv2">
          <front>
            <title>NDNLPv2</title>
            <author>
	      <organization>NFD</organization>
	    </author>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="NDNTLV" target="https://named-data.net/doc/NDN-packet-spec/current/">
          <front>
            <title>NDN Packet Format Specification v0.3</title>
	    <author>
	      <organization>NDN</organization>
	    </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>

  </back>

</rfc>
