<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-lamps-rfc8398bis-05" number="9598" category="std" consensus="true" submissionType="IETF" obsoletes="8398" updates="5280" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3" xml:lang="en">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="I18N Mail Addresses in X.509 Certificates">Internationalized Email Addresses in X.509 Certificates</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9598"/>
    <author fullname="Alexey Melnikov">
      <organization>Isode Ltd</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>14 Castle Mews</street>
          <city>Hampton, Middlesex</city>
          <code>TW12 2NP</code>
          <country>United Kingdom</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Alexey.Melnikov@isode.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Wei Chuang">
      <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheater Parkway</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>weihaw@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Corey Bonnell">
      <organization>DigiCert</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Pittsburgh</city>
          <region>PA</region>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>corey.bonnell@digicert.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2024" month="May"/>

    <area>SEC</area>
    <workgroup>lamps</workgroup>

    <keyword>EAI</keyword>
    <keyword>PKIX</keyword>
    <keyword>email address</keyword>
    <abstract>


<t>This document defines a new name form for inclusion in the otherName
field of an X.509 Subject Alternative Name and Issuer Alternative
Name extension that allows a certificate subject to be associated
with an internationalized email address.</t>
      <t>This document updates RFC 5280 and obsoletes RFC 8398.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t><xref target="RFC5280"/> defines the rfc822Name subjectAltName name type for
representing email addresses as described in <xref target="RFC5321"/>.  The syntax
of rfc822Name is restricted to a subset of US-ASCII characters and
thus can't be used to represent internationalized email addresses
<xref target="RFC6531"/>.  This document defines a new otherName variant to
represent internationalized email addresses.  In addition, this
document requires all email address domains in X.509 certificates to
conform to IDNA2008 <xref target="RFC5890"/>.</t>
      <t>This document obsoletes <xref target="RFC8398"/>. The primary motivation of this document is to simplify the encoding of domain labels
found in the domain part of internationalized email addresses. In
particular, <xref target="RFC8398"/> specifies that domain labels are conditionally
encoded using either A-labels or U-labels. This specification simplifies
encoding and processing of domain labels by mandating that the A-label
representation be used in all cases.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="conventions-and-definitions">
      <name>Conventions Used in This Document</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be
    interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref
    target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as
    shown here.
        </t>
</section>
    <section anchor="name-definitions">
      <name>Name Definitions</name>
      <t>The GeneralName structure <xref target="RFC5280"/> supports many
different name forms including otherName for extensibility.  This
section specifies the SmtpUTF8Mailbox name form of otherName so that
internationalized email addresses can appear in the subjectAltName of
a certificate, the issuerAltName of a certificate, or anywhere else
that GeneralName is used.</t>
      <sourcecode type="ASN.1"><![CDATA[
id-on-SmtpUTF8Mailbox OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-on 9 }

SmtpUTF8Mailbox ::= UTF8String (SIZE (1..MAX))
-- SmtpUTF8Mailbox conforms to Mailbox as specified
-- in Section 3.3 of RFC 6531. Additionally, all domain
-- labels included in the SmtpUTF8Mailbox value are
-- encoded as LDH labels. In particular, domain labels
-- are not encoded as U-labels and instead are encoded
-- using their A-label representation.
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>When the subjectAltName (or issuerAltName) extension contains an
internationalized email address with a non-ASCII Local-part, the
address <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be stored in the SmtpUTF8Mailbox name form of otherName.
The format of SmtpUTF8Mailbox is a modified version of the
internationalized Mailbox that was defined in 
<xref target="RFC6531" sectionFormat="of" section="3.3"/>, which was derived from Mailbox as defined in 
<xref target="RFC5321" sectionFormat="of" section="4.1.2"/>.  <xref target="RFC6531"/> defines the following ABNF rules for Mailbox
whose parts are modified for internationalization: <tt>Local-part</tt>,
<tt>Dot-string</tt>, <tt>Quoted-string</tt>, <tt>QcontentSMTP</tt>, <tt>Domain</tt>, and <tt>Atom</tt>.
In particular, <tt>Local-part</tt> was updated to also support
UTF8-non-ascii.  UTF8-non-ascii was described by 
<xref target="RFC6532" sectionFormat="of" section="3.1"/>. Also, domain was extended to support U-labels, as defined
in <xref target="RFC5890"/>.</t>
      <t>This document further refines internationalized Mailbox ABNF rules as
described in <xref target="RFC6531"/> and calls this SmtpUTF8Mailbox.  In
SmtpUTF8Mailbox, labels that include non-ASCII characters <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
stored in A-label (rather than U-label) form <xref target="RFC5890"/>.  This
restriction reduces complexity for implementations of the certification
path validation algorithm defined in <xref target="RFC5280" sectionFormat="of" section="6"/>.  In
SmtpUTF8Mailbox, domain labels that solely use ASCII characters (meaning
neither A- nor U-labels) <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> use NR-LDH restrictions as specified by
<xref target="RFC5890" sectionFormat="of" section="2.3.1"/>.  NR-LDH stands for "Non-Reserved Letters
Digits Hyphen" and is the set of LDH labels that do not have "--"
characters in the third and forth character positions, which excludes
"tagged domain names" such as A-labels. To facilitate octet-for-octet
comparisons of SmtpUTF8Mailbox values, all NR-LDH and A-label labels
that constitute the domain part <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> only be encoded with lowercase
letters. Consistent with the treatment of rfc822Name in <xref target="RFC5280"/>,
SmtpUTF8Mailbox is an envelope <tt>Mailbox</tt> and has no phrase (such as a
common name) before it, has no comment (text surrounded in parentheses)
after it, and is not surrounded by "&lt;" and "&gt;" characters.</t>
      <t>Due to name constraint compatibility reasons described in <xref target="name-constraints"/>,
SmtpUTF8Mailbox subjectAltName <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be used unless the Local-part
of the email address contains non-ASCII characters.  When the
Local-part is ASCII, rfc822Name subjectAltName <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be used instead of
SmtpUTF8Mailbox.  This is compatible with legacy software that
supports only rfc822Name (and not SmtpUTF8Mailbox).  The appropriate
usage of rfc822Name and SmtpUTF8Mailbox is summarized in Table 1
below.</t>
      <t>SmtpUTF8Mailbox is encoded as UTF8String.  The UTF8String encoding
<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain a Byte Order Mark (BOM) <xref target="RFC3629"/> to aid consistency
across implementations, particularly for comparison.</t>
      <table anchor="santypes">
        <name>Email Address Formatting</name>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Local-part char</th>
            <th align="left">subjectAltName</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">ASCII-only</td>
            <td align="left">rfc822Name</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">non-ASCII</td>
            <td align="left">SmtpUTF8Mailbox</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>Non-ASCII Local-part values may additionally include ASCII characters.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="idna2008">
      <name>IDNA2008</name>
      <t>To facilitate comparison between email addresses, all email address
domains in X.509 certificates <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> conform to IDNA2008 <xref target="RFC5890"/> (and
avoid any "mappings" mentioned in that document).  Use of
non-conforming email address domains introduces the possibility of
conversion errors between alternate forms.  This applies to
SmtpUTF8Mailbox and rfc822Name in subjectAltName, issuerAltName, and
anywhere else that these are used.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="name-matching">
      <name>Matching of Internationalized Email Addresses in X.509 Certificates</name>
      <t>Equivalence comparisons with SmtpUTF8Mailbox consist of
a domain part step and a Local-part step.  The comparison form for
Local-parts is always UTF-8.  The comparison form for domain parts
is always performed with the LDH label (<xref target="RFC5890"/>) encoding of the
relevant domain labels. The comparison of LDH labels in domain parts
reduces complexity for implementations of the certification path
validation algorithm as defined in <xref target="RFC5280" sectionFormat="of" section="6"/> by obviating
the need to convert domain labels to their Unicode representation.</t>
      <t>Comparison of two SmtpUTF8Mailboxes is straightforward with no setup
work needed.  They are considered equivalent if there is an exact
octet-for-octet match.</t>
      <t>Comparison of an SmtpUTF8Mailbox and rfc822Name will always fail.
SmtpUTF8Mailbox values <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> contain a Local-part that includes
one or more non-ASCII characters, while rfc822Names only
includes ASCII characters (including the Local-part). Thus, an
SmtpUTF8Mailbox and rfc822Name will never match.</t>
      <t>Comparison of SmtpUTF8Mailbox values with internationalized email
addresses from other sources (such as received email messages, user
input, etc.) requires additional setup steps for domain part and
Local-part. The initial preparation for the email address to compare
with the SmtpUTF8Mailbox value is to remove any phrases, comments, and
"&lt;" or "&gt;" characters.</t>
      <t>For the setup of the domain part, the following conversions <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be
performed:</t>
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1"><li>
          <t>Convert all labels that constitute the domain part that include
non-ASCII characters to A-labels, if not already in that form. </t>
<ol spacing="normal" type="a">
<li>         <t>
Detect all U-labels present within the domain part using
    <xref target="RFC5891" sectionFormat="of" section="5.1"/>.  </t>
</li>
<li>
          <t>
Transform all detected U-labels (Unicode) to A-labels (ASCII)
   as specified in <xref target="RFC5891" sectionFormat="of" section="5.5"/>.</t>
</li></ol>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Convert all uppercase letters found within the NR-LDH and A-label
labels that constitute the domain part to lowercase letters.</t>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <t>For the setup of the Local-part, the Local-part <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be verified to
conform to the requirements of <xref target="RFC6530"/> and <xref target="RFC6531"/>, including
being a string in UTF-8 form.  In particular, the Local-
part <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be transformed in any way, such as by doing case
folding or normalization of any kind.  The <tt>Local-part</tt> of an
internationalized email address is already in UTF-8. Once setup is
complete, they are again compared octet for octet.</t>
      <t>To summarize non-normatively, the comparison steps, including setup,
are:</t>
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1"><li>
          <t>If the domain contains U-labels, transform them to A-labels.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>If any NR-LDH or A-label domain label in the domain part
contains uppercase letters, lowercase them.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Compare strings octet for octet for equivalence.</t>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <t>This specification expressly does not define any wildcard characters,
and SmtpUTF8Mailbox comparison implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> interpret any
characters as wildcards.  Instead, to specify multiple email
addresses through SmtpUTF8Mailbox, the certificate <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use multiple
subjectAltNames or issuerAltNames to explicitly carry any additional
email addresses.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="name-constraints">
      <name>Name Constraints in Path Validation</name>
      <t>This section updates <xref target="RFC5280" sectionFormat="of" section="4.2.1.10"/> to extend
rfc822Name name constraints to SmtpUTF8Mailbox subjectAltNames.
SmtpUTF8Mailbox-aware path validators will apply name constraint
comparison to the subject distinguished name and both forms of
subject alternative names, rfc822Name and SmtpUTF8Mailbox.</t>
      <t>Both rfc822Name and SmtpUTF8Mailbox subject alternative names
represent the same underlying email address namespace.  Since legacy
Certification Authorities (CAs) constrained to issue certificates for a specific set of domains
would lack corresponding UTF-8 constraints, <xref target="RFC9549"/> updates,
modifies, and extends rfc822Name name constraints defined in
<xref target="RFC5280"/> to cover SmtpUTF8Mailbox subject alternative names.  This
ensures that the introduction of SmtpUTF8Mailbox does not violate
existing name constraints.  Since it is not valid to include
non-ASCII UTF-8 characters in the Local-part of rfc822Name name
constraints, and since name constraints that include a Local-part are
rarely, if at all, used in practice, name constraints updated in
<xref target="RFC9549"/> allow the forms that represent all addresses at a host, or
all mailboxes in a domain and deprecates rfc822Name name constraints
that represent a particular mailbox.  That is, rfc822Name constraints
with a Local-part <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be used.</t>
      <t>Constraint comparison with SmtpUTF8Mailbox subjectAltName starts with
the setup steps defined in <xref target="name-matching"/>.  Setup converts the inputs of
the comparison (which is one of a subject distinguished name, an
rfc822Name, or an SmtpUTF8Mailbox subjectAltName, and one of an
rfc822Name name constraint) to constraint comparison form. For both the
name constraint and the subject, this will convert all A-labels and
NR-LDH labels to lowercase. Strip the Local-part and "@"
separator from each rfc822Name and SmtpUTF8Mailbox, which leaves just the
domain part.  After setup, follow the comparison steps defined
in <xref target="RFC5280" sectionFormat="of" section="4.2.1.10"/> as follows.  If the resulting name
constraint domain starts with a "." character, then for the name
constraint to match, a suffix of the resulting subject alternative
name domain <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> match the name constraint (including the leading
".") octet for octet.  If the resulting name constraint domain does
not start with a "." character, then for the name constraint to
match, the entire resulting subject alternative name domain <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
match the name constraint octet for octet.</t>
      <t>Certificate Authorities that wish to issue CA certificates with email
address name constraints <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use rfc822Name subject alternative
names only.  These <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be IDNA2008-conformant names with no mappings
and with non-ASCII domains encoded in A-labels only.</t>
      <t>The name constraint requirement with an SmtpUTF8Mailbox subject
alternative name is illustrated in the non-normative diagram in
<xref target="nctypes"/>.  The first example (1) illustrates a permitted rfc822Name
ASCII-only host name name constraint and the corresponding valid
rfc822Name subjectAltName and SmtpUTF8Mailbox subjectAltName email
addresses.  The second example (2) illustrates a permitted rfc822Name
host name name constraint with an A-label, and the corresponding valid
rfc822Name subjectAltName and SmtpUTF8Mailbox subjectAltName email
addresses.  Note that an email address with an ASCII-only Local-part is
encoded as rfc822Name despite also having Unicode present in the
domain.</t>
      <figure anchor="nctypes">
        <name>Name Constraints with SmtpUTF8Name and rfc822Name</name>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
+-------------------------------------------------------------------+
|  Root CA Cert                                                     |
+-------------------------------------------------------------------+
                                  |
                                  v
+-------------------------------------------------------------------+
|  Intermediate CA Cert                                             |
|      Permitted                                                    |
|        rfc822Name: elementary.school.example.com (1)              |
|                                                                   |
|        rfc822Name: xn--pss25c.example.com (2)                     |
|                                                                   |
+-------------------------------------------------------------------+
                                  |
                                  v
+-------------------------------------------------------------------+
|  Entity Cert (w/explicitly permitted subjects)                    |
|    SubjectAltName Extension                                       |
|      rfc822Name: student@elementary.school.example.com (1)        |
|      SmtpUTF8Mailbox: u+5B66u+751F@elementary.school.example.com  |
|        (1)                                                        |
|                                                                   |
|      rfc822Name: student@xn--pss25c.example.com (2)               |
|      SmtpUTF8Mailbox: u+533Bu+751F@xn--pss25c.example.com (2)     |
|                                                                   |
+-------------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>Use of SmtpUTF8Mailbox for certificate subjectAltName (and
issuerAltName) will incur many of the same security considerations 
described in <xref target="RFC5280" sectionFormat="of" section="8"/>, but it introduces a new issue by
permitting non-ASCII characters in the email address Local-part.
This issue, as mentioned in <xref target="RFC5890" sectionFormat="of" section="4.4"/> and in <xref target="RFC6532" sectionFormat="of" section="4"/>, is that use of Unicode introduces the risk of visually
similar and identical characters that can be exploited to deceive the
recipient.  The former document references some means to mitigate
against these attacks.  See <xref target="WEBER"/> for more background on security
issues with Unicode.</t>
      <t>Additionally, it is possible to encode a string of Unicode
user-perceived characters in multiple ways. While various Unicode
normalization forms exist, <xref target="RFC6531"/> does not mandate the use of any
such forms for the encoding of the Local-part. Thus, it may be possible
to encode a Local-part value in multiple ways. To mitigate against
attacks where different encodings are used by the mail system and the
Certification Authority issues certificates containing
<tt>SmtpUTF8Mailbox</tt> values, this specification requires an octet-for-octet
comparison of the Local-part. However, requiring the use of binary
comparison may raise interoperability concerns where the mail system
employs one encoding and the Certification Authority employs another.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="differences-from-rfc-8398">
      <name>Differences from RFC 8398</name>
      <t>This document obsoletes <xref target="RFC8398"/>. There are three major changes
defined in this specification:</t>
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1"><li>
          <t>In all cases, domain labels in mail addresses <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be encoded as
LDH labels. In particular, domain names <bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14> be encoded using
U-Labels; instead, use A-Labels.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>To accommodate the first change listed above, the mail address
matching algorithm defined in <xref target="RFC8398" sectionFormat="of" section="5"/> has been modified
to only accept domain labels that are encoded using their A-label
representation.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Additionally, the procedure to process rfc822Name name constraints as defined
      in 
<xref target="RFC8398" sectionFormat="of" section="6"/> has been modified to only accept domain labels
that are encoded using their A-label representation.</t>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>IANA has updated the reference for the id-mod-lamps-eai-addresses-2016 
module in the "SMI Security for PKIX Module Identifier"
(1.3.6.1.5.5.7.0) registry to refer to this document instead of <xref target="RFC8398"/>.</t>
      <t>IANA has updated the reference for the SmtpUTF8Mailbox otherName in the
"SMI Security for PKIX Other Name Forms" (1.3.6.1.5.5.7.8) registry to refer to this document instead of <xref target="RFC8398"/>.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>

    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references anchor="sec-normative-references">
        <name>Normative References</name>

	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9549.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5321.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6531.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5890.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6532.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5891.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6530.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8398.xml"/>

      </references>

      <references anchor="sec-informative-references">
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="WEBER" target="https://www.lookout.net/files/Chris_Weber_Character%20Transformations%20v1.7_IUC33.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>Unraveling Unicode: A Bag of Tricks for Bug Hunting</title>
            <author initials="C." surname="Weber" fullname="Chris Weber">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2009" month="July"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5912.xml"/>

      </references>
    </references>


<section anchor="asn1-module">
      <name>ASN.1 Module</name>
      <t>The following ASN.1 module normatively specifies the SmtpUTF8Mailbox
structure.  This specification uses the ASN.1 definitions from
<xref target="RFC5912"/> with the 2002 ASN.1 notation used in that document.
<xref target="RFC5912"/> updates normative documents using older ASN.1 notation.</t>
      <sourcecode type="ASN.1"><![CDATA[
LAMPS-EaiAddresses-2016
{ iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6)
  internet(1) security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) id-mod(0)
  id-mod-lamps-eai-addresses-2016(92) }

DEFINITIONS IMPLICIT TAGS ::=
BEGIN

IMPORTS
OTHER-NAME
FROM PKIX1Implicit-2009
  { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1) security(5)
  mechanisms(5) pkix(7) id-mod(0) id-mod-pkix1-implicit-02(59) }

id-pkix
FROM PKIX1Explicit-2009
  { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1) security(5)
  mechanisms(5) pkix(7) id-mod(0) id-mod-pkix1-explicit-02(51) } ;

--
-- otherName carries additional name types for subjectAltName,
-- issuerAltName, and other uses of GeneralNames.
--

id-on OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-pkix 8 }

SmtpUtf8OtherNames OTHER-NAME ::= { on-SmtpUTF8Mailbox, ... }

on-SmtpUTF8Mailbox OTHER-NAME ::= {
    SmtpUTF8Mailbox IDENTIFIED BY id-on-SmtpUTF8Mailbox
}

id-on-SmtpUTF8Mailbox OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-on 9 }

SmtpUTF8Mailbox ::= UTF8String (SIZE (1..MAX))
-- SmtpUTF8Mailbox conforms to Mailbox as specified
-- in Section 3.3 of RFC 6531. Additionally, all domain
-- labels included in the SmtpUTF8Mailbox value are
-- encoded as LDH Labels. In particular, domain labels
-- are not encoded as U-Labels and instead are encoded
-- using their A-label representation.

END
]]></sourcecode>
    </section>
    <section anchor="example-of-smtputf8mailbox">
      <name>Example of SmtpUTF8Mailbox</name>
      <t>This non-normative example demonstrates using SmtpUTF8Mailbox as an
otherName in GeneralName to encode the email address
"u+533Bu+751F@xn--pss25c.example.com".</t>
      <t>The hexadecimal DER encoding of the block is:</t>
      <artwork><![CDATA[
a02b0608 2b060105 05070809 a01f0c1d e58cbbe7 949f4078 6e2d2d70
73733235 632e6578 616d706c 652e636f 6d
]]></artwork>
      <t>The text decoding is:</t>
      <artwork><![CDATA[
0  43: [0] {
2   8:   OBJECT IDENTIFIER '1 3 6 1 5 5 7 8 9'
12  31:   [0] {
14  29:     UTF8String 'u+533Bu+751F@xn--pss25c.example.com'
      :     }
      :   }
]]></artwork>
      <t>The example was encoded using Google's "der-ascii" program and the
above text decoding is an output of Peter Gutmann's "dumpasn1"
program.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="false" anchor="acknowledgments">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>The authors thank David Benjamin for providing the motivation for this
document. Additionally, the authors thank Éric Vyncke, John Levine,
Peter van Dijk, Rich Salz, Russ Housley, and Tim Hollebeek for their
reviews and feedback, which meaningfully improved the document.</t>
      <t>The authors also recognize and appreciate the following individuals for
their contributions to <xref target="RFC8398"/>:</t>
    <blockquote>
      <t>Thank you to Magnus Nystrom for motivating this document.  Thanks to
Russ Housley, Nicolas Lidzborski, Laetitia Baudoin, Ryan Sleevi, Sean
Leonard, Sean Turner, John Levine, and Patrik Falstrom for their
feedback.  Also special thanks to John Klensin for his valuable input
on internationalization, Unicode, and ABNF formatting; to Jim Schaad
for his help with the ASN.1 example and his helpful feedback; and
especially to Viktor Dukhovni for helping us with name constraints
and his many detailed document reviews.</t></blockquote>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
