<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-irtf-hrpc-guidelines-21" number="9620" category="info" updates="8280" obsoletes="" submissionType="IRTF" xml:lang="en" consensus="true" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Guidelines for HRPC">Guidelines for Human Rights Protocol
    and Architecture Considerations</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9620"/>
    <author initials="G." surname="Grover" fullname="Gurshabad Grover">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <email>gurshabad@cis-india.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="N." surname="ten Oever" fullname="Niels ten Oever">
      <organization>University of Amsterdam</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mail@nielstenoever.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2024" month="September"/>

    <area>IRTF</area>
    <workgroup>Human Rights Protocol Considerations</workgroup>

   <keyword>International human rights</keyword>
   <keyword>Protocol design</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document sets guidelines for human rights considerations for
      developers working on network protocols and architectures, similar to
      the work done on the guidelines for privacy considerations (RFC
      6973). This is an updated version of the guidelines for human rights
      considerations in RFC 8280.</t>
      <t>This document is a product of the Human Right Protocol Considerations (HRPC) Research Group in the IRTF.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>This document outlines a set of human rights protocol considerations for protocol developers. It provides questions that engineers should ask themselves when developing or improving protocols if they want to understand how their decisions can potentially influence the exercise of human rights on the Internet. It should be noted that the impact of a protocol cannot solely be deduced from its design, but its usage and implementation should also be studied to form a full human rights impact assessment.</t>
      <t>The questions are based on the research performed by the Human Rights Protocol Considerations (HRPC) Research Group, which has been documented before these considerations. The research establishes that human rights relate to standards and protocols and offers a common vocabulary of technical concepts that influence human rights and how these technical concepts can be combined to ensure that the Internet remains an enabling environment for human rights. With this, the contours of a model for developing human rights protocol considerations has taken shape.</t>
      <t>This document is an iteration of the guidelines that can be found in <xref target="RFC8280" format="default"/>. The methods for conducting human rights reviews (<xref target="analyzing-drafts-based-on-their-perceived-or-speculated-impact" format="default"/>) and the guidelines for human rights considerations (<xref target="expert-interviews" format="default"/>) in this document are being tested for relevance, accuracy, and validity <xref target="HR-RT" format="default"/>. The understanding of what human rights are is based on the "Universal Declaration of Human Rights" <xref target="UDHR" format="default"/> and subsequent treaties that jointly form the body of international human rights law <xref target="UNHR" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>This document does not provide a detailed taxonomy of the nature of (potential) human rights violations, whether direct or indirect / long-term or short-term, that certain protocol choices might present. In part, it is because this is highly context-dependent and also because this document aims to provide a practical set of guidelines. However, further research in this field would definitely benefit developers and implementers.</t>
      <t>
	This informational document has consensus for publication from the Internet Research Task Force (IRTF) Human Right Protocol Considerations (HRPC) Research Group. It has been reviewed, tried, and tested by both the research group as well as researchers and practitioners from outside the research group. The research group acknowledges that the understanding of the impact of Internet protocols and architecture on society is a developing practice and is a body of research that is still ongoing. This document is not an IETF product and is not a standard.
    </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="human-rights-threats" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Human Rights Threats</name>
      <t>Threats to the exercise of human rights on the Internet come in many forms. Protocols and standards may harm or enable the right to freedom of expression; right to freedom of information; right to non-discrimination; right to equal protection; right to participate in cultural life, arts, and science; right to freedom of assembly and association; right to privacy; and right to security. An end user who is denied access to certain services or content may be unable to disclose vital information about the malpractices of a government or other authority. A person whose communications are monitored may be prevented or dissuaded from exercising their right to freedom of association or participate in political processes <xref target="Penney" format="default"/>. In a worst-case scenario, protocols that leak information can lead to physical danger. A realistic example to consider is when individuals perceived as threats to the state are subjected to torture, extra-judicial killing, or detention on the basis of information gathered by state agencies through the monitoring of network traffic.</t>
      <t>This document presents several examples of how threats to human rights materialize on the Internet. This threat modeling is inspired by "<xref target="RFC6973" format="title"/>" <xref target="RFC6973" format="default"/>, which is based on security threat analysis. This method is a work in progress and by no means a perfect solution for assessing human rights risks in Internet protocols and systems. Certain specific human rights threats are indirectly considered in Internet protocols as part of the security considerations <xref target="RFC3552" format="default"/>; however, privacy considerations <xref target="RFC6973" format="default"/> or reviews, let alone human rights impact assessments of protocols, are neither standardized nor implemented.</t>
      <t>Many threats, enablers, and risks are linked to different rights. This is not surprising if one takes into account that human rights are interrelated, interdependent, and indivisible. However, here we're not discussing all human rights because not all human rights are relevant to Information and Communication Technologies (ICTs) in general and to protocols and standards in particular <xref target="Orwat" format="default"/>:</t>
      <blockquote>The main source of the values of human rights is the 
<em>International Bill of Human Rights</em> that is composed of the <em>Universal Declaration of Human Rights</em> (UDHR) <xref target="UDHR" format="default"/> along with the <em>International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights</em> (ICCPR) <xref target="ICCPR" format="default"/> and the <em>International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</em> (ICESCR) <xref target="ICESCR" format="default"/>. In the light of several cases of Internet censorship, the UN Human Rights Council Resolution 20/8 was adopted in 2012, affirming that "...the same rights that people have offline must also be protected online..." <xref target="UNHRC2016" format="default"/>. In 2015, the <em>Charter of Human Rights and Principles for the Internet</em> <xref target="IRP" format="default"/> was developed and released <xref target="Jorgensen" format="default"/>. According to these documents, some examples of human rights relevant for ICT systems are <em>human dignity</em> (Art. 1 UDHR), <em>non-discrimination</em> (Art. 2), <em>rights to life, liberty and security</em> (Art. 3), <em>freedom of opinion and expression</em> (Art. 19), <em>freedom of assembly and association</em> (Art. 20), <em>rights to equal protection, legal remedy, fair trial, due process, presumed innocent</em> (Art. 7-11), <em>appropriate social and international order</em> (Art. 28), <em>participation in public affairs</em> (Art. 21), <em>participation in cultural life, protection of intellectual property</em> (Art. 27), and <em>privacy</em> (Art. 12).</blockquote>
      <t>A partial catalog of human rights related to ICTs, including economic rights, can be found in <xref target="Hill" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>This is by no means an attempt to exclude specific rights or prioritize some rights over others.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="conducting-human-rights-reviews" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Conducting Human Rights Reviews</name>
      <t>Ideally, protocol developers and collaborators should incorporate human rights considerations into the design process itself (see <xref target="analyzing-drafts-based-on-guidelines-for-human-rights-considerations-model"/> ("Analyzing Internet-Drafts Based on Guidelines for Human Rights Considerations Model")).
This section provides guidance on how to conduct a human rights review, i.e., gauge the impact or potential impact of a protocol or standard on human rights.</t>
      <t>Human rights reviews can be done by any participant and can take place at different stages of the development process of an Internet-Draft. Generally speaking, it is easier to influence the development of a technology at earlier stages than at later stages. This does not mean that reviews at Last Call are not relevant, but they are less likely to result in significant changes in the reviewed document.</t>
      <t>Human rights reviews can be done by document authors, document shepherds, members of review teams, advocates, or impacted communities to influence the standards development process. IETF documents can benefit from people with different knowledge, perspectives, and backgrounds, especially since their implementations can impact many different communities as well.</t>
      <t>Methods for analyzing technology for specific human rights impacts are still quite nascent. Currently, five methods have been explored by the human rights review team, often in conjunction with each other.</t>
      <section anchor="analyzing-drafts-based-on-guidelines-for-human-rights-considerations-model" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Analyzing Internet-Drafts Based on Guidelines for Human Rights Considerations Model</name>
        <t>This analysis of Internet-Drafts uses the model as described in <xref target="guidelines-for-human-rights-considerations" format="default"/>. The outlined categories and questions can be used to review an Internet-Draft. The advantage of this is that it provides a known overview, and document authors can go back to this document as well as <xref target="RFC8280" format="default"/> to understand the background and the context.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="analyzing-drafts-based-on-their-perceived-or-speculated-impact" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Analyzing Internet-Drafts Based on Their Perceived or Speculated Impact</name>
        <t>When reviewing an Internet-Draft, specific human rights impacts can become apparent by doing a close reading of the draft and seeking to understand how it might affect networks or society. While less structured than the straight use of the human rights considerations model, this analysis may lead to new speculative understandings of links between human rights and protocols.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="expert-interviews" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Expert Interviews</name>
        <t>Interviews with document authors, active members of the working group, or experts in the field can help explore the characteristics of the protocol and its effects.
   There are two main advantages to this approach:</t>
   <ol spacing="normal">
     <li>It allows the reviewer to gain a deeper understanding of the (intended) workings of the protocol.</li>
     <li>It allows for the reviewer to start a discussion with experts or even document authors, which can help the review gain traction when it is published.</li>
   </ol>
      </section>
      <section anchor="interviews-with-impacted-persons-and-communities" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Interviews with Impacted Persons and Communities</name>
        <t>Protocols impact users of the Internet. Interviews can help the reviewer understand how protocols affect the people that use the protocols. Since human rights are best understood from the perspective of the rights-holder, this approach will improve the understanding of the real-world effects of the technology. At the same time, it can be hard to attribute specific changes to a particular protocol; this is of course even harder when a protocol has not been widely deployed.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="tracing-impacts-of-implementations" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Tracing Impacts of Implementations</name>
        <t>The reality of deployed protocols can be at odds with the expectations during the protocol design and development phase <xref target="RFC8980" format="default"/>. When a specification already has associated running code, the code can be analyzed either in an experimental setting or on the Internet where its impact can be observed. In contrast to reviewing the draft text, this approach can allow the reviewer to understand how the specifications work in practice and potentially what unknown or unexpected effects the technology has.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="guidelines-for-human-rights-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Guidelines for Human Rights Considerations</name>
      <t>This section provides guidance for document authors in the form of a questionnaire about protocols and how technical decisions can shape the exercise of human rights. The questionnaire may be useful at any point in the design process, particularly after the document authors have developed a high-level protocol model as described in <xref target="RFC4101" format="default"/>. These guidelines do not seek to replace any existing referenced specifications but, rather, contribute to them and look at the design process from a human rights perspective.</t>
      <t>Protocols and Internet Standards might benefit from a documented discussion of potential human rights risks arising from potential misapplications of the protocol or technology described in the Request for Comments (RFC). This might be coupled with an Applicability Statement for that RFC.</t>
      <t>Note that the guidance provided in this section does not recommend specific practices. The range of protocols developed in the IETF is too broad to make recommendations about particular uses of data or how human rights might be balanced against other design goals.  However, by carefully considering the answers to the following questions, document authors should be able to produce a comprehensive analysis that can serve as the basis for discussion on whether the protocol adequately takes specific human rights threats into account. This guidance is meant to help the thought process of a human rights analysis; it does not provide specific directions for how to write a human rights considerations section (following the example set in <xref target="RFC6973" format="default"/>).</t>
      <t>In considering these questions, authors will need to be aware of the potential of technical advances or the passage of time to undermine protections. In general, considerations of rights are likely to be more effective if they have a purpose and specific use cases rather than abstract, absolute goals.</t>
      <t>Also note that while the section uses the word "protocol", the principles identified in these questions may be applicable to other types of solutions (extensions to existing protocols, architecture for solutions to specific problems, etc.).</t>
      <section anchor="intermediaries" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Intermediaries</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Does your protocol depend on or allow for protocol-specific functions at intermediary nodes?</t>
        <t>Explanation:
	The end-to-end principle <xref target="Saltzer" format="default"/> holds that certain functions can and should be performed at "ends" of the network. <xref target="RFC1958" format="default"/> states that "in very general terms, the community believes that the goal is connectivity ... and the intelligence is end to end rather than hidden in the network". There are new opportunities for failure when a protocol exchange includes both endpoints and an intermediary, especially when the intermediary is not under control of either endpoint, or is even largely invisible to it, for instance, as with intercepting HTTPS proxies <xref target="HTTPS-interception" format="default"/>. This pattern also contributes to ossification because the intermediaries may impose protocol restrictions -- sometimes in violation of the specification -- that prevent the endpoints from using more modern protocols, as described in <xref target="RFC8446" sectionFormat="of" section="9.3"/>.</t>
        <t>Note that intermediaries are distinct from services. In the former case, the third-party element is part of the protocol exchange; whereas in the latter, the endpoints communicate explicitly with the service. The client/server pattern provides clearer separation of responsibilities between elements than having an intermediary. However, even in client/server systems, it is often good practice to provide for end-to-end encryption between endpoints for protocol elements that are outside of the scope of the service, as in the design of Messaging Layer Security (MLS) <xref target="RFC9420" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Example:
Encryption between the endpoints can be used to protect the protocol from interference by intermediaries. The encryption of transport layer information in QUIC <xref target="RFC9000" format="default"/> and of the TLS Server Name Indication (SNI) field <xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-esni" format="default"/> are examples of this practice. One consequence of this is to limit the extent to which network operators can inspect traffic, requiring them to have control of the endpoints in order to monitor their behavior.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to freedom of assembly and association</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="connectivity" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Connectivity</name>
        <t>Questions(s):
Is your protocol optimized for low-bandwidth and high-latency connections? Could your protocol also be developed in a stateless manner?</t>
        <t>Considering the fact that network quality and conditions vary across geography and time, it is also important to design protocols such that they are reliable even on low-bandwidth and high-latency connections.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to freedom of assembly and association</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="reliability" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Reliability</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Is your protocol fault tolerant? Does it downgrade gracefully, i.e., with mechanisms for fallback and/or notice? Can your protocol resist malicious degradation attempts? Do you have a documented way to announce degradation? Do you have measures in place for recovery or partial healing from failure? Can your protocol maintain dependability and performance in the face of unanticipated changes or circumstances?</t>
        <t>Explanation:
Reliability and resiliency ensures that a protocol will execute its function consistently and resistant to error, as described, and will function without unexpected results. Measures for reliability in protocols assure users that their intended communication was successfully executed.</t>
        <t>A system that is reliable degrades gracefully and will have a documented way to announce degradation. It will also have mechanisms to recover from failure gracefully and, if applicable, will allow for partial healing.</t>
        <t>It is important here to draw a distinction between random degradation and malicious degradation. Some attacks against previous versions of TLS, for example, exploited TLS' ability to gracefully downgrade to non-secure cipher suites <xref target="FREAK" format="default"/> <xref target="Logjam" format="default"/>; from a functional perspective, this is useful, but from a security perspective, this can be disastrous.</t>
        <t>For reliability, it is necessary that services notify the users if a delivery fails. In the case of real-time systems, in addition to the reliable delivery, the protocol needs to safeguard timeliness.</t>
        <t>Example:
In the modern IP stack structure, a reliable transport layer requires an indication that transport processing has successfully completed, such as given by TCP's ACK message <xref target="RFC9293" format="default"/>. Similarly, an application-layer protocol may require an application-specific acknowledgement that contains, among other things, a status code indicating the disposition of the request (see <xref target="RFC3724" format="default"/>).</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to security</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="content-signals" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Content Signals</name>
        <t>Question(s): 
 Does your protocol include explicit or implicit plaintext elements, in either the payload or the headers, that can be used for differential treatment? Is there a way to minimize leaking such data to network intermediaries? If not, is there a way for deployments of the protocol to make the differential treatment (including prioritization of certain traffic), if any, auditable for negative impacts on net neutrality?</t>
        <t>Example:
When network intermediaries are able to determine the type of content that a packet is carrying, then they can use that information to discriminate in favor of one type of content and against another. This impacts users' ability to send and receive the content of their choice.</t>
        <t>As recommended in <xref target="RFC8558" format="default"/>, protocol designers should avoid the construction of implicit signals of their content. In general, protocol designers should avoid adding explicit signals for intermediaries. In certain cases, it may be necessary to add such explicit signals, but designers should only do so when they provide clear benefit to end users (see <xref target="RFC8890" format="default"/> for more on the priority of constituencies). In these cases, the implications of those signals for human rights should be documented.</t>
        <t>Note that many protocols provide signals that are intended for endpoints that can be used as implicit signals by intermediaries for traffic discrimination, based on either the content (e.g., TCP port numbers) or the sender/receiver (IP addresses). Where possible, these should be protected from intermediaries by encryption. In many cases (e.g., IP addresses), these signals are difficult to remove; but in other cases, such as TLS Application Layer Protocol Negotiation <xref target="RFC7301" format="default"/>, there are active efforts to protect this data <xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-esni" format="default"/>.</t>
	<t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to non-discrimination</li>
          <li>Right to equal protection</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="internationalization" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Internationalization</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Does your protocol or specification define text string elements, in the payload or headers, that have to be understood or entered by humans? Does your specification allow Unicode? If so, do you accept texts in one character set (which must be UTF-8) or several (which is dangerous for interoperability)? If charsets or encodings other than UTF-8 are allowed, does your specification mandate a proper tagging of the charset? Did you have a look at <xref target="RFC6365" format="default"/>?</t>
        <t>Explanation:
Internationalization refers to the practice of making protocols, standards, and implementations usable in different languages and scripts (see <xref target="localization"/> ("Localization")). In the IETF, internationalization means to add or improve the handling of non-ASCII text in a protocol <xref target="RFC6365" format="default"/>. A different perspective, more appropriate to protocols that are designed for global use from the beginning, is the definition used by the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) <xref target="W3Ci18nDef"/>:</t>

<blockquote>Internationalization is the design and development of a product, application or document content that enables easy localization for target audiences that vary in culture, region, or language.</blockquote>

        <t>Many protocols that handle text only handle one charset (US-ASCII) or leave the question of what coded charset and encoding are used up to local guesswork (which leads, of course, to interoperability problems). If multiple charsets are permitted, they must be explicitly identified <xref target="RFC2277" format="default"/>.  Adding non-ASCII text to a protocol allows the protocol to handle more scripts, hopefully representing users across the world.  In today's world, that is normally best accomplished by allowing only Unicode encoded in UTF-8.</t>
        <t>In current IETF practice <xref target="RFC2277" format="default"/>, internationalization is aimed at user-facing strings, not protocol elements, such as the verbs used by some text-based protocols. (Do note that some strings are both content and protocol elements, such as identifiers.) Although this is reasonable practice for non-user visible elements, developers should provide full and equal support for all scripts and charsets in the user-facing features of protocols and for any content they carry.</t>
        <t>Example:
See <xref target="localization"/> ("Localization").</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to political participation</li>
          <li>Right to participate in cultural life, arts, and science</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="localization" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Localization</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Does your protocol uphold the standards of internationalization? Have you made any concrete steps towards localizing your protocol for relevant audiences?</t>
        <t>Explanation: "Localization refers to the adaptation of a product, application or document content to meet the language, cultural and other requirements of a specific target market (a 'locale')" <xref target="W3Ci18nDef" format="default"/>. For our purposes, it can be described as the practice of translating an implementation to make it functional in a specific language or for users in a specific locale (see <xref target="internationalization"/> ("Internationalization")). Internationalization is related to localization, but they are not the same. Internationalization is a necessary precondition for localization.</t>
        <t>Example:
The Internet is a global medium, but many of its protocols and products are developed with certain audiences in mind that often share particular characteristics like knowing how to read and write in American Standard Code for Information Interchange (ASCII) and knowing English. This limits the ability of a large part of the world's online population from using the Internet in a way that is culturally and linguistically accessible. An example of a standard that has taken into account the view that individuals like to have access to data in their preferred language can be found in <xref target="RFC5646" format="default"/>. The document describes a way to label information with an identifier for the language in which it is written. And this allows information to be presented and accessed in more than one language.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to non-discrimination</li>
          <li>Right to participate in cultural life, arts, and science</li>
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="open-standards" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Open Standards</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Is your protocol fully documented in a way that it could be easily implemented, improved, built upon, and/or further developed? Do you depend on proprietary code for the implementation, running, or further development of your protocol? Does your protocol favor a particular proprietary specification over technically equivalent competing specification(s), for instance, by making any incorporated vendor specification  "required" or "recommended" <xref target="RFC2026" format="default"/>? Do you normatively reference another standard that is behind a paywall (and could you do without it)? Are you aware of any patents that would prevent your standard from being fully implemented <xref target="RFC8179" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC6701" format="default"/>?</t>
        <t>Explanation:
The Internet was able to be developed into the global network of networks because of the existence of open, non-proprietary standards <xref target="Zittrain" format="default"/>. They are crucial for enabling interoperability. Yet, open standards are not explicitly defined within the IETF. On the subject, <xref target="RFC2026" format="default"/> states:</t>
<blockquote>Various national and international standards bodies, such as ANSI, ISO, IEEE, and ITU-T, develop a variety of protocol and service specifications that are similar to Technical Specifications defined here [at the IETF]. National and international groups also publish "implementors' agreements" that are analogous to Applicability Statements, capturing a body of implementation-specific detail concerned with the practical application of their standards. All of these are considered to be "open external standards" for the purposes of the Internet Standards Process.</blockquote> 
<t>Similarly, <xref target="RFC3935" format="default"/> does not define open standards but does emphasize the importance of an "open process", i.e.:</t>
<blockquote>... any interested person can participate in the work, know what is being decided, and make [their] voice heard on the issue.</blockquote>
        <t>Open standards (and open source software) allow users to glean information about how the tools they are using work, including the tools' security and privacy properties. They additionally allow for permissionless innovation, which is important to maintain the freedom and ability to freely create and deploy new protocols on top of the communications constructs that currently exist. It is at the heart of the Internet as we know it, and to maintain its fundamentally open nature, we need to be mindful of the need for developing open standards.</t>
        <t>All standards that need to be normatively implemented should be freely available and with reasonable protection for patent infringement claims so that they can also be implemented in open source or free software. Patents have often held back open standardization or been used against those deploying open standards, particularly in the domain of cryptography <xref target="Newegg" format="default"/>. An exemption of this is sometimes made when a standardized protocol normatively relies on specifications produced by others Standards Development Organizations (SDOs) that are not freely available. Patents in open standards or in normative references to other standards should have a patent disclosure <xref target="Note-well" format="default"/>, royalty-free licensing <xref target="Patent-policy" format="default"/>, or some other form of fair, reasonable, and non-discriminatory terms.</t>
        <t>Example:
<xref target="RFC6108" format="default"/> describes a system for providing critical end-user notifications to web browsers, which has been deployed by Comcast, an Internet Service Provider (ISP). Such a notification system is being used to provide near-immediate notifications to customers, such as to warn them that their traffic exhibits patterns that are indicative of malware or virus infection. There are other proprietary systems that can perform such notifications, but those systems utilize Deep Packet Inspection (DPI) technology. In contrast, that document describes a system that does not rely upon DPI and is instead based on open IETF standards and open source applications.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to participate in cultural life, arts, and science</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="heterogeneity-support" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Heterogeneity Support</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Does your protocol support heterogeneity by design? Does your protocol allow for multiple types of hardware? Does your protocol allow for multiple types of application protocols? Is your protocol liberal in what it receives and handles? Will it remain usable and open if the context changes?</t>
        <t>Explanation:
The Internet is characterized by heterogeneity on many levels: devices, nodes, router scheduling algorithms, queue management mechanisms, routing protocols, levels of multiplexing, protocol versions and implementations, and underlying link layers (e.g., point-to-point, multi-access links, wireless, Fiber Distributed Data Interface (FDDI), etc.) in the traffic mix and in the levels of congestion at different times and places. Moreover, as the Internet is composed of autonomous organizations and ISPs, each with their own separate policy concerns, there is a large heterogeneity of administrative domains and pricing structures. As a result, the heterogeneity principle proposed in <xref target="RFC1958" format="default"/> needs to be supported by design <xref target="FIArch" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Heterogeneity support in protocols can, thus, enable a wide range of devices and (by extension) users to participate on the network.</t>
<t>Example:
Heterogeneity significantly contributed to the success of the Internet architecture <xref target="Zittrain" format="default"/>. There is a famous quote often attributed to Niels Bohr: "Prediction is very difficult, especially if it's about the future." This also holds true for future uses of the Internet architecture and infrastructure. Therefore, as a rule of thumb, it is important to -- as far as possible -- design your protocol for different devices and uses, especially at lower layers of the stack. However, if you choose not to do this, it could be relevant to document the reasoning for that.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to political participation</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="adaptability" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Adaptability</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Is your protocol written in a modular fashion, and does it facilitate or hamper extensibility? In this sense, does your protocol impact permissionless innovation? (See <xref target="open-standards"/> ("Open Standards").)</t>
        <t>Explanation:
Adaptability is closely interrelated with permissionless innovation: both maintain the freedom and ability to create and deploy new protocols on top of the communications constructs that currently exist. It is at the heart of the Internet as we know it, and to maintain its fundamentally open nature, we need to be mindful of the impact of protocols on maintaining or reducing permissionless innovation to ensure that the Internet can continue to develop.</t>
        <t>Adaptability and permissionless innovation can be used to shape information networks as groups of users prefer. Furthermore, a precondition of adaptability is the ability of the people who can adapt the network to be able to know and understand the network. This is why adaptability and permissionless innovation are inherently connected to the right to education and the right to science as well as the right to freedom of assembly and association and the right to freedom of expression, since it allows the users of the network to determine how to assemble, collaborate, and express themselves.</t>
        <t>Example:
WebRTC generates audio and/or video data. WebRTC can be used in different locations by different parties; WebRTC's standard Application Programming Interfaces (APIs) are developed to support applications from different voice service providers. Multiple parties will have similar capabilities. In order to ensure that all parties can build upon existing standards, these need to be adaptable and allow for permissionless innovation.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to education</li>
          <li>Right to science</li>
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to freedom of assembly and association</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="integrity" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Integrity</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Does your protocol maintain, assure, and/or verify the accuracy of payload data? Does your protocol maintain and assure the consistency of data? Does your protocol in any way allow for the data to be (intentionally or unintentionally) altered?</t>
        <t>Explanation:
Integrity refers to the maintenance and assurance of the accuracy and consistency of data to ensure it has not been (intentionally or unintentionally) altered.</t>
        <t>Example:
Integrity verification of data is important to prevent vulnerabilities and attacks from on-path attackers. These attacks happen when a third party (often for malicious reasons) intercepts a communication between two parties, inserting themselves in the middle and changing the content of the data. In practice, this looks as follows:</t>
        <t>Alice wants to communicate with Bob.
Alice sends a message to Bob, which Corinne intercepts and modifies. 
Bob cannot see that the data from Alice was altered by Corinne. 
Corinne intercepts and alters the communication as it is sent between Alice and Bob. 
Corinne is able to control the communication content.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to security</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="authenticity" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Authenticity</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Do you have sufficient measures to confirm the truth of an attribute of a single piece of data or entity? Can the attributes get garbled along the way (see <xref target="security"/> ("Security"))? If relevant, have you implemented IPsec, DNS Security (DNSSEC), HTTPS, and other standard security best practices?</t>
        <t>Explanation:
Authenticity ensures that data does indeed come from the source it claims to come from. This is important to prevent certain attacks or unauthorized access and use of data.</t>
        <t>At the same time, authentication should not be used as a way to prevent heterogeneity support, as is often done for vendor lock-in or digital rights management.</t>
        <t>Example:
Authentication of data is important to prevent vulnerabilities and attacks from on-path attackers. These attacks happen when a third party (often for malicious reasons) intercepts a communication between two parties, inserting themselves in the middle and posing as both parties. In practice, this looks as follows:</t>
        <t>Alice wants to communicate with Bob. 
Alice sends data to Bob. 
Corinne intercepts the data sent to Bob. 
Corinne reads (and potentially alters) the message to Bob. 
	Bob cannot see that the data did not come from Alice but from Corinne.</t>
        <t>With proper authentication, the scenario would be as follows:</t>
        <t>Alice wants to communicate with Bob. 
Alice sends data to Bob. 
Corinne intercepts the data sent to Bob. 
Corinne reads and alters the message to Bob. 
Bob is unable to verify whether that the data came from Alice.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to privacy</li>
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to security</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="confidentiality" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Confidentiality</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Does the protocol expose the transmitted data over the wire? Does the protocol expose information related to identifiers or data? If so, what does it reveal to each protocol entity (i.e., recipients, intermediaries, and enablers) <xref target="RFC6973" format="default"/>? What options exist for protocol implementers to choose to limit the information shared with each entity? What operational controls are available to limit the information shared with each entity?</t>
        <t>What controls or consent mechanisms does the protocol define or require before personal data or identifiers are shared or exposed via the protocol? If no such mechanisms or controls are specified, is it expected that control and consent will be handled outside of the protocol?</t>
        <t>Does the protocol provide ways for initiators to share different pieces of information with different recipients? If not, are there mechanisms that exist outside of the protocol to provide initiators with such control?</t>
        <t>Does the protocol provide ways for initiators to limit the sharing or expressing of individuals' preferences to recipients or intermediaries with regard to the collection, use, or disclosure of their personal data? If not, are there mechanisms that exist outside of the protocol to provide users with such control? Is it expected that users will have relationships that govern the use of the information (contractual or otherwise) with those who operate these intermediaries? Does the protocol prefer encryption over cleartext operation?</t>
        <t>Explanation:
Confidentiality refers to keeping your data secret from unintended listeners <xref target="RFC3552" format="default"/>. The growth of the Internet depends on users having confidence that the network protects their personal data <xref target="RFC1984" format="default"/>. The possibility of pervasive monitoring and surveillance undermines users' trust and can be mitigated by ensuring confidentiality, i.e., passive attackers should gain little or no information from observation or inference of protocol activity <xref target="RFC7258" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC7624" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Example:
Protocols that do not encrypt their payload make the entire content of the communication available to the idealized attacker along their path. Following the advice in <xref target="RFC3365" format="default"/>, most such protocols have a secure variant that encrypts the payload for confidentiality, and these secure variants are seeing ever-wider deployment. A noteworthy exception is DNS <xref target="RFC1035" format="default"/>, as DNSSEC <xref target="RFC4033" format="default"/> does not have confidentiality as a requirement. This implies that, in the absence of the use of more recent standards like DNS over TLS <xref target="RFC7858" format="default"/> or DNS over HTTPS <xref target="RFC8484" format="default"/>, all DNS queries and answers generated by the activities of any protocol are available to the attacker. When store-and-forward protocols are used (e.g., SMTP <xref target="RFC5321" format="default"/>), intermediaries leave this data subject to observation by an attacker that has compromised these intermediaries, unless the data is encrypted end-to-end by the application-layer protocol or the implementation uses an encrypted store for this data <xref target="RFC7624" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to privacy</li>
          <li>Right to security</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="security" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Security</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Did you have a look at <xref target="RFC3552" format="default"> "Guidelines for Writing RFC Text on Security Considerations"</xref>? Have you found any attacks that are somewhat related to your protocol/specification yet considered out of scope of your document? Would these attacks be pertinent to the human-rights-enabling features of the Internet (as described throughout this document)?</t>
        <t>Explanation:
Security is not a single monolithic property of a protocol or system but rather a series of related yet somewhat independent properties. Not all of these properties are required for every application. Since communications are carried out by systems and access to systems is through communications channels, security goals obviously interlock, but they can also be independently provided <xref target="RFC3552" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Typically, any protocol operating on the Internet can be the target of passive attacks (when the attacker can access and read packets on the network) and active attacks (when an attacker is capable of writing information to the network packets) <xref target="RFC3552" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Example:
See <xref target="RFC3552" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to freedom of assembly and association</li>
          <li>Right to non-discrimination</li>
          <li>Right to security</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="privacy" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Privacy</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Did you have a look at the guidelines described in Section <xref target="RFC6973" sectionFormat="bare" section="7"/> of "Privacy Considerations for Internet Protocols" <xref target="RFC6973"/>? Does your protocol maintain the confidentiality of metadata? Could your protocol counter traffic analysis? Does your protocol adhere to data minimization principles?  Does your document identify potentially sensitive data logged by your protocol and/or for how long that needs to be retained for technical reasons?</t>
        <t>Explanation:
	Privacy refers to the right of an entity (normally a person), acting on its own behalf, to determine the degree to which it will interact with its environment, including the degree to which the entity is willing to share its personal information with others <xref target="RFC4949" format="default"/>. If a protocol provides insufficient privacy protection, it may have a negative impact on freedom of expression as users self-censor for fear of surveillance or find that they are unable to express themselves freely.</t>
        <t>Example:
See <xref target="RFC6973" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to privacy</li>
          <li>Right to non-discrimination</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="anonymity-and-pseudonymity" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Anonymity and Pseudonymity</name>
        <t>Question(s): Does your protocol make use of identifiers? Are these
identifiers persistent?  Are they used across multiple contexts? Is it
possible for the user to reset or rotate them without negatively
impacting the operation of the protocol? Are they visible to others
besides the protocol endpoints? Are they tied to real-world
identities? Have you considered "<xref target="RFC6973" format="title"/>" <xref target="RFC6973" format="default"/>, especially Section <xref target="RFC6973" sectionFormat="bare" section="6.1.2"/>?</t>
        <t>Explanation:
Most protocols depend on the use of some kind of identifier in order to correlate
activity over time and space. For instance:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>IP addresses are used as an identity for the source and
          destination for IP datagrams.</li>
          <li>QUIC connection identifiers are used to correlate packets
          belonging to the same connection.</li>
          <li>HTTP uses cookies to correlate multiple HTTP requests from the
          same client.</li>
          <li>Email uses email addresses of the form example@example.com to
          identify senders and receivers.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>In general, these identifiers serve a necessary function for protocol operations
by allowing them to maintain continuity. However, they can also create privacy
risks. There are two major ways in which those risks manifest:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>The identifier may itself reveal the user's identity in some way
          or be tied to an identifier that does, as is the case when E.164
          (telephone) numbers are used as identifiers for instant messaging
          systems.</li>
	  <li>While the identifier may not reveal the user's identity, it may
	  make it possible to link enough of a user's behavior to threaten
	  their privacy, as is the case with HTTP cookies.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>Because identifiers are necessary for protocol operation, true anonymity
is very difficult to achieve, but there are practices that promote
user privacy even when identifiers are used.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to non-discrimination</li>
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to political participation</li>
          <li>Right to freedom of assembly and association</li>
        </ul>
        <section anchor="pseudonymity" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Pseudonymity</name>
          <t>In general, user privacy is better preserved when identifiers are
pseudonymous (not tied to a user's real-world identity).</t>
          <t>Example: In the development of the IPv6 protocol, it was discussed to
embed a Media Access Control (MAC) address into unique IP
addresses. This would make it possible for eavesdroppers and other
information collectors to identify when different addresses used in
different transactions actually correspond to the same node. This is
why standardization efforts like "<xref target="RFC8981" format="title"/>" <xref target="RFC8981" format="default"/> and MAC address
randomization <xref target="I-D.ietf-madinas-mac-address-randomization" format="default"/> have been
pursued.</t>
          <t>Note that it is often attractive to try to create a pseudonym from
a persistent identifier. This can be very difficult to do correctly
in a way that does not allow for recovering the persistent identifiers.</t>
          <t>Example: A common practice in web tracking is to "encrypt" email
addresses by hashing them, thus allegedly making them
"non-personally identifying". However, because hash functions
are public operations, it is possible to do a dictionary search for candidate
email addresses and recover the original address <xref target="Email-hashing" format="default"/>.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="unlinkability" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Unlinkability</name>
          <t>Even true pseudonymous identifiers can present a privacy risk if they are used across a wide enough scope. User privacy is better preserved
if identifiers have limited scope both in time and space.</t>
   <t>Example: An example is the Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) where sending a persistent identifier as the client name was not mandatory but, in practice, done by many implementations before DHCP <xref target="RFC7844" format="default"/>.</t>
          <t>Example: Third-party cookies in HTTP allow trackers to correlate
HTTP traffic across sites.  This is the foundation of a whole
ecosystem of web tracking. Increasingly, web browsers are restricting
the use of third-party cookies in order to protect user privacy.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="censorship-resistance" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Censorship Resistance</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Does your protocol architecture facilitate censorship? Does it include "choke points" that are easy to use for censorship? Does it expose identifiers that can be used to selectively block certain kinds of traffic? Could it be designed to be more censorship resistant? Does your protocol make it apparent or transparent when access to a resource is restricted and why it is restricted?</t>
        <t>Explanation:
Governments and service providers block or filter content or traffic, often without the knowledge of end users <xref target="RFC7754" format="default"/>. For a survey of censorship techniques employed across the world, see <xref target="RFC9505" format="default"/>, which lays out protocol properties that have been exploited to censor access to information. Censorship resistance refers to the methods and measures to prevent Internet censorship.</t>
        <t>Example:
The current design of the Web has a number of architectural choke points where it is possible for censors to intervene. These include obtaining the control of the domain name itself, DNS blocking either at the protocol layer or at the resolver, IP address blocking, and blocking at the web server. There has been extensive work on content distribution systems, which are intended to be more censorship resistant; and some, such as BitTorrent, are in wide use. However, these systems may have inferior reliability and performance compared to the Web (e.g., they do not support active content on the server).</t>
        <t>Example:
Identifiers of content exposed within a protocol might be used to facilitate censorship by allowing the censor to determine which traffic to block. DNS queries, the "host" request header in an HTTP request, and the Server Name Indication (SNI) in a Transport Layer Security (TLS) ClientHello are all examples of protocol elements that can travel in plaintext and be used by censors to identify what content a user is trying to access <xref target="RFC9505" format="default"/>. Protocol mechanisms such as Encrypted ClientHello <xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-esni" format="default"/> or DNS over HTTPS <xref target="RFC8484" format="default"/> that encrypt metadata provide some level of resistance to this type of protocol inspection. Full traffic encryption systems, such as Tor <eref target="https://torproject.org" brackets="angle"/>, can also be used by people to access otherwise censored resources.</t>
        <t>Example: As noted above, one way to censor web traffic is to require the server to block it or require ISPs to block requests to the server. In HTTP, denial or restriction of access can be made apparent by the use of status code 451, which allows server operators and intermediaries to operate with greater transparency in circumstances where issues of law or public policy affect their operation <xref target="RFC7725" format="default"/>. If a protocol potentially enables censorship, protocol designers should strive towards creating error codes that capture different scenarios (e.g., blocked due to administrative policy, unavailable because of legal requirements, etc.) to minimize ambiguity for end users.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to political participation</li>
          <li>Right to participate in cultural life, arts, and science</li>
          <li>Right to freedom of assembly and association</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="outcome-transparency" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Outcome Transparency</name>
        <t>Question(s): Are the intended and foreseen effects of your protocol documented and easily comprehensible? Have you described the central use case(s) for your protocol with a clear description of expected behavior and how it may, or may not, impact other protocols, implementations, user expectations, or behavior? Have you reviewed other protocols that solve similar problems, or made use of similar mechanisms, to see if there are lessons that can be learned from their use and misuse?</t>
        <t>Explanation: Certain technical choices may have unintended consequences.</t>
        <t>Example: Lack of authenticity may lead to lack of integrity and negative externalities; of which, spam is an example. Lack of data that could be used for billing and accounting can lead to so-called "free" arrangements that obscure the actual costs and distribution of the costs, for example, the barter arrangements that are commonly used for Internet interconnection, and the commercial exploitation of personal data for targeted advertising, which is the most common funding model for the so-called "free" services such as search engines and social networks. Unexpected outcomes might not be technical but rather architectural, social, or economic. Therefore, it is of importance to document the intended outcomes and other possible outcomes that have been considered.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to privacy</li>
          <li>Right to freedom of assembly and association</li>
          <li>Right to access to information</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="accessibility" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Accessibility</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Is your protocol designed to provide an enabling environment for all? Have you looked at the W3C Web Accessibility Initiative for examples and guidance <xref target="W3CAccessibility" format="default"/>?</t>
        <t>Explanation:
Sometimes in the design of protocols, websites, web technologies, or web tools, barriers are created that exclude people from using the Web. The Internet should be designed to work for all people, whatever their hardware, software, language, culture, location, or physical or mental ability. When the Internet technologies meet this goal, it will be accessible to people with a diverse range of hearing, movement, sight, and cognitive ability <xref target="W3CAccessibility" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Example:
The HTML protocol as defined in <xref target="HTML" format="default"/> specifically requires that every image must have an alt attribute (with a few exceptions) to ensure images are accessible for people who cannot themselves decipher non-text content in web pages.</t>
        <t>Another example is the work done in the AVT and AVTCORE Working Groups in the IETF that enables text conversation in multimedia, text telephony, wireless multimedia, and video communications for sign language and lipreading (i.e., <xref target="RFC9071" format="default"/>).</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to non-discrimination</li>
          <li>Right to freedom of assembly and association</li>
          <li>Right to education</li>
          <li>Right to political participation</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="decentralization" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Decentralization</name>
        <t>Question(s):
Can your protocol be implemented without a single point of control? If applicable, can your protocol be deployed in a federated manner? Does your protocol create additional centralized points of control?</t>
        <t>Explanation:
Decentralization is one of the central technical concepts of the architecture of the Internet and is embraced as such by the IETF <xref target="RFC3935" format="default"/>. It refers to the absence or minimization of centralized points of control, a feature that is assumed to make it easy for new users to join and new uses to unfold <xref target="Ziewitz" format="default"/>. It also reduces issues surrounding single points of failure and distributes the network such that it continues to function even if one or several nodes are disabled. With the commercialization of the Internet in the early 1990s, there has been a slow move away from decentralization, to the detriment of the technical benefits of having a decentralized Internet. For a more detailed discussion of this topic, please see <xref target="I-D.arkko-iab-internet-consolidation" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Example:
The bits traveling the Internet are increasingly susceptible to monitoring and censorship from both governments and ISPs as well as third (malicious) parties. The ability to monitor and censor is further enabled by the increased centralization of the network that creates central infrastructure points that can be tapped into. The creation of peer-to-peer networks and the development of voice-over-IP protocols using peer-to-peer technology in combination with Distributed Hash Table (DHT) for scalability are examples of how protocols can preserve decentralization <xref target="I-D.pouwelse-censorfree-scenarios" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to freedom of expression</li>
          <li>Right to freedom of assembly and association</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="remedy" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Remedy</name>
        <t>Question(s): Can your protocol facilitate a negatively impacted party's right to remedy without disproportionately impacting other parties' human rights, especially their right to privacy?</t>
        <t>Explanation: Providing access to remedy by states and corporations is a part of the UN Guiding Principles on Business and Human Rights <xref target="UNGP" format="default"/>. Access to remedy may help victims of human rights violations in seeking justice or allow law enforcement agencies to identify a possible violator. However, current mechanisms in protocols that try to enable "attribution" to individuals impede the exercise of the right to privacy. The former UN Special Rapporteur for Freedom of Expression has also argued that anonymity is an inherent part of freedom of expression <xref target="Kaye" format="default"/>. Considering the potential adverse impact of attribution on the right to privacy and freedom of expression, enabling attribution on an individual level is most likely not consistent with human rights.</t>
        <t>Example: Adding personally identifiable information to data streams as a means to enable the human right to remedy might help in identifying a violator of human rights and provide access to remedy, but this would disproportionately affect all users right to privacy, anonymous expression, and association.
Furthermore, there are some recent advances in enabling abuse detection in end-to-end encrypted messaging systems, which also carry some risk to users' privacy <xref target="Messenger-franking" format="default"/> <xref target="Hecate" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Impacts:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Right to remedy</li>
          <li>Right to security</li>
          <li>Right to privacy</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="misc-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Miscellaneous Considerations</name>
        <t>Question(s): Have you considered potential negative consequences (individual or societal) that your protocol or document might have?</t>
        <t>Explanation: Publication of a particular RFC under a certain status has consequences. Publication as an Internet Standard as part of the Standards Track may signal to implementers that the specification has a certain level of maturity, operational experience, and consensus.  Similarly, publication of a specification as an experimental document not part of the Standards Track would signal to the community that the document "may not be intended to be an Internet Standard, or it may be intended for eventual standardization but not yet ready" for wide deployment <xref target="RFC2026" format="default"/>. The extent of the deployment, and consequently its overall impact on end users, may depend on the document status presented in the RFC. See <xref target="RFC2026" format="default"/> and updates to it for a fuller explanation.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="document-status" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Document Status</name>
      <t>This research group document lays out best practices and guidelines for human rights reviews of network protocols, architectures, and other Internet-Drafts and RFCs.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>Article three of the "Universal Declaration of Human Rights" reads: "Everyone has the right to life, liberty and security of person" <xref target="UDHR" format="default"/>. This article underlines the importance of security and its interrelation with human life and liberty; but since human rights are indivisible, interrelated, and interdependent, security is also closely linked to other human rights and freedoms. This document seeks to strengthen human rights, freedoms, and security by relating and translating these concepts to concepts and practices as they are used in Internet protocol and architecture development. The aim of this is to secure human rights and thereby improve the sustainability, usability, and effectiveness of the network. The document seeks to achieve this by providing guidelines as done in <xref target="conducting-human-rights-reviews" format="default"/> of this document.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="research-group-information" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Research Group Information</name>
      <t>The discussion list for the IRTF Human Rights Protocol Considerations
      Research Group is located at the e-mail address: <eref
      target="mailto:hrpc@ietf.org" brackets="angle"/>.</t>
      <t>Information on the group and information on how to subscribe to the
      list is at: <eref target="https://www.irtf.org/mailman/listinfo/hrpc"
      brackets="angle"/>.</t>
      <t>Archives of the list can be found at: <eref
      target="https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/browse/hrpc/"
      brackets="angle"/>.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>

    <displayreference target="I-D.pouwelse-censorfree-scenarios" to="Pouwelse"/> 
    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-madinas-mac-address-randomization" to="MAC-ADDRESS-RANDOMIZATION"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.arkko-iab-internet-consolidation" to="Arkko"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-tls-esni" to="TLS-ESNI"/>

    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>

      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9293.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1958.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1984.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2026.xml"/> 
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2277.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3365.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3724.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3935.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8179.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4101.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8981.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4949.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5321.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5646.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6108.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6365.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6701.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6973.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7258.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7624.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7725.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7844.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7858.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8280.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8484.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8980.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7754.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9000.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9071.xml"/>


      <reference anchor="UDHR" target="https://www.un.org/en/about-us/universal-declaration-of-human-rights">
        <front>
          <title>Universal Declaration of Human Rights</title>
          <author>
            <organization>United Nations General Assembly</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="1948"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Orwat">
        <front>
          <title>Values and Networks: Steps Toward Exploring their Relationships</title>
          <author initials="C." surname="Orwat">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Bless">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="May" year="2016"/>
        </front>
        <refcontent>ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review, vol. 46, no. 2, pp 25-31</refcontent>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2935634.2935640"/>
      </reference>

<reference anchor="Ziewitz">
        <front>
          <title>A Prehistory of Internet Governance</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Ziewitz">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="I." surname="Brown">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="2013"/>
        </front>
        <refcontent>Research Handbook on Governance of the Internet, edited by Ian Brown. Cheltenham: Edward Elgar Publishing</refcontent>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.4337/9781849805025.00008"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Note-well" target="https://www.ietf.org/about/note-well/">
        <front>
          <title>Note Well</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IETF</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

   <reference anchor="IRP" target="https://internetrightsandprinciples.org/campaign/">
        <front>
          <title>10 Internet Rights &amp; Principles</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Internet Rights and Principles Dynamic Coalition</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ICCPR" target="https://www.ohchr.org/en/instruments-mechanisms/instruments/international-covenant-civil-and-political-rights">
        <front>
          <title>International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights</title>
          <author>
            <organization>United Nations General Assembly</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="1966"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Saltzer">
        <front>
          <title>End-to-end arguments in system design</title>
          <author initials="J. H." surname="Saltzer">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="D. P." surname="Reed">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="D. D." surname="Clark">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="1984"/>
        </front>
        <refcontent>ACM Transactions on Computer Systems, vol. 2, no. 4, pp 277-288</refcontent>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/357401.357402"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ICESCR" target="https://www.ohchr.org/en/instruments-mechanisms/instruments/international-covenant-economic-social-and-cultural-rights">
        <front>
          <title>International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</title>
          <author>
            <organization>United Nations General Assembly</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="1966"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

<reference anchor="Penney" target="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2769645">
        <front>
          <title>Chilling Effects: Online Surveillance and Wikipedia Use</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Penney">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="September" year="2016"/>
        </front>
	<refcontent>Berkeley Technology Law Journal, vol. 31, no. 1, pp 117-182</refcontent>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.15779/Z38SS13"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="UNHRC2016" target="https://digitallibrary.un.org/record/845728?ln=en">
        <front>
          <title>The promotion, protection and enjoyment of human rights on the Internet</title>
          <author>
            <organization>United Nations Human Rights Council</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="June" year="2016"/>
        </front>
	<refcontent>A/HRC/32/L.20</refcontent> 
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="W3Ci18nDef" target="https://www.w3.org/International/questions/qa-i18n.en">
        <front>
          <title>Localization vs. Internationalization</title>
          <author initials="R" surname="Ishida">
            <organization>W3C</organization>
          </author>
	  <author initials="S" surname="Miller">
	    <organization>Boeing</organization>
	  </author>
          <date month="December" year="2005"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Patent-policy" target="https://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/">
        <front>
          <title>W3C Patent Policy</title>
          <author initials="D" surname="Weitzner">
            <organization>W3C</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2004"/>
        </front>
	<refcontent>W3C Recommendation</refcontent>
      </reference>

<!-- [I-D.pouwelse-censorfree-scenarios] IESG state: Expired Long way used to include editor role-->
<reference anchor="I-D.pouwelse-censorfree-scenarios" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-pouwelse-censorfree-scenarios-02">
<front>
<title>Media without censorship (CensorFree) scenarios</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Pouwelse" fullname="Johan Pouwelse" role="editor">
<organization>Delft University of Technology</organization>
</author>
<date month="October" day="22" year="2012"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-pouwelse-censorfree-scenarios-02"/>
</reference>

<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9505.xml"/>

<!-- [I-D.ietf-madinas-mac-address-randomization] IESG state: RFC Ed Queue Long way used to include editor role-->
<reference anchor="I-D.ietf-madinas-mac-address-randomization" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-ietf-madinas-mac-address-randomization-15">
<front>
<title>Randomized and Changing MAC Address State of Affairs</title>
<author initials="J. C." surname="Ziga" fullname="Juan-Carlos Ziga">
<organization>CISCO</organization>
</author>
<author initials="C. J." surname="Bernardos" fullname="Carlos J. Bernardos" role="editor">
<organization>Universidad Carlos III de Madrid</organization>
</author>
<author initials="A." surname="Andersdotter" fullname="Amelia Andersdotter">
<organization>Safespring AB</organization>
</author>
<date month="July" day="15" year="2024"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-madinas-mac-address-randomization-15"/>
</reference>

      <reference anchor="HTML" target="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/">
        <front>
          <title>HTML Living Standard</title>
          <author>
            <organization>WHATWG</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="August" year="2024"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Zittrain" target="https://dash.harvard.edu/handle/1/4455262">
        <front>
          <title>The Future of the Internet and How to Stop It</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Zittrain">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2008"/>
        </front>
        <refcontent>Yale University Press</refcontent>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="FIArch" target="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-642-30241-1_6">
        <front>
          <title>Design Principles for the Future Internet Architecture</title>
          <author surname="Papadimitriou" initials="D."/>
          <author surname="Zahariadis" initials="T."/>
          <author surname="Martinez-Julia" initials="P."/>
          <author surname="Papafili" initials="I."/>
          <author surname="Morreale" initials="V."/>
          <author surname="Torelli" initials="F."/>
          <author surname="Sales" initials="B."/>
          <author surname="Demeester" initials="P.">
          </author>
          <date year="2012" month="January"/>
        </front>
	<refcontent>The Future Internet, pp. 55-67</refcontent>
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1007/978-3-642-30241-1_6"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="W3CAccessibility" target="https://www.w3.org/standards/webdesign/accessibility">
        <front>
          <title>Accessibility</title>
          <author>
            <organization>W3C</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Newegg" target="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2013/11/newegg-on-trial-mystery-company-tqp-re-writes-the-history-of-encryption/">
        <front>
          <title>Newegg on trial: Mystery company TQP rewrites the history of encryption</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Mullin">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2013"/>
        </front>
        <refcontent>Ars Technica</refcontent>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Hill" target="http://www.apig.ch/UNIGE%20Catalog.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Partial Catalog of Human Rights Related to ICT Activities</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Hill">
            <organization>Association for Proper Internet Governance (APIG)</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="May" year="2014"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Kaye" target="https://digitallibrary.un.org/record/798709?v=pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Report of the Special Rapporteur on the Promotion and Protection of the Right to Freedom of Opinion and Expression, David Kaye</title>
          <author initials="D." surname="Kaye">
            <organization/>
          </author> 
          <date month="May" year="2015"/>
        </front>
        <refcontent>A/HRC/29/32</refcontent>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="UNGP" target="https://www.ohchr.org/en/publications/reference-publications/guiding-principles-business-and-human-rights">
        <front>
          <title>Guiding Principles on Business and Human Rights: Implementing the United Nations 'Protect, Respect and Remedy' Framework</title>
          <author>
            <organization>United Nations</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2012" month="January"/>
        </front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="UNHR" target="https://www.ohchr.org/en/core-international-human-rights-instruments-and-their-monitoring-bodies">
        <front>
          <title>The Core International Human Rights Instruments and their monitoring bodies</title>
          <author>
            <organization>United Nations</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="HR-RT" target="https://github.com/IRTF-HRPC/reviews">
        <front>
          <title>IRTF-HRPC / reviews</title>
          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2020"/>
        </front>
        <refcontent>commit 3f5fbff</refcontent>
      </reference>

<!-- [I-D.arkko-iab-internet-consolidation] IESG state: Expired -->
      <xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/draft-arkko-iab-internet-consolidation.xml"/>

      <reference anchor="FREAK" target="https://web.archive.org/web/20150304002021/https://freakattack.com/">
        <front>
          <title>Tracking the FREAK Attack</title>
          <author>
            <organization>University of Michigan</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      <refcontent>Wayback Machine archive</refcontent>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Logjam">
        <front>
          <title>Imperfect Forward Secrecy: How Diffie-Hellman Fails in Practice</title>
          <author initials="D." surname="Adrian">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="K." surname="Bhargavan">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="Z." surname="Durumeric">
            <organization/>
	  </author>                                                            
          <author initials="P." surname="Gaudry">
            <organization/>
	  </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Green">
            <organization/>
	  </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Halderman">
            <organization/>
          </author>                        
          <author initials="N." surname="Heninger">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="D." surname="Springall">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="E." surname="Thom">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="L." surname="Valenta">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="B." surname="VanderSloot">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="E." surname="Wustrow">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="S." surname="Zanella-Bguelin">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="P." surname="Zimmerman">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2015"/>
        </front>
        <refcontent>CCS '15: Proceedings of the 22nd ACM SIGSAC Conference on Computer and Communications Security, pp 5-17</refcontent>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2810103.2813707"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Hecate" target="https://www.usenix.org/conference/usenixsecurity22/presentation/issa">
        <front>
          <title>Hecate, Abuse Reporting in Secure Messengers with Sealed Sender</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Issa">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="N." surname="Alhaddad">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Varia">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2022" month="August"/>
        </front>
	<refcontent>31st USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security 22), pp 2335-2352</refcontent>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Messenger-franking" target="https://eprint.iacr.org/2017/664">
        <front>
          <title>Message Franking via Committing Authenticated Encryption</title>
          <author initials="P." surname="Grubbs">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Lu">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="T." surname="Ristenpart">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2017" month="July"/>
        </front>
	<refcontent>Cryptology ePrint Archive, Paper 2017/664</refcontent>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Email-hashing" target="https://freedom-to-tinker.com/2018/04/09/four-cents-to-deanonymize-companies-reverse-hashed-email-addresses/">
        <front>
          <title>Four cents to deanonymize: Companies reverse hashed email addresses</title>
          <author initials="G." surname="Acar">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="S." surname="Englehardt">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="A." surname="Narayanan">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="HTTPS-interception">
        <front>
          <title>The Security Impact of HTTPS Interception</title>
          <author initials="Z." surname="Durumeric">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="Z." surname="Ma">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="D." surname="Springall">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Barnes">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="N." surname="Sullivan">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="E." surname="Bursztein">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Bailey">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Halderman">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="V." surname="Paxson">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2017"/>
        </front>
        <refcontent>NDSS Symposium 2017</refcontent>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.14722/ndss.2017.23456"/>
      </reference>

      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9420.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8558.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8890.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7301.xml"/>

<!-- [I-D.ietf-tls-esni] IESG state: I-D Exists -->      
      <xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/draft-ietf-tls-esni.xml"/>

      <reference anchor="Jorgensen">
        <front>
          <title>An internet bill of rights</title>
          <author initials="R. F." surname="Jrgensen">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="2013"/>
        </front>
        <refcontent>Research Handbook on Governance of the Internet, edited by Ian Brown. Cheltenham: Edward Elgar Publishing</refcontent>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.4337/9781849805025.00022"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    
    <section anchor="acknowledgements" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>Thanks to:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li><t><contact fullname="Corinne Cath-Speth"/> for work on <xref
        target="RFC8280" format="default"/>.</t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Reese Enghardt"/>, <contact fullname="Joe
        Hall"/>, <contact fullname="Avri Doria"/>, <contact fullname="Joey
        Salazar"/>, <contact fullname="Corinne Cath-Speth"/>, <contact
        fullname="Farzaneh Badii"/>, <contact fullname="Sandra Braman"/>,
        <contact fullname="Colin Perkins"/>, <contact fullname="John
        Curran"/>, <contact fullname="Eliot Lear"/>, <contact
        fullname="Mallory Knodel"/>, <contact fullname="Brian Trammell"/>,
        <contact fullname="Jane Coffin"/>, <contact fullname="Eric
        Rescorla"/>, <contact fullname="Sofa Celi"/>, and the hrpc list for
        reviews and suggestions.</t></li>
        <li><t>Individuals who conducted human rights reviews for their work
        and feedback: <contact fullname="Amelia Andersdotter"/>, <contact
        fullname="Shane Kerr"/>, <contact fullname="Beatrice Martini"/>,
        <contact fullname="Karan Saini"/>, and <contact fullname="Shivan Kaul
        Sahib"/>.</t></li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
