<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
<!ENTITY zwsp "&#8203;">
<!ENTITY nbhy "&#8209;">
<!ENTITY wj "&#8288;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-calext-jscontact-16" number="9553" submissionType="IETF" consensus="true" category="std" xml:lang="en" obsoletes="" updates="" tocInclude="true" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.6.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="JSContact">JSContact: A JSON Representation of Contact Data</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9553"/>
    <author initials="R." surname="Stepanek" fullname="Robert Stepanek">
      <organization>Fastmail</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <extaddr>PO Box 234</extaddr>
          <street>Collins St. West</street>
          <city>Melbourne</city>
          <region>VIC</region>
          <code>8007</code>
          <country>Australia</country>
          <region/>
        </postal>
        <email>rsto@fastmailteam.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Loffredo" fullname="Mario Loffredo">
      <organization>IIT-CNR</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Via Moruzzi, 1</street>
          <city>Pisa</city>
          <code>56124</code>
          <country>Italy</country>
          <region/>
        </postal>
        <email>mario.loffredo@iit.cnr.it</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2024" month="May"/>
    <area>art</area>
    <workgroup>calext</workgroup>
    <keyword>JSON</keyword>
    <keyword>addressbook</keyword>
    <keyword>contacts</keyword>
    <keyword>cards</keyword>
    <keyword>VCARD</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This specification defines a data model and JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) representation of contact card
        information that can be used for data storage and exchange in address book or directory applications. It aims to
        be an alternative to the vCard data format and to be unambiguous, extendable, and simple to process. In contrast
        to the JSON-based jCard format, it is not a direct mapping from the vCard data model and expands semantics where
        appropriate. Two additional specifications define new vCard elements and how to convert between JSContact and
        vCard.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>This document defines a data model for contact card data normally used in address book or directory
        applications and services. It aims to be an alternative to the vCard data format <xref target="RFC6350" format="default"/>.
      </t>
      <t>The key design considerations for this data model are as follows:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>The data model and set of attributes should be mostly compatible with the model defined for the vCard data
          format
          <xref target="RFC6350" format="default"/>
          and extensions
          <xref target="RFC6473" format="default"/>
          <xref target="RFC6474" format="default"/>
          <xref target="RFC6715" format="default"/>
          <xref target="RFC6869" format="default"/>
          <xref target="RFC8605" format="default"/>. The specification should add new attributes or value types where
          appropriate. Not all existing vCard definitions need an equivalent in JSContact, especially if the vCard
          definition is considered to be obsolete or otherwise inappropriate. Conversion between the data formats need
          not fully preserve semantic meaning.
        </li>
        <li>The attributes of the card data must be described as simple key-value pairs to reduce the complexity of the
          representation of the card data.
        </li>
        <li>The data model should avoid all ambiguities and make it difficult to make mistakes during implementation.
        </li>
        <li>Extensions, such as new properties and components, <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> lead to a required update of this
          document.
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>The representation of this data model is defined in the Internet JSON (I-JSON) format <xref target="RFC7493" format="default"/>,
        which is a strict subset of the JSON data interchange format <xref target="RFC8259" format="default"/>. Using
        JSON is mostly a pragmatic choice: its widespread use makes JSContact easier to adopt, and the availability of
        production-ready JSON implementations eliminates a whole category of parser-related interoperability issues.
      </t>
      <section anchor="relation-to-vcard" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Motivation and Relation to vCard, jCard, and xCard</name>
        <t>The vCard data format
          <xref target="RFC6350"/>
          is an interchange format for contacts data between address book service providers and vendors. However, this
          format has gone through multiple specification iterations with only a subset of its deprecated <xref target="RFC2426">version 3
          </xref> being widely in use. Consequently, products and services use an internal contact data model that is
          richer than what they expose when serializing that information to vCard. In addition, service providers often
          use a proprietary JSON representation of contact data in their APIs.
        </t>
        <t>JSContact provides a standard JSON-based data model and representation of contact data as an alternative to
          proprietary formats.
        </t>
        <t>At the time of writing this document, several missing features in vCard were brought to the attention of the
          authors such as social media contacts, gender pronouns, and others. This highlights how vCard is not perceived
          as an evolving format and, consequently, hasn't been updated for about ten years. JSContact addresses these
          unmet demands and defines new vCard properties and parameters to allow interchanging them in both formats.
        </t>
        <t>Two additional documents define the relation of JSContact and vCard:
          <xref target="RFC9554" format="default"/>
          defines new vCard properties and parameters, and
          <xref target="RFC9555" format="default"/>
          defines how to convert JSContact data from and to vCard.
        </t>
        <t>The xCard
          <xref target="RFC6351" format="default"/>
          and jCard
          <xref target="RFC7095" format="default"/>
          specifications define alternative representations for vCard data in XML and JSON formats, respectively. Both
          explicitly aim to not change the underlying data model. Accordingly, they are regarded as equal to vCard in
          the context of this document.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="notational-conventions" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Notational Conventions</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be
    interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref
    target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as
    shown here.
        </t>
        <t>The ABNF definitions in this document use the notations of <xref target="RFC5234"/>. ABNF rules not defined in
          this document are defined in either
          <xref target="RFC5234"/>
          (such as the ABNF for CRLF, WSP, DQUOTE, VCHAR, ALPHA, and DIGIT) or <xref target="RFC6350"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="data-type-notations">
        <name>Data Type Notations</name>
        <t>This section introduces the notations and terminology used to define data types in JSContact.</t>
        <t>The underlying format for JSContact is JSON, so its data types also build on JSON values. The terms "object"
          and "array" as well as the four primitive types ("strings", "numbers", "booleans", and "null") are to be
          interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC8259" section="1"/>. All JSContact data <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
          valid according to the constraints given in <xref target="RFC7493">I-JSON</xref>. Unless otherwise noted, all
          member names in JSON objects and all string values are case-sensitive. Within the context of JSON objects, the
          term "key" is synonymous with "member name" as defined in <xref target="RFC8259" section="1"/>.
        </t>
        <section anchor="objects-and-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Objects and Properties</name>
          <t>JSContact defines data types for contact information such as addresses or names. This information typically
            consists of multiple related elements; for example, a personal name and surname together form a name. These
            related elements are organized in JSContact objects. A JSContact object is a JSON object that has the
            following:
          </t>
          <ol>
            <li>A unique type name registered in the IANA  <xref target="iana-type-registry">"JSContact Types"
              registry</xref>.
            </li>
            <li>One or more object members for which the name and allowed value types are specified. Such members are
              called "properties".
            </li>
            <li>One property named @type with a string value that matches the type name of the JSContact object. In
              general, this property does not need to be set explicitly as outlined in <xref target="prop-type"/>.
            </li>
          </ol>
          <t>The following sections specify how to define JSContact object types. Sections
            <xref target="validating-jscontact" format="counter"/>
            and
            <xref target="vendor-specific-extensions" format="counter"/>
            then define the exact requirements for property names.
          </t>
          <t>The next paragraph illustrates how a JSContact object is defined.  The names "Foo" and "baz" are only for demonstration and have no meaning outside the example.</t>
          <ul empty="true" anchor="example-foo-object">
            <li>
            <t>A Foo object has the following properties:</t>
            <dl spacing="normal">
              <dt>@type: String.</dt>
              <dd>The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Foo", if set.
              </dd>
              <dt>baz: Number (mandatory).</dt>
              <dd>The baz level of the contact. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be an integer greater than 0 and less
                than 10.
              </dd>
            </dl>
            </li>
          </ul>
	  <t>The above paragraph illustrates the following:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>It defines a JSContact object type named "Foo" that has two properties, named "@type" and "baz".</li>
            <li>The @type property adheres to the rules outlined in <xref target="prop-type"/>. Because of this, it is
              neither defined to be mandatory nor optional, as this depends on how the Foo object type is used.
            </li>
            <li>The baz property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be valid according to the definition of the Number type.
            </li>
            <li>The property has one attribute, "mandatory", which specifies that the property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
              present for a value of the Foo object type to be valid.
            </li>
            <li>The free-text description of the baz property describes the semantics and further restrictions for its
              values.
            </li>
          </ul>
        </section>
        <section anchor="type-signatures" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Type Signatures</name>
          <t>Type signatures are given for all JSON values and JSContact definitions in this document. The following
            conventions are used:
          </t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>String:</dt>
            <dd>The JSON string type.</dd>
            <dt>Number:</dt>
            <dd>The JSON number type.</dd>
            <dt>Boolean:</dt>
            <dd>The JSON boolean type.</dd>
            <dt>A[B]:</dt>
            <dd>A JSON object where all keys are of type A and all values are of type B.</dd>
            <dt>A[]:</dt>
            <dd>A JSON array of values of type A.</dd>
            <dt>A|B:</dt>
            <dd>The value is either of type A or of type B.</dd>
            <dt>*:</dt>
            <dd>The type is undefined (the value could be any type, although permitted values may be constrained by the
              context of this value).
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t><xref target="common-data-types"/>
            defines common data types, including signed or unsigned integers and dates.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="property-attributes" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Property Attributes</name>
          <t>Object properties may also have a set of attributes defined along with the type signature. These have the
            following meanings:
          </t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>mandatory:</dt>
            <dd>The property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set for an instance of this object to be valid.
            </dd>
            <dt>optional:</dt>
            <dd>The property can, but need not, be set for an instance of this object to be valid.</dd>
            <dt>default:</dt>
            <dd>This is followed by a JSON value. That value will be used for this property if it is omitted.</dd>
            <dt>defaultType:</dt>
            <dd>This is followed by the name of a JSContact object type. A property value of JSContact object type is
              expected to be of this named type, in case it omits the @type property.
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="prop-type" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>The @type Property</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact type of a JSON object. It <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> match the
              type name of the JSContact object of which the JSON object is an instance of.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>The purpose of the @type property is to help implementations identify which JSContact object type a given
            JSON object represents. Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> validate that JSON objects with this property
            conform to the specification of the JSContact object type of that name.
          </t>
          <t>In many cases, the @type property value is implied by where its object occurs in JSContact data. Assuming
            that both A and B are JSContact object types:
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li>An object that is set as the value for a property with type signature "A" <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> have the
              @type property set. If the @type property is not set, then its value is implied to be A by the property
              definition.
            </li>
            <li>An object that is set as the value for a property with type signature "A|B (defaultType: A)" <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> have the @type property set if it is an instance of A. It <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have the @type
              property set if it is an instance of B. If, instead, the defaultType attribute is not defined, then the
              @type property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> also be set for A.
            </li>
            <li>An object that is not the value of a property, such as the topmost object in JSON data (directly or as a
              member of an array), <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have the @type property set.
            </li>
          </ul>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="common-data-types" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Common Data Types</name>
        <t>In addition to the standard JSON data types, a couple of additional data types are common to the definitions
          of JSContact objects and properties.
        </t>
        <section anchor="id" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Id</name>
          <t>Where "Id" is given as a data type, it means a String of at least 1 and a maximum of 255 octets in size,
            and it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only contain characters from the "URL and Filename Safe" base64url alphabet, as
            defined in <xref target="RFC4648" sectionFormat="of" section="5"/>, excluding the pad character ("="). This
            means the allowed characters are the ASCII alphanumeric characters ("A-Za-z0-9"), hyphen ("-"), and
            underscore ("_").
          </t>
          <t>In many places in JSContact, a JSON map is used where the map keys are of type Id and the map values are
            all the same type of object. This construction represents an unordered set of objects, with the added
            advantage that each entry has a name (the corresponding map key). This allows for more concise patching of
            objects and, when applicable, for the objects in question to be referenced from other objects within the
            JSContact object. The map keys <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be preserved across multiple versions of the JSContact
            object.
          </t>
          <t>Unless otherwise specified for a particular property, there are no uniqueness constraints on an Id value
            (other than, of course, the requirement that you cannot have two values with the same key within a single
            JSON map). For example, two <xref target="card">Card</xref> objects might use the same Ids in their
            respective photos properties. Or within the same Card, the same Id could appear in the emails and phones
            properties. These situations do not imply any semantic connections among the objects.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="int-unsignedint" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Int and UnsignedInt</name>
          <t>Where "Int" is given as a data type, it means an integer in the range -2<sup>53</sup>+1 &lt;= value &lt;= 2<sup>
            53</sup>-1, which is the safe range for integers stored in a floating-point double, represented as a JSON
            Number.
          </t>
          <t>Where "UnsignedInt" is given as a data type, it means an integer in the range 0 &lt;= value &lt;= 2<sup>
            53</sup>-1 represented as a JSON Number.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="patchobject" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>PatchObject</name>
          <t>A PatchObject is of type "String[*]" and represents an unordered set of patches on a JSON object. Each key
            is a path represented in a subset of the JSON Pointer format <xref target="RFC6901"/>. The paths have an
            implicit leading "/", so each key is prefixed with "/" before applying the JSON Pointer evaluation
            algorithm.
          </t>
          <t>A patch within a PatchObject is only valid if all the following conditions apply:</t>
          <ol>
            <li>The pointer <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> reference inside an array, but if the last reference token in the pointer
              is an array index, then the patch value <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be null. The pointer <bcp14>MUST NOT
              </bcp14> use "-" as an array index in any of its reference tokens (i.e., you <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> insert/delete
              from an array, but you <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> replace the contents of its existing members. To add or remove
              members, one needs to replace the complete array value).
            </li>
            <li>All reference tokens prior to the last (i.e., the value after the final slash) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> already
              exist as values in the object being patched. If the last reference token is an array index, then a member
              at this index <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> already exist in the referenced array.
            </li>
            <li>There <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be two patches in the PatchObject where the pointer of one is the prefix
              of the pointer of the other, e.g., "addresses/1/city" and "addresses".
            </li>
            <li>The value for the patch <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be valid for the property being set (of the correct type and
              obeying any other applicable restrictions), or if null, the property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be optional.
            </li>
          </ol>
          <t>The value associated with each pointer determines how to apply that patch:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>If null, remove the property from the patched object. If the key is not present in the parent, this is a
              no-op.
            </li>
            <li>If non-null, set the value given as the value for this property (this may be a replacement or addition
              to the object being patched).
            </li>
          </ul>
          <t>A PatchObject does not define its own <xref target="prop-type">@type</xref> property. Instead, the @type
            property in a patch <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be handled as any other patched property value.
          </t>
          <t>Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reject a PatchObject in its entirety if any of its patches are invalid.
            Implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> apply partial patches.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="resource" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Resource</name>
          <t>The Resource data type defines a resource associated with the entity represented by the Card, identified by
            a URI <xref target="RFC3986" format="default"/>. Later in this document, several property definitions refer
            to the Resource type as the basis for their property-specific value types. The Resource type defines the
            properties that are common to all of them. Property definitions making use of Resource <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> define
            additional properties for their value types.
          </t>
          <t>A Resource object has the following properties:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact type of the object.  The value <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be "Resource"; instead, the value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the name
            of a concrete resource type (see <xref target="resource-properties"/>).</dd>
            <dt>kind: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The kind of the resource. The allowed values are defined in the property definition that makes use of the
              Resource type. Some property definitions may change this property from being optional to mandatory.
            </dd>
            <dt>uri: String (mandatory).</dt>
            <dd>
              The resource value. This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a <em>URI</em> as defined in <xref target="RFC3986" sectionFormat="of" section="3"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>mediaType: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The media type <xref target="RFC2046" format="default"/> of the resource identified by the uri property value.
            </dd>
            <dt>contexts: String[Boolean] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The contexts in which to use this resource. Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>pref: UnsignedInt (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The preference of the resource in relation to other resources. Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>label: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              A custom label for the value. Also see <xref target="prop-label"/>.
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="utcdatetime" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>UTCDateTime</name>
          <t>The UTCDateTime type is a String in "date-time" format <xref target="RFC3339" format="default"/>, with
            further restrictions that any letters <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be in uppercase and the time offset <bcp14>MUST
            </bcp14> be the character "Z". Fractional second values <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be included unless they are
            non-zero, and they <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> have trailing zeros to ensure there is only a single
            representation for each date-time.
          </t>
          <t>For example, "2010-10-10T10:10:10.003Z" is conformant, but "2010-10-10T10:10:10.000Z" is invalid; the
            correct encoding is "2010-10-10T10:10:10Z".
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="common-properties">
        <name>Common Properties</name>
        <t>Most of the properties in this document are specific to a single JSContact object type. Such properties are
          defined along with the respective object type. The properties in this section are common to multiple data
          types and are defined here to avoid repetition. Note that these properties <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only be set for
          a JSContact object if they are explicitly mentioned as allowable for this object type.
        </t>
        <section anchor="prop-contexts" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>contexts</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>contexts: String[Boolean].</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>The contexts in which to use the contact information. For example, someone might have distinct phone numbers for work and private contexts and may set the desired context on the respective phone number in the <xref target="phones"> phones </xref> property. </t>
              <t>This section defines common contexts. Additional contexts may be defined in the properties or data
                types that make use of this property. The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated
                </xref> common context values are:
              </t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li>private: the contact information that may be used in a private context.</li>
                <li>work: the contact information that may be used in a professional context.</li>
              </ul>
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="prop-label" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>label</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>label: String.</dt>
            <dd>The labels associated with the contact data. Such labels may be set for
              phone numbers, email addresses, and other resources. Typically, these labels are displayed along with their
              associated contact data in graphical user interfaces. Note that succinct labels are best for proper
              display on small graphical interfaces and screens.
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="prop-pref" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>pref</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>pref: UnsignedInt.</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>A preference order for contact information. For example, a person may
                have two email addresses and prefer to be contacted with one of them.
              </t>
              <t>The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be in the range of 1 to 100. Lower values correspond to a higher level of
                preference, with 1 being most preferred. If no preference is set, then the contact information <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be interpreted as being least preferred.
              </t>
              <t>Note that the preference is only defined in relation to contact information of the same type. For
                example, the preference orders within emails and phone numbers are independent of each other.
              </t>
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="prop-phonetic" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>phonetic</name>
          <t>The following properties define how to pronounce a value in the language indicated in the Card <xref target="language">language
          </xref> property or the language tag of its <xref target="localizations">localizations</xref>. Exemplary uses
            of these properties are defining how to pronounce Japanese names and romanizing Mandarin or Cantonese name
            and address components. The properties are defined as follows:
          </t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>phonetic: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The phonetic representation of a value.
              Any script language subtag in the Card <xref target="language">language</xref> property <bcp14>MUST
            </bcp14> be ignored and not used with the phonetic property. If this property is set, then at least one of
              the phoneticScript or phoneticSystem properties that relate to this value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set.
            </dd>
            <dt>phoneticScript: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The script used in the value of the related phonetic property. This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a valid script
              subtag as defined in <xref target="RFC5646" section="2.2.3"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>phoneticSystem: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
                The phonetic system used in the related value of the phonetic property. The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated
              </xref> values are:
              </t>
              <ul>
                <li>ipa: denotes the <xref target="IPA">International Phonetic Alphabet</xref>.
                </li>
                <li>jyut: denotes the Cantonese romanization system "Jyutping".</li>
                <li>piny: denotes the Standard Mandarin romanization system "Hanyu Pinyin".</li>
              </ul>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>The relation between the phoneticSystem, phoneticScript, and phonetic properties is type-specific. This
            specification defines this relation in the <xref target="name">Name</xref> and <xref target="address">
              Address
            </xref> object types, respectively.
          </t>
          <t>The following example illustrates the phonetic property for a <xref target="name-prop">name</xref>:
          </t>
          <figure anchor="example-phonetic">
            <name>Example of a phonetic Property for the Name "John Smith" as Pronounced in the USA</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"name": {
  "components": [{
    "kind": "given",
    "value": "John",
    "phonetic": "/ˈdʒɑːn/"
  }, {
    "kind": "surname",
    "value": "Smith",
    "phonetic": "/smɪθ/"
  }],
  "phoneticSystem": "ipa"
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="internationalization">
        <name>Internationalization</name>
        <t>JSContact aims to be used for international contacts and address book data. Notably, text values such as
          names and addresses are likely to cover a wide range of languages and cultures. This section describes
          internationalization for free-form text values as well as Uniform Resource Identifiers (URIs).
        </t>
        <section>
          <name>Free-Form Text</name>
          <t>Properties having free-form text values <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> contain any valid sequence of Unicode characters
            encoded as a JSON string. Such values can contain unidirectional left-to-right and right-to-left text, as
            well as bidirectional text using Unicode Directional Formatting Characters as described in Section 2 of <xref target="UBiDi"/>. Implementations setting bidirectional text <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> make sure that each
            property value complies with the requirements of the Unicode Bidirectional Algorithm. Implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> assume that text values of adjacent properties are processed or displayed as a combined string; for
            example, the values of a given name component and a surname component may or may not be rendered together.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>URIs</name>
          <t>Several properties require their string value to be a URI as defined in <xref target="RFC3986"/>.
            Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> make sure to use proper percent-encoding for URIs that cannot be
            represented using unreserved URI characters.
            <xref target="RFC3987" section="3.1"/>
            defines how to convert Internationalized Resource Identifiers to URIs.
            JSContact makes no recommendation on how to display URIs, but the WHATWG URL Living Standard (see
            "Internationalization and special characters" (Section 4.8.3) of <xref target="WHATWG-URL"/>) provides
            guidance for URLs found in the context of a web browser.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="validating-jscontact">
        <name>Validating JSContact</name>
        <t>This specification distinguishes between three kinds of properties regarding validation: IANA-registered
          properties and unknown properties, which are defined in this section, and vendor-specific properties, which
          are defined in <xref target="vendor-specific-properties"/>. A JSContact object is invalid if any of its
          properties are invalid.
        </t>
        <t>This document defines whether each property is mandatory or optional. A mandatory property <bcp14>MUST
        </bcp14> be present for a JSContact object to be valid. An optional property does not need to be present. The
          values of both required and optional properties <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> adhere to the data type and definition of
          that property.
        </t>
        <section anchor="case-sensitivity">
          <name>Case-Sensitivity</name>
          <t>All property names, object type names, and enumerated values are case-sensitive, unless explicitly stated
            otherwise in their definitions. Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> handle a JSContact object as invalid if
            a type name, property name, or enumerated value only differs in case from one defined for any JSContact
            version known to that implementation. This applies regardless of what JSContact version the Card object
            defines in its <xref target="prop-version">version</xref> property.
            <xref target="unknown-properties"/>
            defines how to handle unknown properties.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-registered-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>IANA-Registered Properties</name>
          <t>
            An IANA-registered property is any property that has been registered according to the IANA property registry
            rules as outlined in <xref target="iana-considerations"/>. All properties defined in this specification,
            including their object value types and enumerated values, are registered at IANA.
          </t>
          <t>
            Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> validate IANA-registered properties in JSContact data, unless they are
            unknown to the implementation (<xref target="unknown-properties"/>). They <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reject invalid
            IANA-registered properties. A property is invalid if its name matches the name of an IANA-registered
            property but the value violates its definition according to the JSContact specification version defined in
            the Card <xref target="prop-version">version</xref> property.
          </t>
          <t>
            IANA-registered property names <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain ASCII control characters (U+0000 to U+001F,
            U+007F), the COLON (U+003A), or the QUOTATION MARK (U+0022). They <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only contain ASCII
            alphanumeric characters that match the ALPHA and DIGIT rules defined in
            <xref target="RFC5234" section="B.1"/>
            or the COMMERCIAL AT (U+0040) character. IANA-registered property names <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be notated in
            lower camel case.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="reserved-properties">
          <name>Reserved Properties</name>
          <t>IANA-registered properties can be reserved (<xref target="iana-registry-policy"/>).  Implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> set properties having a reserved name in JSContact
            objects for which this property is reserved or all objects if the property context in the registry is "not applicable".
            Reserved properties have no type, and their type signature is "not applicable".  Any JSContact object including a property that is reserved in context of this object <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be considered invalid.</t>
          <t>This document reserves one property as described below.</t>
          <section anchor="prop-extra" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>extra</name>
            <dl spacing="normal">
              <dt>extra: not applicable.</dt>
              <dd>The reserved property "extra" provides implementors with a property name that is certain to never
                occur as a property in any JSContact object. Implementations might want to map unknown or vendor-specific
                properties to a variable with this name, but this is implementation-specific.
              </dd>
            </dl>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section anchor="unknown-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Unknown Properties</name>
          <t>
            Implementations may encounter JSContact data where a property name is unknown to that implementation but the
            name adheres to the syntactic restrictions of IANA-registered property names. Implementations <bcp14>MUST
          </bcp14> make sure that such a name does not violate the case-sensitivity rules defined in <xref target="case-sensitivity"/>. If the property name is valid, then implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT
          </bcp14> treat such properties as invalid. Instead, they <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> preserve them in the JSContact
            object.
          </t>
          <t>Implementations that create or update JSContact data <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only set IANA-registered
            properties or vendor-specific properties. Preserving properties that are unknown to the implementation is to
            allow applications and services to interoperate without data loss, even if not all of them implement the
            same set of JSContact extensions.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="enumerated-values" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Enumerated Values</name>
          <t>Several properties in this document restrict their allowed values to a list of String values. These values
            are case-sensitive. If not noted otherwise for a specific property, the initial list of values for such
            properties is registered at IANA in the <xref target="iana-enum-registry">"JSContact Enum Values"
              registry</xref>. Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only set IANA-registered or <xref target="vendor-specific-values">vendor-specific
            </xref> values for such properties.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="vendor-specific-extensions">
        <name>Vendor-Specific Extensions</name>
        <t>Vendors may extend properties and values for experimentation or to store contacts data that is only useful
          for a single service or application. Such extensions are not meant for interoperation. If, instead,
          interoperation is desired, vendors are strongly encouraged to define and register new properties, types, and
          values at IANA as defined in <xref target="iana-considerations"/>.
          <xref target="iana-registered-properties"/>
          defines the naming conventions for IANA-registered elements.
        </t>
        <section anchor="vendor-specific-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Vendor-Specific Properties</name>
          <t>
            Vendor-specific property names <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> start with a vendor-specific prefix followed by a name,
            as produced by the "v-extension" ABNF below. The prefix and name together form the property name. The
            vendor-specific prefix <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a domain name under control of the service or application that
            sets the property, but it need not resolve in the Domain Name System
            <xref target="RFC1034"/>
            <xref target="RFC1035"/>. The prefix "ietf.org" and its subdomain names are reserved for IETF
            specifications. The name <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain the TILDE (U+007E) and SOLIDUS (U+002F) characters,
            as these require special escaping when encoding a JSON Pointer
            <xref target="RFC6901"/>
            for that property.
          </t>
          <t>
            Vendor-specific properties <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be set in any JSContact object. Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> preserve vendor-specific properties in JSContact data, irrespective if they know their use. They <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> reject the property value as invalid, unless they are in control of the vendor-specific property as
            outlined in the above paragraph.
          </t>
          <t>The ABNF rule "v-extension" formally defines valid vendor-specific property names. Note that the vendor
            prefix allows for more values than Internationalized Domain Names (IDNs) <xref target="RFC9499"/>; therefore,
            JSContact implementations can simply validate property names without implementing the full set of rules that
            apply to domain names.
          </t>
          <figure anchor="vendor-property-abnf">
            <name>ABNF Rules for Vendor-Specific Property Names</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="abnf"><![CDATA[
v-extension = v-prefix ":" v-name

v-prefix = v-label *("." v-label)

v-label = alnum-int / alnum-int *(alnum-int / "-") alnum-int

alnum-int = ALPHA / DIGIT / NON-ASCII
  ; see RFC 6350, Section 3.3

v-name = 1*(WSP / "!" / %x23-2e / %x30-7d / NON-ASCII)
  ; any characters except CTLs, DQUOTE, SOLIDUS, and TILDE
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The value of vendor-specific properties can be any valid JSON value, and naming restrictions do not apply to
            such values. Specifically, if the property value is a JSON object, then the keys of such objects need not be
            named as vendor-specific properties, as illustrated in <xref target="vendor-property-example"/>:
          </t>
          <figure anchor="vendor-property-example">
            <name>Examples of Vendor-Specific Properties</name>
            <sourcecode type=""><![CDATA[
"example.com:foo": "bar",
"example.com:foo2": {
  "bar": "baz"
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="vendor-specific-values" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Vendor-Specific Values</name>
          <t>
            Some JSContact IANA-registered properties allow their values to be vendor-specific. One such example is the  <xref target="kind">"kind"
          </xref> property, which enumerates its standard values but also allows for arbitrary vendor-specific values.
            Such vendor-specific values <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be valid "v-extension" values as defined in <xref target="vendor-specific-properties"/>. The example in
            <xref target="vendor-value-example"/>
            illustrates this:
          </t>
          <figure anchor="vendor-value-example">
            <name>Example of a Vendor-Specific Value</name>
            <sourcecode><![CDATA[
"kind": "example.com:baz"
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
          <t>
            Vendors are strongly encouraged to specify a new standard value once a vendor-specific one turns out to also
            be useful for other systems.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="versioning">
        <name>Versioning</name>
        <t>Every instance of a JSContact <xref target="card">Card</xref> indicates which JSContact version its
          IANA-registered properties and values are based on.
          The version is indicated both in the <xref target="prop-version">version</xref> property within the Card and
          in the <xref target="iana-media-type">version</xref> parameter of the JSContact media type. All
          IANA-registered elements indicate the version at which they were introduced or obsoleted.
        </t>
        <t>A JSContact version consists of a major and minor version.</t>
        <t>Differing major version values indicate substantial differences in JSContact semantics and format.
          Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be prepared for property definitions and other JSContact elements that
          differ in a backwards-incompatible manner.
        </t>
        <t>Differing minor version values indicate additions that enrich JSContact data but do not introduce
          backwards-incompatible changes. Typically, these are new property enum values or properties with a narrow
          semantic scope. A new minor version <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> require implementations to change their processing
          of JSContact data. Changing the major version number resets the minor version number to zero.
        </t>
        <section anchor="version-format-and-reqs">
          <name>Version Format and Requirements</name>
          <t>A version value starts with the numeric major version, followed by the FULL STOP character (U+002E),
            followed by the numeric minor version. Later versions are numerically higher than former versions, with the
            major version being more significant than the minor version. A version value is produced by the following
            ABNF:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <name>The ABNF for JSContact Version Values</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="abnf"><![CDATA[
jsversion = 1*DIGIT "." 1*DIGIT
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="current-version">
          <name>Current Version</name>
          <t>This specification registers JSContact version value "1.0" (<xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="card" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Card</name>
      <t>This section defines the JSContact object type Card. A Card stores contact information, typically that of a
        person, organization, or company.
      </t>
      <t>Its media type is defined in <xref target="iana-media-type"/>.
      </t>
      <t><xref target="example-card"/>
        shows a basic Card for the person "John Doe". As the object is the topmost object in the JSON data, it has the
        @type property set according to the rules defined in <xref target="prop-type"/>.
      </t>
      <figure anchor="example-card">
        <name>Example of a Basic Card</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "@type": "Card",
  "version": "1.0",
  "uid": "22B2C7DF-9120-4969-8460-05956FE6B065",
  "kind": "individual",
  "name": {
    "components": [
      { "kind": "given", "value": "John" },
      { "kind": "surname", "value": "Doe" }
    ],
    "isOrdered": true
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
      </figure>
      <section anchor="metadata-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Metadata Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties about this instance of a Card such as its unique identifier, its creation
          date, and how it relates to other Cards and other metadata information.
        </t>
        <section anchor="cardtype" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>@type</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String (mandatory).</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact type of the Card object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Card".
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="prop-version" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>version</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>version: String (mandatory).</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact version of this Card. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of
              the IANA-registered JSContact Version values for the version property. Also see <xref target="current-version"/>.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-version">
            <name>Example for the version Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"version": "1.0"
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="created" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>created</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>created: UTCDateTime (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The date and time when the Card was created.</dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-created">
            <name>Example for the created Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"created": "2022-09-30T14:35:10Z"
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="kind" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>kind</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>kind: String (optional; default: "individual").</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>The kind of the entity the Card represents.</t>
              <t>The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:
              </t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li>individual: a single person</li>
                <li>group: a group of people or entities</li>
                <li>org: an organization</li>
                <li>location: a named location</li>
                <li>device: a device such as an appliance, a computer, or a network element</li>
                <li>application: a software application</li>
              </ul>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-kind">
            <name>Example for the kind Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"kind": "individual"
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="language" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>language</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>language: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>The language tag, as defined in <xref target="RFC5646"/>, that best describes the language used
                for text in the Card, optionally including additional information such as the script. Note that values <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be localized in the  <xref target="localizations">
                  localizations
                </xref> property.
              </t>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-language">
            <name>Example for the language Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"language": "de-AT"
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="members" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>members</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>members: String[Boolean] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>The set of Cards that are members of this group Card. Each key in the set is the uid
                property value of the member, and each boolean value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "true". If this property is
                set, then the value of the kind property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "group".
              </t>
              <t>The opposite is not true. A group Card will usually contain the members property to specify the members
                of the group, but it is not required to. A group Card without the members property can be considered an
                abstract grouping or one whose members are known empirically (e.g., "IETF Participants").
              </t>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-members">
            <name>Example for the members Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"kind": "group",
"name": {
  "full": "The Doe family"
},
"uid": "urn:uuid:ab4310aa-fa43-11e9-8f0b-362b9e155667",
"members": {
  "urn:uuid:03a0e51f-d1aa-4385-8a53-e29025acd8af": true,
  "urn:uuid:b8767877-b4a1-4c70-9acc-505d3819e519": true
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="prodId" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>prodId</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>prodId: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>The identifier for the product that created the Card. If set, the value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be at least
                one character long.
              </t>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-prodId">
            <name>Example for the prodId Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"prodId": "ACME Contacts App version 1.23.5"
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="relatedTo" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>relatedTo</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>relatedTo: String[Relation] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>The set of Card objects that relate to the Card. The value is a map, where each key is the uid property
                value of the related Card, and the value defines the relation.
              </t>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>The Relation object has the following properties:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal" newline="true">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Relation", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>relation: String[Boolean] (optional; default: empty Object).</dt>
	    <dd><t>
              The relationship of the related Card to the Card, defined as a set of relation types.
              The keys in the set define the relation type; the values for each key in the set <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "true".
              The relationship between the two objects is undefined if the set is empty.
              </t>
              <t>The initial list of <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> relation types matches the
                IANA-registered <xref target="IANA-vCard">TYPE</xref> parameter values of the vCard RELATED property
                (<xref target="RFC6350" section="6.6.6"/>):
              </t>
              <ul>
                <li>
                  acquaintance
                </li>
                <li>
                  agent
                </li>
                <li>
                  child
                </li>
                <li>
                  co-resident
                </li>
                <li>
                  co-worker
                </li>
                <li>
                  colleague
                </li>
                <li>
                  contact
                </li>
                <li>
                  crush
                </li>
                <li>
                  date
                </li>
                <li>
                  emergency
                </li>
                <li>
                  friend
                </li>
                <li>
                  kin
                </li>
                <li>
                  me
                </li>
                <li>
                  met
                </li>
                <li>
                  muse
                </li>
                <li>
                  neighbor
                </li>
                <li>
                  parent
                </li>
                <li>
                  sibling
                </li>
                <li>
                  spouse
                </li>
                <li>
                  sweetheart
                </li>
              </ul>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-relatedto">
            <name>Example for the relatedTo Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"relatedTo": {
  "urn:uuid:f81d4fae-7dec-11d0-a765-00a0c91e6bf6": {
    "relation": {
      "friend": true
    }
  },
  "8cacdfb7d1ffdb59@example.com": {
    "relation": {}
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="uid" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>uid</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>uid: String (mandatory).</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>An identifier that associates the object as the same across different systems, address books,
                and views. The value <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be a URN <xref target="RFC8141"/>, but for compatibility with
                <xref target="RFC6350"/>, it <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> also be a URI
                <xref target="RFC3986"/>
                or free-text value. The value of the URN <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be in the "uuid" namespace <xref target="RFC9562" format="default"/>. <xref target="RFC9562" format="default"/> describes multiple versions of Universally Unique IDentifiers (UUIDs); UUID version 4 is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>.
              </t>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-uid">
            <name>Example for the uid Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"uid": "urn:uuid:f81d4fae-7dec-11d0-a765-00a0c91e6bf6"
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="updated" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>updated</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>updated: UTCDateTime (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The date and time when the data in the Card was last modified.</dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-updated">
            <name>Example for the updated Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"updated": "2021-10-31T22:27:10Z"
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="name-and-organization-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Name and Organization Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties that name the entity represented by the Card and its related organizations
          and roles. It also describes how to refer to the entity represented by the Card in spoken or written language.
        </t>
        <section anchor="name-prop" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>name</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>name: Name (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The name of the entity represented by the Card. This can be any type of name, e.g., it can, but need
              not, be the legal name of a person.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <section anchor="name">
            <name>Name Object</name>
            <t>A Name object has the following properties:</t>
            <dl spacing="normal">
              <dt>@type: String.</dt>
              <dd>
                The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Name", if set.
              </dd>
              <dt>components: NameComponent[] (optional).</dt>
              <dd>
                <t>The <xref target="namecomponent">components</xref> making up this name. The components property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set if the full property is not set; otherwise, it <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be set. The
                  component list <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have at least one entry having a different kind property value than
                  "separator".
                </t>
                <t>Name components <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be ordered such that when their values are joined as a String,
                  a valid full name of the entity is produced. If so, implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> set the
                  isOrdered property value to "true".
                </t>
                <t>If the name components are ordered, then the defaultSeparator property and name components with the
                  kind property value set to "separator" give guidance on what characters to insert between components,
                  but implementations are free to choose any others. When lacking a separator, inserting a single space
                  character in between the name component values is a good choice.
                </t>
                <t>If, instead, the name components follow no particular order, then the isOrdered property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "false", the components property <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain a NameComponent with the
                  kind property value set to "separator", and the defaultSeparator property <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be
                  set.
                </t>
                <t><xref target="example-name-twoword"/>
                  shows an example for the name "Vincent van Gogh". Note how a single name component value may consist
                  of multiple words.
                </t>
                <figure anchor="example-name-twoword">
                  <name>Example of a Surname with Two Words</name>
                  <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"name": {
  "components": [
    { "kind": "given", "value": "Vincent" },
    { "kind": "surname", "value": "van Gogh" }
  ],
  "isOrdered": true
}
]]></sourcecode>
                </figure>
                <t><xref target="example-name-surname2"/>
                  illustrates a name with a second surname such as a Spanish name. Additional examples are shown in
                  Figures
                  <xref target="example-name-sortas" format="counter"/>
                  and <xref target="example-localizations-replace" format="counter"/>.
                </t>
                <figure anchor="example-name-surname2">
                  <name>Example of a Second Surname</name>
                  <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"name": {
  "components": [
    { "kind": "given", "value": "Diego" },
    { "kind": "surname", "value": "Rivera" },
    { "kind": "surname2", "value": "Barrientos" }
  ],
  "isOrdered": true
}
]]></sourcecode>
                </figure>
              </dd>
              <dt>isOrdered: Boolean (optional; default: "false").</dt>
              <dd>The indicator if the name components in the components property are ordered.</dd>
              <dt>defaultSeparator: String (optional).</dt>
              <dd>
                The default separator to insert between name component values when concatenating all name component
                values to a single String. Also see the definition of the kind property value "separator" for the <xref target="namecomponent">
                NameComponent
              </xref> object. The defaultSeparator property <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set if the Name isOrdered
                property value is "false" or if the components property is not set.
              </dd>
              <dt>full: String (optional).</dt>
              <dd>
                <t>
                  The full name representation of the Name. The full property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set if the
                  components property is not set.
                </t>
                <figure anchor="example-full">
                  <name>Example for the full Property</name>
                  <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"full": "Mr. John Q. Public, Esq."
]]></sourcecode>
                </figure>
              </dd>
              <dt>
                sortAs: String[String] (optional).
              </dt>
              <dd>
                <t>The value to lexicographically sort the name in relation to other names when compared by a name
                  component type. The keys in the map define the name component type. The values define the
                  verbatim string to compare when sorting by the name component type. Absence of a key indicates that
                  the name component type <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be considered during sort. Sorting by that missing
                  name component type, or if the sortAs property is not set, is implementation-specific. The sortAs
                  property <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set if the components property is not set.
                </t>
                <t>Each key in the map <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a valid name component type value as defined for the kind
                  property of the NameComponent object (see below). For each key in the map, there <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> exist
                  at least one NameComponent object that has the type in the components property of the name.
                </t>
                <t><xref target="example-name-sortas"/>
                  illustrates the use of the sortAs property. The property value indicates that the middle name followed
                  by both surnames should be used when sorting the name by surname. The absence of "middle" indicates
                  that the middle name on its own should be disregarded during sort. Even though the name only contains
                  one name component for the given name, the sortAs property still explicitly defines how to sort by the
                  given name; otherwise, sorting by it would be undefined.
                </t>
              </dd>
              <dt>
                phoneticScript: String (optional).
              </dt>
              <dd>
                The script used in the value of the NameComponent phonetic property. See
                <xref target="prop-phonetic"/>
                for more information and
                <xref target="example-name-phonetic"/>
                for an example.
              </dd>
              <dt>
                phoneticSystem: String (optional).
              </dt>
              <dd>
                <t>
                  The phonetic system used in the NameComponent phonetic property. See
                  <xref target="prop-phonetic"/>
                  for more information and
                  <xref target="example-name-phonetic"/>
                  for an example.
                </t>
              </dd>
            </dl>
            <figure anchor="example-name-sortas">
              <name>Example for the sortAs Property</name>
              <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"name": {
  "components": [
    { "kind": "given", "value": "Robert" },
    { "kind": "given2", "value": "Pau" },
    { "kind": "surname", "value": "Shou Chang" }
  ],
  "sortAs": {
    "surname": "Pau Shou Chang",
    "given": "Robert"
  },
  "isOrdered": true
}
]]></sourcecode>
            </figure>
            <figure anchor="example-name-phonetic">
              <name>Example for the phonetic and localizations Properties</name>
              <sourcecode type=""><![CDATA[
{
  "@type": "Card",
  "language": "zh-Hant",
  "name": {
    "components": [
      { "kind": "surname", "value": "孫" },
      { "kind": "given", "value": "中山" },
      { "kind": "given2", "value": "文" },
      { "kind": "given2", "value": "逸仙" }
    ]
  },
  "localizations": {
    "yue": {
      "name/phoneticSystem": "jyut",
      "name/phoneticScript": "Latn",
      "name/components/0/phonetic": "syun1",
      "name/components/1/phonetic": "zung1saan1",
      "name/components/2/phonetic": "man4",
      "name/components/3/phonetic": "jat6sin1"
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
            </figure>
          </section>
          <section anchor="namecomponent">
            <name>NameComponent</name>
            <t>A NameComponent object has the following properties:</t>
            <dl spacing="normal">
              <dt>@type: String.</dt>
              <dd>
                The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "NameComponent", if set.
              </dd>
              <dt>value: String (mandatory).</dt>
              <dd>
                The value of the name component. This can be composed of one or multiple words such as "Poe" or "van
                Gogh".
              </dd>
              <dt>kind: String (mandatory).</dt>
              <dd>
                <t>
                  The kind of the name component. The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:
                </t>
                <ul spacing="normal">
                  <li>title: an honorific title or prefix, e.g., "Mr.", "Ms.", or "Dr.".</li>
                  <li>given: a given name, also known as "first name" or "personal name".</li>
                  <li>given2: a name that appears between the given and surname such as a middle name or patronymic
                    name.
                  </li>
                  <li>surname: a surname, also known as "last name" or "family name".</li>
                  <li>surname2: a secondary surname (used in some cultures), also known as "maternal surname".</li>
                  <li>credential: a credential, also known as "accreditation qualifier" or "honorific suffix", e.g.,
                    "B.A.", "Esq.".
                  </li>
                  <li>generation: a generation marker or qualifier, e.g., "Jr." or "III".</li>
                  <li>separator: a formatting separator between two ordered name non-separator components. The value
                    property of the component includes the verbatim separator, for example, a hyphen character or even
                    an empty string. This value has higher precedence than the defaultSeparator property of the Name.
                    Implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> insert two consecutive separator components; instead, they <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> insert a single separator component with the combined value. This component kind <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set if the Name isOrdered property value is "false".
                  </li>
                </ul>
              </dd>
              <dt>phonetic: String (optional).</dt>
              <dd>The pronunciation of the name component. If this property is set, then at least one of the Name
                object properties, phoneticSystem or phoneticScript, <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set. Also see <xref target="prop-phonetic"/>.
              </dd>
            </dl>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section anchor="nicknames" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>nicknames</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>nicknames: Id[Nickname] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The nicknames of the entity represented by the Card.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A Nickname object has the following properties:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Nickname", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>name: String (mandatory).</dt>
            <dd>
              The nickname.
            </dd>
            <dt>contexts: String[Boolean] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The contexts in which to use the nickname. Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>pref: UnsignedInt (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The preference of the nickname in relation to other nicknames. Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-nicknames">
            <name>Example for the nicknames Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"nicknames": {
  "k391": {
    "name": "Johnny"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="organizations" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>organizations</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>organizations: Id[Organization] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The company or organization names and units associated with the Card.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>An Organization object has the following properties, of which at least one of the name and units properties <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set:
          </t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Organization", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>name: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The name of the organization.
            </dd>
            <dt>units: OrgUnit[] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>A list of organizational units, ordered as descending by hierarchy (e.g., a geographic or functional
              division sorts before a department within that division). If set, the list <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> contain at
              least one entry.
            </dd>
            <dt>sortAs: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The value to lexicographically sort the organization in relation to other organizations when compared
              by name. The value defines the verbatim string value to compare. In absence of this property, the name
              property value <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be used for comparison.
            </dd>
            <dt>contexts: String[Boolean] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The contexts in which association with the organization applies. For example, membership in a choir may
              only apply in a private context. Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>An OrgUnit object has the following properties:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "OrgUnit", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>name: String (mandatory).</dt>
            <dd>
              The name of the organizational unit.
            </dd>
            <dt>sortAs: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The value to lexicographically sort the organizational unit in relation to other organizational units
              of the same level when compared by name. The level is defined by the array index of the organizational
              unit in the units property of the Organization object. The property value defines the verbatim string
              value to compare. In absence of this property, the name property value <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be used for
              comparison.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-organizations">
            <name>Example for the organizations Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"organizations": {
  "o1": {
    "name": "ABC, Inc.",
    "units": [
      { "name": "North American Division" },
      { "name": "Marketing" }
    ],
    "sortAs": "ABC"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="speakToAs" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>speakToAs</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>speakToAs: SpeakToAs (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The information that directs how to address, speak to, or refer to the entity that is represented by the Card.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A SpeakToAs object has the following properties, of which at least one of the grammaticalGender and
            pronouns properties <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set:
          </t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "SpeakToAs", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>
              grammaticalGender: String (optional).
            </dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
                The grammatical gender to use in salutations and other grammatical constructs. For example,
                the German language distinguishes by grammatical gender in salutations such as "Sehr geehrte" (feminine)
                and "Sehr geehrter" (masculine). The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:
              </t>
              <ul spacing="compact">
                <li>
                  animate
                </li>
                <li>
                  common
                </li>
                <li>
                  feminine
                </li>
                <li>
                  inanimate
                </li>
                <li>
                  masculine
                </li>
                <li>
                  neuter
                </li>
              </ul>
              <t>Note that the grammatical gender does not allow inferring the gender identities or assigned sex of the
                contact.
              </t>
            </dd>
            <dt>pronouns: Id[Pronouns] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
                The pronouns that the contact chooses to use for themselves.
              </t>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A Pronouns object has the following properties:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Pronouns", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>pronouns: String (mandatory).</dt>
            <dd>
              The pronouns. Any value or form is allowed. Examples in English include "she/her" and
              "they/them/theirs". The value <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be overridden in the <xref target="localizations">
              localizations
            </xref> property.
            </dd>
            <dt>contexts: String[Boolean] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The contexts in which to use the pronouns. Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>pref: UnsignedInt (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The preference of the pronouns in relation to other pronouns in the same context. Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-speakToAs">
            <name>Example for the speakToAs Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"speakToAs": {
  "grammaticalGender": "neuter",
  "pronouns": {
    "k19": {
      "pronouns": "they/them",
      "pref": 2
    },
    "k32": {
      "pronouns": "xe/xir",
      "pref": 1
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="titles" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>titles</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>titles: Id[Title] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The job titles or functional positions of the entity represented by the Card.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A Title object has the following properties:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Title", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>name: String (mandatory).</dt>
            <dd>
              The title or role name of the entity represented by the Card.
            </dd>
            <dt>kind: String (optional; default: "title").</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
                The organizational or situational kind of the title. Some organizations and individuals
                distinguish between <em>titles</em> as organizational positions and <em>roles</em> as more temporary
                assignments such as in project management.
              </t>
              <t>The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:
              </t>
              <ul spacing="compact">
                <li>title</li>
                <li>role</li>
              </ul>
            </dd>
            <dt>organizationId: Id (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The identifier of the organization in which this title is held.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-titles">
            <name>Example for the titles Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"titles": {
  "le9": {
    "kind": "title",
    "name": "Research Scientist"
  },
  "k2": {
    "kind": "role",
    "name": "Project Leader",
    "organizationId": "o2"
  }
},
"organizations": {
  "o2": {
    "name": "ABC, Inc."
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="contact-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Contact Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines how properties contact the entity represented by the Card.</t>
        <section anchor="emails" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>emails</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>emails: Id[EmailAddress] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The email addresses in which to contact the entity represented by the Card.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>An EmailAddress object has the following properties:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "EmailAddress", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>address: String (mandatory).</dt>
            <dd>
              The email address. This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be an <em>addr-spec</em> value as defined in <xref target="RFC5322" sectionFormat="of" section="3.4.1"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>contexts: String[Boolean] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The contexts in which to use this email address. Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>pref: UnsignedInt (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The preference of the email address in relation to other email addresses. Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>label: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              A custom label for the value. Also see <xref target="prop-label"/>.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-emails">
            <name>Example for the emails Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"emails": {
  "e1": {
    "contexts": {
      "work": true
    },
    "address": "jqpublic@xyz.example.com"
  },
  "e2": {
    "address": "jane_doe@example.com",
    "pref": 1
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="onlineServices" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>onlineServices</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>onlineServices: Id[OnlineService] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The online services that are associated with the entity represented by the Card. This can be messaging
              services, social media profiles, and other.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>An OnlineService object has the following properties, of which at least the uri or user property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set:
          </t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "OnlineService", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>service: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The name of the online service or protocol. The name <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be capitalized the same as on the
              service's website, app, or publishing material, but names <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be considered equal if they
              match case-insensitively. Examples are "GitHub", "kakao", and "Mastodon".
            </dd>
            <dt>uri: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The identifier for the entity represented by the Card at the online service. This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a <em>
              URI
            </em> as defined in <xref target="RFC3986" sectionFormat="of" section="3"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>user: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The name the entity represented by the Card at the online service. Any free-text value is allowed. The
              service property <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be set.
            </dd>
            <dt>contexts: String[Boolean] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The contexts in which to use the service. Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>pref: UnsignedInt (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The preference of the service in relation to other services. Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>label: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              A custom label for the value. Also see <xref target="prop-label"/>.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-onlineServices">
            <name>Example for the onlineServices Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"onlineServices": {
  "x1": {
    "uri": "xmpp:alice@example.com"
  },
  "x2": {
    "service": "Mastodon",
    "user": "@alice@example2.com",
    "uri": "https://example2.com/@alice"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="phones" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>phones</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>phones: Id[Phone] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The phone numbers by which to contact the entity represented by the Card.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>Phone object has the following properties:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Phone", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>number: String (mandatory).</dt>
            <dd>
              The phone number as either a URI or free text. Typical URI schemes are "tel"
              <xref target="RFC3966" format="default"/>
              or "sip" <xref target="RFC3261" format="default"/>, but any URI scheme is allowed.
            </dd>
            <dt>features: String[Boolean] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
                The set of contact features that the phone number may be used for. The set is represented as an object,
                with each key being a method type. The boolean value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "true". The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated
              </xref> method type values are:
              </t>
              <ul spacing="compact">
                <li>mobile: this number is for a mobile phone.</li>
                <li>voice: this number supports calling by voice.</li>
                <li>text: this number supports text messages (SMS).</li>
                <li>video: this number supports video conferencing.</li>
                <li>main-number: this number is a main phone number such as the number of the front desk at a company,
                  as opposed to a direct-dial number of an individual employee.
                </li>
                <li>textphone: this number is for a device for people with hearing or speech difficulties.</li>
                <li>fax: this number supports sending faxes.</li>
                <li>pager: this number is for a pager or beeper.</li>
              </ul>
            </dd>
            <dt>contexts: String[Boolean] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The contexts in which to use the number. Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>pref: UnsignedInt (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The preference of the number in relation to other numbers. Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>label: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              A custom label for the value. Also see <xref target="prop-label"/>.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-phones">
            <name>Example for the phones Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"phones": {
  "tel0": {
    "contexts": {
      "private": true
    },
    "features": {
      "voice": true
    },
    "number": "tel:+1-555-555-5555;ext=5555",
    "pref": 1
  },
  "tel3": {
    "contexts": {
      "work": true
    },
    "number": "tel:+1-201-555-0123"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="preferredLanguages" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>preferredLanguages</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>preferredLanguages : Id[LanguagePref] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The preferred languages for contacting the entity associated with the Card.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A LanguagePref object has the following properties:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "LanguagePref", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>language: String (mandatory).</dt>
            <dd>The preferred language. This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a language tag as defined in <xref target="RFC5646"/>
              .
            </dd>
            <dt>contexts: String[Boolean] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The contexts in which to use the language. Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>pref: UnsignedInt (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The preference of the language in relation to other languages of the same contexts. Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-preferredLanguages">
            <name>Example for the preferredLanguages Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"preferredLanguages": {
  "l1": {
    "language": "en",
    "contexts": {
      "work": true
    },
    "pref": 1
  },
  "l2": {
    "language": "fr",
    "contexts": {
      "work": true
    },
    "pref": 2
  },
  "l3": {
    "language": "fr",
    "contexts": {
      "private": true
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="calendaring-and-scheduling-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Calendaring and Scheduling Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties for scheduling calendar events with the entity represented by the Card.</t>
        <section anchor="calendars" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>calendars</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>calendars: Id[Calendar] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The calendaring resources of the entity represented by the Card, such as to look up free-busy information.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A Calendar object has all properties of the <xref target="resource">Resource</xref> data type, with the
            following additional definitions:
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li>The @type property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Calendar", if set.
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>The kind property is mandatory. Its <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:
              </t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li>
                  calendar: The resource is a calendar that contains entries such as calendar events or tasks.
                </li>
                <li>
                  freeBusy: The resource allows for free-busy lookups, for example, to schedule group events.
                </li>
              </ul>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-calendars">
            <name>Example for the calendars Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"calendars": {
  "calA": {
    "kind": "calendar",
    "uri": "webcal://calendar.example.com/calA.ics"
  },
  "project-a": {
    "kind": "freeBusy",
    "uri": "https://calendar.example.com/busy/project-a"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="schedulingAddresses" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>schedulingAddresses</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>schedulingAddresses: Id[SchedulingAddress] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The scheduling addresses by which the entity may receive calendar scheduling invitations.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A SchedulingAddress object has the following properties:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "SchedulingAddress", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>uri: String (mandatory).</dt>
            <dd>
              The address to use for calendar scheduling with the contact. This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a URI as defined
              in <xref target="RFC3986" sectionFormat="of" section="3"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>contexts: String[Boolean] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The contexts in which to use the scheduling address. Also see <xref target="prop-contexts"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>pref: UnsignedInt (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The preference of the scheduling address in relation to other scheduling addresses. Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>label: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              A custom label for the scheduling address. Also see <xref target="prop-label"/>.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-schedulingAddresses">
            <name>Example for the schedulingAddresses Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"schedulingAddresses": {
  "sched1": {
    "uri": "mailto:janedoe@example.com"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="address-and-location-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Address and Location Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties for postal addresses and geographical locations associated with the entity
          represented by the Card.
        </t>
        <section anchor="addresses-prop" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>addresses</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>addresses: Id[Address] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The addresses of the entity represented by the Card, such as postal addresses or geographic locations.</dd>
          </dl>
          <section anchor="address">
            <name>Address Object</name>
            <t>An Address object has the following properties, of which at least one of components, coordinates,
              countryCode, full or timeZone <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set:
            </t>
            <dl spacing="normal">
              <dt>@type: String.</dt>
              <dd>
                The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Address", if set.
              </dd>
              <dt>
                components: AddressComponent[] (optional).
              </dt>
              <dd>
                <t>The <xref target="addresscomponent">components</xref> that make up the address. The component list <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have at least one entry that has a kind property value other than "separator".
                </t>
                <t>Address components <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be ordered such that when their values are joined as a
                  String, a valid full address is produced. If so, implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> set the isOrdered
                  property value to "true".
                </t>
                <t>If the address components are ordered, then the defaultSeparator property and address components with
                  the kind property value set to "separator" give guidance on what characters to insert between
                  components, but implementations are free to choose any others. When lacking a separator, inserting a
                  single space character in between address component values is a good choice.
                </t>
                <t>If, instead, the address components follow no particular order, then the isOrdered property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "false", the components property <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain an AddressComponent with
                  the kind property value set to "separator", and the defaultSeparator property <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be
                  set.
                </t>
              </dd>
              <dt>isOrdered: Boolean (optional; default: "false").</dt>
              <dd>The indicator if the address components in the components property are ordered.</dd>
              <dt>countryCode: String (optional).</dt>
              <dd>
                The Alpha-2 country code <xref target="ISO.3166-1"/>.
              </dd>
              <dt>coordinates: String (optional).</dt>
              <dd>A "geo:" URI
                <xref target="RFC5870" format="default"/>
                for the address.
              </dd>
              <dt>timeZone: String (optional).</dt>
              <dd>The time zone in which the address is located. This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a time zone name
                registered in the IANA <xref target="IANA-TZ">Time Zone Database</xref>.
              </dd>
              <dt>
                contexts: String[Boolean] (optional).
              </dt>
              <dd>
                <t>
                  The contexts in which to use this address. The boolean value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "true". In addition
                  to the common contexts (<xref target="prop-contexts"/>), allowed key values are:
                </t>
                <ul spacing="compact">
                  <li>billing: an address to be used for billing.</li>
                  <li>delivery: an address to be used for delivering physical items.</li>
                </ul>
              </dd>
              <dt>full: String (optional).</dt>
              <dd>
                The full address, including street, region, or country. The purpose of this property is to define an
                address, even if the individual address components are not known.
              </dd>
              <dt>defaultSeparator: String (optional).</dt>
              <dd>
                The default separator to insert between address component values when concatenating all address
                component values to a single String. Also see the definition of the kind property value "separator" for
                the <xref target="addresscomponent">AddressComponent</xref> object. The defaultSeparator property <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set if the Address isOrdered property value is "false" or if the components property is not
                set.
              </dd>
              <dt>pref: UnsignedInt (optional).</dt>
              <dd>
                The preference of the address in relation to other addresses. Also see <xref target="prop-pref"/>.
              </dd>
              <dt>
                phoneticScript: String (optional).
              </dt>
              <dd>
                The script used in the value of the AddressComponent phonetic property. Also see <xref target="prop-phonetic"/>.
              </dd>
              <dt>
                phoneticSystem: String (optional).
              </dt>
              <dd>
                The phonetic system used in the AddressComponent phonetic property. Also see <xref target="prop-phonetic"/>.
              </dd>
            </dl>
            <t>The following example illustrates the use of the address property for "54321 Oak St, Reston, CA 20190,
              USA". Additional examples are shown in <xref target="address-examples"/>.
            </t>
            <figure anchor="example-address-us">
              <name>Example of an Address in the USA</name>
              <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"addresses": {
  "k23": {
    "contexts": {
      "work": true
    },
    "components": [
      { "kind": "number", "value": "54321" },
      { "kind": "separator", "value": " " },
      { "kind": "name", "value": "Oak St" },
      { "kind": "locality", "value": "Reston" },
      { "kind": "region", "value": "VA" },
      { "kind": "separator", "value": " " },
      { "kind": "postcode", "value": "20190" },
      { "kind": "country", "value": "USA" }
    ],
    "countryCode": "US",
    "defaultSeparator": ", ",
    "isOrdered": true
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
            </figure>
          </section>
          <section anchor="addresscomponent">
            <name>AddressComponent Object</name>
            <t>An AddressComponent object has the following properties:</t>
            <dl spacing="normal">
              <dt>@type: String.</dt>
              <dd>
                The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "AddressComponent", if set.
              </dd>
              <dt>value: String (mandatory).</dt>
              <dd>
                The value of the address component.
              </dd>
              <dt>
                kind: String (mandatory).
              </dt>
              <dd>
                <t>
                  The kind of the address component. The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:
                </t>
                <ul spacing="compact">
                  <li>room: the room, suite number, or identifier.</li>
                  <li>apartment: the extension designation such as the apartment number, unit, or box number.</li>
                  <li>floor: the floor or level the address is located on.</li>
                  <li>building: the building, tower, or condominium the address is located in.</li>
                  <li>number: the street number, e.g., "123". This value is not restricted to numeric values and can
                    include any value such as number ranges ("112-10"), grid style ("39.2 RD"), alphanumerics
                    ("N6W23001"), or fractionals ("123 1/2").
                  </li>
                  <li>name: the street name.</li>
                  <li>block: the block name or number.</li>
                  <li>subdistrict: the subdistrict, ward, or other subunit of a district.</li>
                  <li>district: the district name.</li>
                  <li>locality: the municipality, city, town, village, post town, or other locality.</li>
                  <li>region: the administrative area such as province, state, prefecture, county, or canton.</li>
                  <li>postcode: the postal code, post code, ZIP code, or other short code associated with the address by
                    the relevant country's postal system.
                  </li>
                  <li>country: the country name.</li>
                  <li>direction: the cardinal direction or quadrant, e.g., "north".</li>
                  <li>landmark: the publicly known prominent feature that can substitute the street name and number,
                    e.g., "White House" or "Taj Mahal".
                  </li>
                  <li>postOfficeBox: the post office box number or identifier.</li>
                  <li>separator: a formatting separator between two ordered address non-separator components. The value
                    property of the component includes the verbatim separator, for example, a hyphen character or even
                    an empty string. This value has higher precedence than the defaultSeparator property of the Address.
                    Implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> insert two consecutive separator components; instead, they <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> insert a single separator component with the combined value. This component kind <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set if the Address isOrdered property value is "false".
                  </li>
                </ul>
              </dd>
              <dt>phonetic: String (optional).</dt>
              <dd>The pronunciation of the name component. If this property is set, then at least one of the Address
                object phoneticSystem or phoneticScript properties <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set. Also see <xref target="prop-phonetic"/>.
              </dd>
            </dl>
          </section>
          <section anchor="address-examples">
            <name>Additional Address Examples</name>
            <t>The following example illustrates the use of the address property for "46, 1 Sukhumvit 51 Alley, Khlong
              Tan Nuea, Watthana, Bangkok 10110, Thailand".
            </t>
            <figure anchor="example-address-th">
              <name>Example of an Address in Thailand</name>
              <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"addresses": {
  "k25": {
    "components": [
      { "kind": "number", "value": "46" },
      { "kind": "name", "value": "1 Sukhumvit 51 Alley" },
      { "kind": "subdistrict", "value": "Khlong Tan Nuea" },
      { "kind": "district", "value": " Watthana" },
      { "kind": "locality", "value": "Bangkok" },
      { "kind": "country", "value": "Thailand" },
      { "kind": "postcode", "value": "10110" }
    ],
    "defaultSeparator": ", ",
    "isOrdered": true
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
            </figure>
            <t>
              The following example illustrates the use of the address property for "2-7-2 Marunouchi, Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo
              100-8994" and its Japanese localization (<xref target="localizations"/>).
            </t>
            <figure anchor="example-address-jp">
              <name>Example of an Address in Tokyo and Its Localization in Japanese</name>
              <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"addresses": {
   "k26": {
     "components": [
       { "kind": "block", "value": "2-7" },
       { "kind": "separator", "value": "-" },
       { "kind": "number", "value": "2" },
       { "kind": "separator", "value": " " },
       { "kind": "district", "value": "Marunouchi" },
       { "kind": "locality", "value": "Chiyoda-ku" },
       { "kind": "region", "value": "Tokyo" },
       { "kind": "separator", "value": " " },
       { "kind": "postcode", "value": "100-8994" }
     ],
     "defaultSeparator": ", ",
     "full": "2-7-2 Marunouchi, Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100-8994",
     "isOrdered": true
   }
},
"localizations": {
  "jp": {
    "addresses/k26": {
      "components": [
        { "kind": "region", "value": "東京都" },
        { "kind": "locality", "value": "千代田区" },
        { "kind": "district", "value": "丸ノ内" },
        { "kind": "block", "value": "2-7" },
        { "kind": "separator", "value": "-" },
        { "kind": "number", "value": "2" },
        { "kind": "postcode", "value": "〒100-8994" }
      ],
      "defaultSeparator": "",
      "full": "〒100-8994東京都千代田区丸ノ内2-7-2",
      "isOrdered": true
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
            </figure>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="resource-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Resource Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties for digital resources associated with the entity represented by the Card.</t>
        <section anchor="cryptoKeys" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>cryptoKeys</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>cryptoKeys: Id[CryptoKey] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The cryptographic resources such as public keys and certificates associated with the entity
              represented by the Card.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A CryptoKey object has all properties of the <xref target="resource">Resource</xref> data type, with the
            following additional definition:
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li>The @type property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "CryptoKey", if set.
            </li>
          </ul>
          <t>The following example shows how to refer to an external cryptographic resource.</t>
          <figure anchor="example-cryptoKeys-external">
            <name>Example of cryptoKeys with External Data</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"cryptoKeys": {
  "mykey1": {
    "uri": "https://www.example.com/keys/jdoe.cer"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
          <t>The following example shows how to embed key data in the CryptoKey. The key data is depicted in multiple
            lines only for demonstration purposes.
          </t>
          <figure anchor="example-cryptoKeys-embedded">
            <name>Example of cryptoKeys with Embedded Data</name>
          
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"cryptoKeys": {
  "mykey2": {
    "uri": "data:application/pgp-keys;base64,LS0tLS1CRUdJTiBSU0EgUFVC
            TElDIEtFWS0tLS0tCk1JSUJDZ0tDQVFFQSt4R1ovd2N6OXVnRnBQMDdOc
            3BvNlUxN2wwWWhGaUZweHhVNHBUazNMaWZ6OVIzenNJc3UKRVJ3dGE3K2
            ZXSWZ4T28yMDhldHQvamhza2lWb2RTRXQzUUJHaDRYQmlweVdvcEt3Wjk
            zSEhhRFZaQUFMaS8yQQoreFRCdFdkRW83WEdVdWpLRHZDMi9hWkt1a2Zq
            cE9pVUk4QWhMQWZqbWxjRC9VWjFRUGgwbUhzZ2xSTkNtcEN3Cm13U1hBO
            VZObWh6K1BpQitEbWw0V1duS1cvVkhvMnVqVFh4cTcrZWZNVTRIMmZueT
            NTZTNLWU9zRlBGR1oxVE4KUVNZbEZ1U2hXckhQdGlMbVVkUG9QNkNWMm1
            NTDF0aytsN0RJSXFYclFoTFVLREFDZU01cm9NeDBrTGhVV0I4UAorMHVq
            MUNObE5ONEpSWmxDN3hGZnFpTWJGUlU5WjRONll3SURBUUFCCi0tLS0tR
            U5EIFJTQSBQVUJMSUMgS0VZLS0tLS0K"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="directories" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>directories</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>directories: Id[Directory] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The directories containing information about the entity represented by the Card.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A Directory object has all properties of the <xref target="resource">Resource</xref> data type, with the
            following additional definitions:
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li>The @type property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Directory", if set.
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>The kind property is mandatory. Its <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:
              </t>
              <ul>
                <li>directory: the resource is a directory service that the entity represented by the Card is a part of.
                  This typically is an organizational directory that also contains associated entities, e.g., co-workers
                  and management in a company directory.
                </li>
                <li>entry: the resource is a directory entry of the entity represented by the Card. In contrast to the
                  "directory" type, this is the specific URI for the entity <em>within</em> a directory.
                </li>
              </ul>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <t>In addition, the Directory object has the following property:</t>
          <dl>
            <dt>listAs: UnsignedInt (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The position of the directory resource in the list of all Directory objects having the same kind
              property value in the Card. If set, the listAs value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be higher than zero. Multiple
              directory resources <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> have the same listAs property value or none. Sorting such
              same-valued entries is implementation-specific.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-directories">
            <name>Example for the directories Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"directories": {
  "dir1": {
    "kind": "entry",
    "uri": "https://dir.example.com/addrbook/jdoe/Jean%20Dupont.vcf"
  },
  "dir2": {
    "kind": "directory",
    "uri": "ldap://ldap.example/o=Example%20Tech,ou=Engineering",
    "pref": 1
  }
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="links" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>links</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>links: Id[Link] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The links to resources that do not fit any of the other use-case-specific resource properties.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A Link object has all properties of the <xref target="resource">Resource</xref> data type, with the
            following additional definitions:
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li>The @type property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Link", if set.
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>The kind property is optional. Its <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:
              </t>
              <ul>
                <li>contact: the resource is a URI by which the entity represented by the Card may be contacted; this
                  includes web forms or other media that require user interaction.
                </li>
              </ul>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-links">
            <name>Example for the links Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"links": {
  "link3": {
    "kind": "contact",
    "uri": "mailto:contact@example.com",
    "pref": 1
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="media" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>media</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>media: Id[Media] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The media resources such as photographs, avatars, or sounds that are associated with the entity
              represented by the Card.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A Media object has all properties of the <xref target="resource">Resource</xref> data type, with the
            following additional definitions:
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li>The @type property value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Media", if set.
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>The kind property is mandatory. Its <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:
              </t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li>photo: the resource is a photograph or avatar.</li>
                <li>sound: the resource is audio media, e.g., to specify the proper pronunciation of the name property
                  contents.
                </li>
                <li>logo: the resource is a graphic image or logo associated with the entity represented by the Card.
                </li>
              </ul>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="example-media">
            <name>Example for the media Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"media": {
  "res45": {
    "kind": "sound",
    "uri": "CID:JOHNQ.part8.19960229T080000.xyzMail@example.com"
  },
  "res47": {
    "kind": "logo",
    "uri": "https://www.example.com/pub/logos/abccorp.jpg"
  },
  "res1": {
    "kind": "photo",
    "uri": "data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/4AAQSkZJRgABAQAASABIAAD/4..."
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="multilingual-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Multilingual Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties for localizing the content of the Card in human languages.</t>
        <section anchor="localizations" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>localizations</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>localizations: String[PatchObject] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>The property values localized to languages other than the <xref target="language">main language</xref> of
                the Card. Localizations provide language-specific alternatives for existing property values and <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> add new properties. The keys in the localizations property value are language tags <xref target="RFC5646"/>; the values are of type PatchObject and localize the Card in that language
                tag. The paths in the PatchObject are relative to the Card that includes the localizations property. A
                patch <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> target the localizations property.
              </t>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>Conceptually, a Card is localized as follows:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>Determine the language tag in which the Card should be localized.</li>
            <li>If the localizations property includes a key for that language, obtain the PatchObject value. If there
              is no such key, stop.
            </li>
            <li>Create a copy of the Card, but do not copy the localizations property.</li>
            <li>Apply all patches in the PatchObject to the copy of the Card.</li>
            <li>Optionally, set the language property in the copy of the Card.</li>
            <li>Use the patched copy of the Card as the localized variant of the original Card.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>A patch in the PatchObject may contain any value type. Its value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a valid value
            according to the definition of the patched property.
          </t>
          <t><xref target="example-localizations-replace"/>
            localizes the name property by completely replacing its contents in Ukrainian language with Cyrillic script.
          </t>
          <figure anchor="example-localizations-replace">
            <name>Example of Localizing a Top-Level Property</name>
            <sourcecode type=""><![CDATA[
{
  "name": {
    "components": [
      { "kind": "title", "value": "Mr." },
      { "kind": "given", "value": "Ivan" },
      { "kind": "given2", "value": "Petrovich" },
      { "kind": "surname", "value": "Vasiliev" }
    ]
  },
  "localizations": {
    "uk-Cyrl": {
      "name": {
        "components": [
          { "kind": "title", "value": "г-н" },
          { "kind": "given", "value": "Иван" },
          { "kind": "given2", "value": "Петрович" },
          { "kind": "surname", "value": "Васильев" }
        ]
      }
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
          <t><xref target="example-localizations-patch"/>
            localizes the title name by patching <em>inside</em> the titles property. All properties, except the name
            property in the Title object, are left as is.
          </t>
          <figure anchor="example-localizations-patch">
            <name>Example of Localizing a Nested Property</name>
          
            <sourcecode type=""><![CDATA[
"name": {
  "full": "Gabriel García Márquez"
},
"titles": {
  "t1": {
    "kind": "title",
    "name": "novelist"
  }
},
"localizations": {
  "es": {
    "titles/t1/name": "escritor"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="additional-properties" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Additional Properties</name>
        <t>This section defines properties for which none of the previous sections are appropriate.</t>
        <section anchor="anniversaries" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>anniversaries</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>anniversaries: Id[Anniversary] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The memorable dates and events for the entity represented by the Card.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>An Anniversary object has the following properties:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Anniversary", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>
              kind: String (mandatory).
            </dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
                The kind of anniversary. The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:
              </t>
              <ul spacing="compact">
                <li>birth: a birthday anniversary</li>
                <li>death: a deathday anniversary</li>
                <li>wedding: a wedding day anniversary</li>
              </ul>
            </dd>
            <dt>
              date: PartialDate|Timestamp (mandatory; defaultType: PartialDate).
            </dt>
            <dd>
              <t>The date of the anniversary in the Gregorian calendar. This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be either a whole or
                partial calendar date or a complete UTC timestamp (see the definition of the Timestamp and PartialDate
                object types below).
              </t>
            </dd>
            <dt>place: Address (optional).</dt>
            <dd>An address associated with this anniversary, e.g., the place of birth or death.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A PartialDate object represents a complete or partial calendar date in the Gregorian calendar. It
            represents a complete date, a year, a month in a year, or a day in a month. It has the following properties:
          </t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "PartialDate", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>year:</dt>
            <dd>UnsignedInt (optional). The calendar year.</dd>
            <dt>month: UnsignedInt (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The calendar month, represented as the integers 1 &lt;= month &lt;= 12. If this property is set, then
              either the year or the day property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set.
            </dd>
            <dt>day: UnsignedInt (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The calendar month day, represented as the integers 1 &lt;= day &lt;= 31, depending on the validity
              within the month and year. If this property is set, then the month property <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set.
            </dd>
            <dt>calendarScale: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The calendar system in which this date occurs, in lowercase. This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be either a
              calendar system name registered as a Common Locale Data Repository (CLDR)
              <xref target="RFC7529" format="default"/>
              or a vendor-specific value. The year, month, and day still <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be represented in the
              Gregorian calendar. Note that the year property might be required to convert the date between the
              Gregorian calendar and the respective calendar system.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A Timestamp object has the following properties:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Timestamp", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>utc: UTCDateTime (mandatory).</dt>
            <dd>The point in time in UTC time.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t><xref target="example-anniversaries"/>
            illustrates anniversaries with partial dates and a timestamp. Note how the @type property is set for the
            Timestamp object value according to the rules defined in <xref target="prop-type"/>.
          </t>
          <figure anchor="example-anniversaries">
            <name>Example for the anniversaries Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"anniversaries": {
  "k8": {
    "kind": "birth",
    "date": {
      "year": 1953,
      "month": 4,
      "day": 15
    }
  },
  "k9": {
    "kind": "death",
    "date": {
      "@type": "Timestamp",
      "utc": "2019-10-15T23:10:00Z"
    },
    "place": {
      "full": "4445 Tree Street\nNew England, ND 58647\nUSA"
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="keywords" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>keywords</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>keywords: String[Boolean] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>The set of free-text keywords, also known as <em>tags</em>. Each key in the set is a keyword, and each boolean value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "true".
              </t>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-keywords">
            <name>Example for the keywords Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"keywords": {
  "internet": true,
  "IETF": true
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="notes" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>notes</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>notes: Id[Note] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The free-text notes that are associated with the Card.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A Note object has the following properties:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Note", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>
              note: String (mandatory).
            </dt>
            <dd>The free-text value of this note.
            </dd>
            <dt>
              created: UTCDateTime (optional).
            </dt>
            <dd>The date and time when this note was created.
            </dd>
            <dt>
              author: Author (optional).
            </dt>
            <dd>The author of this note.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>An Author object has the following properties, of which at least one property other than @type <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set:
          </t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Author", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>
              name: String (optional).
            </dt>
            <dd>The name of this author.
            </dd>
            <dt>
              uri: String (optional).
            </dt>
            <dd>
              <t>The URI value that identifies the author.</t>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-notes">
            <name>Example for the notes Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"notes": {
  "n1": {
    "note": "Open office hours are 1600 to 1715 EST, Mon-Fri",
    "created": "2022-11-23T15:01:32Z",
    "author": {
      "name": "John"
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="personalInfo" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>personalInfo</name>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>personalInfo: Id[PersonalInfo] (optional).</dt>
            <dd>The personal information of the entity represented by the Card.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A PersonalInfo object has the following properties:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            <dt>@type: String.</dt>
            <dd>
              The JSContact type of the object. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "PersonalInfo", if set.
            </dd>
            <dt>
              kind: String (mandatory).
            </dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
                The kind of personal information. The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values
                are:
              </t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li>expertise: a field of expertise or a credential</li>
                <li>hobby: a hobby</li>
                <li>interest: an interest</li>
              </ul>
            </dd>
            <dt>value: String (mandatory).</dt>
            <dd>
              The actual information.
            </dd>
            <dt>
              level: String (optional).
            </dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
                The level of expertise or engagement in hobby or interest. The <xref target="enumerated-values">enumerated</xref> values are:</t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li>
                  high
                </li>
                <li>
                  medium
                </li>
                <li>
                  low
                </li>
              </ul>
            </dd>
            <dt>listAs: UnsignedInt (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              The position of the personal information in the list of all PersonalInfo objects that have the
              same kind property value in the Card. If set, the listAs value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be higher than zero.
              Multiple personal information entries <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> have the same listAs property value or none.
              Sorting such same-valued entries is implementation-specific.
            </dd>
            <dt>label: String (optional).</dt>
            <dd>
              A custom label. See <xref target="prop-label"/>.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-personalInfo">
            <name>Example for the personalInfo Property</name>
            <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
"personalInfo": {
  "pi2": {
    "kind": "expertise",
    "value": "chemistry",
    "level": "high"
  },
  "pi1": {
    "kind": "hobby",
    "value": "reading",
    "level": "high"
  },
  "pi6": {
    "kind": "interest",
    "value": "r&b music",
    "level": "medium"
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="iana-media-type" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Media Type Registration</name>
        <t>This document defines a media type for use with JSContact data formatted in JSON.</t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Type name:</dt>
          <dd>application</dd>
          <dt>Subtype name:</dt>
          <dd>jscontact+json</dd>
          <dt>Required parameters:</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>None</t>
          </dd>
          <dt>Optional parameters:</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>version</t>
            <t>This parameter conveys the version of the JSContact data in the body part. It <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> occur
              more than once. If this parameter is set, then the values of all JSContact <xref target="iana-property-registry-version">version
              </xref> properties in the body part <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> match the parameter value.
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>Encoding considerations:</dt>
          <dd>This is the same as the encoding considerations of application/json, as specified in <xref target="RFC8259" sectionFormat="of" section="11"/>.
          </dd>
          <dt>Security considerations:</dt>
          <dd>See
            <xref target="security-considerations" format="default"/>
            of RFC 9553.
          </dd>
          <dt>Interoperability considerations:</dt>
          <dd>While JSContact is designed to avoid ambiguities as much as possible, when converting objects from other
            contact formats to/from JSContact, it is possible that differing representations for the same logical data
            or ambiguities in interpretation might arise. The semantic equivalence of two JSContact objects may be
            determined differently by different applications, for example, where URL values differ in case between the
            two objects.
          </dd>
          <dt>Published specification:</dt>
          <dd>RFC 9553</dd>
          <dt>Applications that use this media type:</dt>
          <dd>Applications that currently make use of the text/vcard media type can use this as an alternative.</dd>
          <dt>Fragment identifier considerations:</dt>
          <dd>A JSON Pointer fragment identifier may be used, as defined in <xref target="RFC6901" sectionFormat="comma" section="6"/>.
          </dd>
          <dt>Additional information:</dt>
          <dd>
            <t><br/>
            </t>
            <dl newline="false" spacing="compact">
              <dt>Magic number(s):</dt>
              <dd>N/A</dd>
              <dt>File extensions(s):</dt>
              <dd>N/A</dd>
              <dt>Macintosh file type code(s):</dt>
              <dd>N/A</dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>
          <dt>Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:</dt>
          <dd>calsify@ietf.org</dd>
          <dt>Intended usage:</dt>
          <dd>COMMON</dd>
          <dt>Restrictions on usage:</dt>
          <dd>N/A</dd>
          <dt>Author:</dt>
          <dd>See the "Authors' Addresses" section of RFC 9553.</dd>
          <dt>Change controller:</dt>
          <dd>IETF</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-jscontact-registry" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Creation of the JSContact Registry Group</name>
        <t>IANA has created the "JSContact" registry group. The new registry definitions in the following sections all
          belong to that group.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-registry-policy" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Registry Policy and Change Procedures</name>
        <t>Registry assignments that introduce <xref target="versioning">backwards-incompatible</xref> changes require
          the JSContact major version to change; other changes only require a change to the minor version. The registry
          policy for assignments that require the JSContact major version to change is Standards Action (<xref target="RFC8126" sectionFormat="comma" section="4.9"/>). The registry policy for other assignments is
          Specification Required (<xref target="RFC8126" sectionFormat="comma" section="4.6"/>).
        </t>
        <t>The designated expert (DE) decides if a major or minor version change is required and assigns the new version
          to the <xref target="iana-version-registry">"JSContact Version" registry</xref>. Version numbers increment by
          one, and a major version change resets the minor version to zero. An assignment may apply multiple changes and
          to more than one registry at once, in which case a single version change is sufficient. If the registry policy
          is Specification Required, then the DE may decide that it is enough to document the new assignment in the
          Description item of the respective registry.
        </t>
        <t>A registration <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have an intended usage of "common", "reserved", or "obsolete".
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>A "common" usage denotes an item with shared semantics and syntax across systems. Up-to-date systems <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> expect such items to occur in JSContact data.
          </li>
          <li>A "reserved" usage reserves an item in the registry without assigning semantics to avoid name collisions
            with future extensions or protocol use. Implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> expect or add items with
            such names outside the protocols or extensions that use them; otherwise, any such JSContact data is invalid.
          </li>
          <li>An "obsolete" usage denotes an item that is no longer expected to be added by up-to-date systems. A new
            assignment has probably been defined, covering the obsolete item's semantics. Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> expect such items to occur in JSContact data up to the "Until Version" registry field, inclusively.
            They <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> add such items for any version after which the item was obsoleted; otherwise,
            any such JSContact data is invalid.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>The intended usage of registry items may change between versions, but the DE must carefully
          consider the impact on existing implementations and standards before doing so.
        </t>
        <t>The registration procedure is not a formal standards process but rather an administrative procedure intended
          to allow community comments and to check whether it is coherent without excessive time delay. It is designed
          to encourage vendors to document and register new items they add for use cases not covered by the original
          specification, leading to increased interoperability.
        </t>
        <section anchor="iana-registry-preliminary-community-review" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Preliminary Community Review</name>
          <t>Notice of a potential new registration <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be sent to the Calext WG mailing list &lt;calsify@ietf.org&gt;
            for review. This mailing list is appropriate for soliciting community feedback on a proposed registry
            assignment.
          </t>
          <t>The intent of the public posting to this list is to solicit comments and feedback on the choice of the item
            name or value, the unambiguity of its description, and a review of any interoperability or security
            considerations. The submitter may submit a revised registration proposal or abandon the registration
            completely at any time.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-registry-submit-request-to-iana" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Submit Request to IANA</name>
          <t>Registration requests can be sent to IANA &lt;iana@iana.org&gt;.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-registry-designated-expert-review" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Designated Expert Review</name>
          <t>The primary concern of the DE is preventing name collisions and encouraging the submitter to document
            security and privacy considerations.
          </t>
          <t>A new type name, property name, or enumerated value <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> differ only in case from an
            already-registered name or value.
          </t>
          <t>For a common-use registration, the DE is expected to confirm that suitable documentation is available to
            ensure interoperability. The DE should also verify that the new assignment does not conflict with work that
            is active or already published within the IETF.
          </t>
          <t>The DE will either approve or deny the registration request and publish a notice of the decision to the
            Calext WG mailing list or its successor, as well as inform IANA. A denial notice must be justified by an
            explanation, and in the cases where it is possible, concrete suggestions on how the request can be modified
            to become acceptable should be provided.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-registry-change-procedures" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Change Procedures</name>
          <t>Once a JSContact registry group item has been published by IANA, the Change Controller may request a change
            to its definition. The same procedure that would be appropriate for the original registration request is
            used to process a change request.
          </t>
          <t>JSContact registrations do not get deleted; instead, items that are no longer believed appropriate for use
            are declared obsolete by a change to their "Intended Usage" field; such items will be clearly marked in the
            IANA registry.
          </t>
          <t>Significant changes to a JSContact registry item's definition should be requested only when there are
            serious omissions or errors in the published specification, as such changes may cause interoperability
            issues. When review is required, a change request may be denied if it renders entities that were valid under
            the previous definition invalid under the new definition.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-version-registry" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Creation of the JSContact Version Registry</name>
        <t>IANA has created the "JSContact Version" registry. The purpose of this new registry is to define the allowed
          value range of JSContact major and minor version numbers.
        </t>
        <t>The registry entries sort numerically in ascending order by the "Major Version" column, and entries with equal "Major Version" sort numerically in ascending order by the "Minor Version" column.</t>
        <t>The registry process is outlined in <xref target="iana-registry-policy" format="default"/>.
        </t>
        <section anchor="iana-version-registry-template" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>JSContact Version Registry Template</name>
          <dl newline="false">
            <dt>Major Version:</dt>
            <dd>The numeric value of a JSContact major version number. It <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a positive integer.
            </dd>
            <dt>Highest Minor Version:</dt>
            <dd>The maximum numeric value of a JSContact minor version for the given major version. It <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be zero or a positive integer. All numbers less than or equal to this value are valid minor version
              values for the given major version.
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-version-registry-contents" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Initial Contents of the JSContact Version Registry</name>
          <t>The following table lists the initial valid major and minor version number ranges.</t>
          <table anchor="tab-iana-version-registry" align="center">
            <name>JSContact Version Registry</name>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">Major Version</th>
                <th align="left">Highest Minor Version</th>
                <th align="left">Reference</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">1</td>
                <td align="left">0</td>
                <td align="left">RFC 9553</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-property-registry" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Creation of the JSContact Properties Registry</name>
        <t>IANA has created the "JSContact Properties" registry. The purpose of this new registry is to allow
          interoperability of extensions to JSContact objects.
        </t>
        <t>The registry entries sort alphabetically in ascending order by the following columns: "Property Name" first,
          "Property Context" second, and "Since Version" third. Equal entries sort in any order.
        </t>
        <t>The registry process for a new property is outlined in <xref target="iana-registry-policy" format="default"/>.
        </t>
        <section anchor="iana-property-registry-template" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>JSContact Properties Registry Template</name>
          <dl newline="false">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>The name of the property. The property name <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> already be registered for any of the
              object types listed in the "Property Context" field of this registration. Other object types <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> have already registered a different property with the same name; however, the same name <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only be used when the semantics are analogous.
            </dd>
            <dt>Property Type:</dt>
            <dd>For properties with intended usage other than "reserved", this
            is the type of this property, using type signatures as specified
            in <xref target="type-signatures" format="default"/>. The property
            type <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be registered in the "JSContact Types"
            registry. For reserved property names, the value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the
            verbatim string "not applicable".
            </dd>
            <dt>Property Context:</dt>
            <dd>A comma-separated list of JSContact object types (<xref target="iana-type-registry-contents"/>) that
              contain the property. For reserved property names, the value <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be the verbatim string "not applicable".
            </dd>
            <dt>Intended Usage:</dt>
            <dd>May be "common", "reserved", or "obsolete".</dd>
            <dt>Since Version:</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact version on which the property definition is based. The version <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one
              of the allowed values of the version property in the "JSContact Version" registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).
            </dd>
            <dt>Until Version:</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact version after which the property was obsoleted; therefore, it <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be
              used in later versions. The Until Version value either <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set or <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of the allowed values of the version property in the "JSContact Version" registry (see
              <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).
            </dd>
            <dt>Change Controller:</dt>
            <dd>Person or entity responsible for requesting a change to the entry's definition ("IETF" for RFCs from the
              IETF stream).
            </dd>
            <dt>Reference or Description:</dt>
            <dd>A brief description or RFC number and section reference where the property is specified. This must
              include references to all RFC documents where this property is introduced or updated. For reserved
              property names, the reference or description <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be omitted.
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-property-registry-contents" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Initial Contents of the JSContact Properties Registry</name>
          <t>The following table lists the initial "common" usage entries of the "JSContact Properties" registry. For
            all properties, the Since Version is "1.0", the Until Version is not set, the Change Controller is "IETF",
            and RFC section references are for RFC 9553.
          </t>
          <table anchor="tab-iana-property-registry" align="center">
            <name>JSContact Properties with "common" Usage</name>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">Property Name</th>
                <th align="left">Property Type</th>
                <th align="left">Property Context</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">@type</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address (<xref target="address"/>), AddressComponent (<xref target="addresscomponent"/>), Anniversary (<xref target="anniversaries"/>), Author (<xref target="notes" format="default"/>), Card (<xref target="cardtype"/>), Calendar (<xref target="calendars"/>), CryptoKey (<xref target="cryptoKeys"/>), Directory (<xref target="directories"/>), EmailAddress (<xref target="emails"/>), LanguagePref (<xref target="preferredLanguages"/>), Link <xref target="links"/>), Media (<xref target="media"/>), Name (<xref target="name"/>), NameComponent (<xref target="namecomponent"/>), Nickname (<xref target="nicknames"/>), Note (<xref target="notes"/>), OnlineService (<xref target="onlineServices"/>), Organization (<xref target="organizations"/>), OrgUnit (<xref target="organizations"/>), PartialDate (<xref target="anniversaries"/>), PersonalInfo (<xref target="personalInfo"/>), Phone (<xref target="phones"/>), Pronouns (<xref target="speakToAs"/>), Relation (<xref target="relatedTo"/>), SchedulingAddress (<xref target="schedulingAddresses"/>), SpeakToAs (<xref target="speakToAs"/>), Timestamp (<xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>), Title (<xref target="titles"/>)
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">address</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">EmailAddress (<xref target="emails" format="default"/>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">addresses</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Address]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="address" format="default"/>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">anniversaries</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Anniversary]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">author</td>
                <td align="left">Author</td>
                <td align="left">Note (<xref target="notes" format="default"/>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">calendars</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Calendar]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="calendars" format="default"/>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">calendarScale</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">PartialDate (<xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">components</td>
                <td align="left">AddressComponent[]</td>
                <td align="left">Address (<xref target="address" format="default"/>)</td> 
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">components</td>
                <td align="left">NameComponent[]</td>
                <td align="left">Name (<xref target="namecomponent" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">contexts</td>
                <td align="left">String[Boolean]</td>
                <td align="left">Address (<xref target="address"/>), Calendar (<xref target="calendars"/>), CryptoKey (<xref target="cryptoKeys"/>), Directory (<xref target="directories"/>), EmailAddress (<xref target="emails"/>), LanguagePref (<xref target="preferredLanguages"/>), Link (<xref target="links"/>), Media (<xref target="media"/>), Nickname (<xref target="nicknames"/>), OnlineService (<xref target="onlineServices"/>), Organization (<xref target="organizations"/>), Phone (<xref target="phones"/>), Pronouns (<xref target="speakToAs"/>), SchedulingAddress (<xref target="schedulingAddresses"/>). Also see Sections <xref target="resource" format="counter"/> and <xref target="prop-contexts" format="counter"/>.
                </td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">coordinates</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address (<xref target="address" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">countryCode</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address (<xref target="address" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">created</td>
                <td align="left">UTCDateTime</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="created"/>), Note (<xref target="notes"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">date</td>
                <td align="left">PartialDate|Timestamp</td>
                <td align="left">Anniversary (<xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>)</td>                
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">day</td>
                <td align="left">UnsignedInt</td>
                <td align="left">PartialDate (<xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">defaultSeparator</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address (<xref target="address"/>), Name (<xref target="name"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">directories</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Directory]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="directories" format="default"/>)</td>              
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">emails</td>
                <td align="left">Id[EmailAddress]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="emails" format="default"/>)</td>              
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">features</td>
                <td align="left">String[Boolean]</td>
                <td align="left">Phone (<xref target="phones" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">full</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address (<xref target="address"/>), Name (<xref target="name"/>)</td>              
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">grammaticalGender</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">SpeakToAs (<xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>)</td>                
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">isOrdered</td>
                <td align="left">Boolean</td>
                <td align="left">Address (<xref target="address"/>), Name (<xref target="name"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">keywords</td>
                <td align="left">String[Boolean]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="keywords" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">kind</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">AddressComponent (<xref target="addresscomponent"/>), Anniversary (<xref target="anniversaries"/>), Calendar (<xref target="calendars"/>), Card (<xref target="kind"/>), CryptoKey (<xref target="cryptoKeys"/>), Directory (<xref target="directories"/>), Link (<xref target="links"/>), Media (<xref target="media"/>), NameComponent (<xref target="namecomponent"/>), PersonalInfo (<xref target="personalInfo"/>), Title (<xref target="titles"/>)
                </td>              
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">label</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Calendar (<xref target="calendars"/>), CryptoKey (<xref target="cryptoKeys"/>), Directory (<xref target="directories"/>), EmailAddress (<xref target="emails"/>), Link (<xref target="links"/>), Media (<xref target="media"/>), OnlineService (<xref target="onlineServices"/>), PersonalInfo (<xref target="personalInfo"/>), Phone (<xref target="phones"/>), SchedulingAddress (<xref target="schedulingAddresses"/>). Also see Sections <xref target="resource" format="counter"/> and <xref target="prop-label" format="counter"/>.
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">language</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="language"/>), LanguagePref (<xref target="preferredLanguages"/>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">level</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">PersonalInfo (<xref target="personalInfo"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">links</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Link]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="links" format="default"/>)</td>                
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">listAs</td>
                <td align="left">UnsignedInt</td>
                <td align="left">Directory (<xref target="directories"/>), PersonalInfo (<xref target="personalInfo"/>)</td>            
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">localizations</td>
                <td align="left">String[PatchObject]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="localizations" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">media</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Media]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="media" format="default"/>)</td>              
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">mediaType</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Calendar (<xref target="calendars"/>), CryptoKey (<xref target="cryptoKeys"/>), Directory (<xref target="directories"/>), Link (<xref target="links"/>), Media (<xref target="media"/>). Also see <xref target="resource"/>.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">members</td>
                <td align="left">String[Boolean]</td>
                <td align="left">Card  (<xref target="members" format="default"/>)</td>              
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">month</td>
                <td align="left">UnsignedInt</td>
                <td align="left">PartialDate (<xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>)</td>              
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">name</td>
                <td align="left">Name</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="name" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">name</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Author  (<xref target="notes"/>), Nickname (<xref target="nicknames"/>), Organization (<xref target="organizations"/>), OrgUnit (<xref target="organizations"/>), Title (<xref target="titles"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">nicknames</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Nickname]</td>
                <td align="left">Card  (<xref target="nicknames" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">note</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Note (<xref target="notes" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">notes</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Note]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="notes" format="default"/>)</td>              
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">number</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Phone (<xref target="phones" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">onlineServices</td>
                <td align="left">Id[OnlineService]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="onlineServices" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">organizationId</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Title (<xref target="titles" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">organizations</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Organization]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="organizations" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">personalInfo</td>
                <td align="left">Id[PersonalInfo]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">phones</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Phone]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="phones" format="default"/>)</td>              
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">phonetic</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">AddressComponent (<xref target="addresscomponent"/>), NameComponent (<xref target="namecomponent"/>)</td>              
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">phoneticScript</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address (<xref target="address"/>), Name (<xref target="name"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">phoneticSystem</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address (<xref target="address" format="counter"/>), Name (<xref target="name"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">place</td>
                <td align="left">Address</td>
                <td align="left">Anniversary (<xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>)</td>              
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">pref</td>
                <td align="left">UnsignedInt</td>
                <td align="left">Address (<xref target="address"/>), Calendar (<xref target="calendars"/>), CryptoKey (<xref target="cryptoKeys"/>), Directory (<xref target="directories"/>), EmailAddress (<xref target="emails"/>), LanguagePref (<xref target="preferredLanguages"/>), Link (<xref target="links"/>), Media (<xref target="media"/>), Nickname (<xref target="nicknames"/>), OnlineService (<xref target="onlineServices"/>), Phone (<xref target="phones"/>), Pronouns (<xref target="speakToAs"/>), SchedulingAddress (<xref target="schedulingAddresses"/>). Also see Sections <xref target="resource" format="counter"/> and <xref target="prop-pref" format="counter"/>.
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">preferredLanguages</td>
                <td align="left">String[LanguagePref]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="preferredLanguages" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">prodId</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="prodId" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">pronouns</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Pronouns]</td>
                <td align="left">SpeakToAs (<xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">relatedTo</td>
                <td align="left">String[Relation]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">relation</td>
                <td align="left">String[Boolean]</td>
                <td align="left">Relation (<xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>)</td>                
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">schedulingAddresses</td>
                <td align="left">Id[SchedulingAddress]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="schedulingAddresses" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">service</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">OnlineService (<xref target="onlineServices" format="default"/>)</td>              
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">sortAs</td>
                <td align="left">String[String]</td>
                <td align="left">Name (<xref target="name" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">sortAs</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Organization (<xref target="organizations" format="default"/>), OrgUnit (<xref target="organizations"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">speakToAs</td>
                <td align="left">SpeakToAs</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">timeZone</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Address (<xref target="address" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">titles</td>
                <td align="left">Id[Title]</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="titles" format="default"/>)</td>              
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">uid</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="uid" format="default"/>)</td>                
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">units</td>
                <td align="left">OrgUnit[]</td>
                <td align="left">Organization (<xref target="organizations" format="default"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">updated</td>
                <td align="left">UTCDateTime</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="updated" format="default"/>)</td>                
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">uri</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Author (<xref target="notes"/>), Calendar (<xref target="calendars"/>), CryptoKey (<xref target="cryptoKeys"/>), Directory (<xref target="directories"/>), Link (<xref target="links"/>), Media (<xref target="media"/>), OnlineService (<xref target="onlineServices"/>), SchedulingAddress (<xref target="schedulingAddresses"/>). Also see <xref target="resource"/>.
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">user</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">OnlineService (<xref target="onlineServices" format="default"/>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">utc</td>
                <td align="left">UTCDateTime</td>
                <td align="left">Timestamp (<xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">value</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">AddressComponent (<xref target="addresscomponent"/>), NameComponent (<xref target="namecomponent"/>), PersonalInfo (<xref target="personalInfo"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr anchor="iana-property-registry-version">
                <td align="left">version</td>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">Card (<xref target="prop-version"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">year</td>
                <td align="left">UnsignedInt</td>
                <td align="left">PartialDate (<xref target="anniversaries"/>)</td>               
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <t>The following table lists the initial "reserved" usage entries of the "JSContact Properties" registry. For
            this property, the Change Controller is "IETF", and the RFC section reference is for RFC 9553.
          </t>
          <table anchor="tab-iana-reserved-property-registry" align="center">
            <name>JSContact Properties with "reserved" Usage</name>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">Property Name</th>
                <th align="left">Property Type</th>
                <th align="left">Property Context</th>
		<th align="left">Intended Usage</th>
                <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">extra</td>
                <td align="left">not applicable</td>
                <td align="left">not applicable</td>
		<td align="left">reserved</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="prop-extra" format="default"/>
                </td>
               
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-type-registry" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Creation of the JSContact Types Registry</name>
        <t>IANA has created the "JSContact Types" registry. The purpose of this new registry is to avoid name collisions
          for JSContact type names and provide a complete reference for all data types used for JSContact property
          values.
        </t>
        <t>The registry entries sort alphabetically in ascending order by the "Type Name" column. Equal entries sort in
          any order.
        </t>
        <t>The registry process for a new type is outlined in <xref target="iana-registry-policy" format="default"/>.
        </t>
        <section anchor="iana-type-registry-template" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>JSContact Types Registry Template</name>
          <dl newline="false">
            <dt>Type Name:</dt>
            <dd>The name of the type.</dd>
            <dt>Intended Usage:</dt>
            <dd>May be "common", "reserved", or "obsolete".</dd>
            <dt>Since Version:</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact version on which this type definition is based. The version <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of
              the allowed values of the version property in the "JSContact Version" registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).
            </dd>
            <dt>Until Version:</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact version after which the type definition was obsoleted; therefore, it <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be used in later versions. The Until Version value either <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set or <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of the allowed values of the version property in the "JSContact Version" registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).
            </dd>
            <dt>Change Controller:</dt>
            <dd>Person or entity responsible for requesting a change to the entry's definition ("IETF" for RFCs from the
              IETF stream).
            </dd>
            <dt>Reference or Description:</dt>
            <dd>A brief description or RFC number and section reference where the Type is specified. For reserved type
              names, the reference or description <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be omitted.
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-type-registry-contents" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Initial Contents of the JSContact Types Registry</name>
          <t>The following table lists the initial "common" usage entries in the "JSContact Types" registry. For all of
            these types, the Since Version is "1.0", the Until Version is not set, the Change Controller is "IETF", and
            RFC section references are for RFC 9553.
          </t>
          <table anchor="tab-iana-type-registry-common" align="left">
            <name>JSContact Types with "common" Usage</name>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">Type Name</th>
                <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Address</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="address" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">AddressComponent</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Anniversary</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Author</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="notes" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Boolean</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="type-signatures" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Calendar</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="calendars" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Card</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="card" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">CryptoKey</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="cryptoKeys" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Directory</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="directories" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">EmailAddress</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="emails" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Id</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="id" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Int</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="int-unsignedint" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">LanguagePref</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="preferredLanguages" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Link</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="links" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Media</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="media" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Name</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="name" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">NameComponent</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="namecomponent" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Nickname</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="nicknames" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Note</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="notes" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Number</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="type-signatures" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">OnlineService</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="onlineServices" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Organization</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="organizations" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">OrgUnit</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="organizations" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">PartialDate</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">PatchObject</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="patchobject" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">PersonalInfo</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Phone</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Pronouns</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Relation</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">SchedulingAddress</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="schedulingAddresses" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">SpeakToAs</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">String</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="type-signatures" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Timestamp</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Title</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="titles" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">UnsignedInt</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="int-unsignedint" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">UTCDateTime</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="utcdatetime" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <t>The following table lists the initial "reserved" usage entry of the "JSContact Types" registry. For this
            type, the version is "1.0", the Change Controller is "IETF", and the RFC section reference is for RFC 9553.
          </t>
          <table anchor="tab-iana-type-registry-reserved" align="left">
            <name>JSContact Types with "reserved" Usage</name>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left">Type Name</th>
                <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">Resource</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <xref target="resource" format="default"/>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-enum-registry" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Creation of the JSContact Enum Values Registry</name>
        <t>IANA has created the "JSContact Enum Values" registry. The purpose of the new registry is to allow
          interoperable extension of semantics for JSContact properties with enumerable values. Each such property will
          have a subregistry of allowed values.
        </t>
        <t>The registry entries sort alphabetically in ascending order by the following columns: "Property Name" first,
          "Property Context" second, and "Since Version" third. The enum values sort alphabetically in ascending order.
          Equal entries sort in any order.
        </t>
        <t>The registry process for a new enum value or adding a new enumerable property is outlined in <xref target="iana-registry-policy" format="default"/>.
        </t>
        <section anchor="iana-enum-registry-registry-template" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>JSContact Enum Values Registry Property Template</name>
          <t>This template is for adding a subregistry for a new enumerable property to the "JSContact Enum Values"
            registry.
          </t>
          <dl newline="false">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>The name(s) of the property or properties where these values may be used. This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
              registered in the "JSContact Properties" registry.
            </dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>The list of allowed object types where the property or properties may appear, as registered in the
              "JSContact Properties" registry. This disambiguates where there may be two distinct properties with the
              same name in different contexts.
            </dd>
            <dt>Since Version:</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact version on which the enum value definition is based. The version <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
              one of the allowed values of the version property in the "JSContact Version" registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).
            </dd>
            <dt>Until Version:</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact version after which the enum value definition was obsoleted; therefore, the enum value
              definition <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be used in later versions. The Until Version value either <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set or <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of the allowed values of the version property in the
              "JSContact Version" registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).
            </dd>
            <dt>Change Controller:</dt>
            <dd>Person or entity responsible for requesting a change to the entry's definition ("IETF" for RFCs from the
              IETF stream).
            </dd>
            <dt>Reference or Description:</dt><dd>A brief description or RFC number and
            section reference for the semantics of the value.</dd>
	  </dl>
	    <t>
            Note that the initial contents will be the initial list of defined values for the enum, using the template defined in <xref target="iana-enum-registry-value-template" format="default"/>. A subregistry will be created with
              these values for this property name/context tuple.
            </t>
	  
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-enum-registry-value-template" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>JSContact Enum Values Registry Value Template</name>
          <t>This template is for adding a new enum value to a subregistry in the "JSContact Enum Values" registry.</t>
          <dl newline="false">
            <dt>Enum Value:</dt>
            <dd>The verbatim value of the enum.</dd>
            <dt>Since Version:</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact version on which the enum value definition is based. The version <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
              one of the allowed values of the version property in the "JSContact Version" registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).
            </dd>
            <dt>Until Version:</dt>
            <dd>The JSContact version after which the enum value was obsoleted; therefore, the enum value <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be used in later versions. The Until Version value either <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set or <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of the allowed values of the version property in the "JSContact Version" registry (see <xref target="tab-iana-version-registry"/>).
            </dd>
	    <dt> Change Controller:</dt><dd>Person or entity responsible for requesting a
      change to the entry's definition ("IETF" for RFCs from the IETF
      stream).</dd>
            <dt>Reference or Description:</dt>
            <dd>A brief description or RFC number and section reference for the semantics of the value.</dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-enum-registry-contents" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Initial Contents of the JSContact Enum Values Registry</name>
          <t>For all entries in each subregistry created in this section, the Since Version is "1.0", the Until Version
            is not set, the Change Controller is "IETF", and RFC section references are for RFC 9553.
          </t>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>contexts</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Address</dd>
    	    </dl>
	 <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-addr-contexts" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for contexts (Context: Address)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">billing</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="address" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">delivery</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="address" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">private</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="prop-contexts" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">work</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="prop-contexts" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>contexts</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Calendar, CryptoKey, Directory, EmailAddress, LanguagePref, Link, Media, Nickname, OnlineService,
              Organization, Phone, Pronouns, SchedulingAddress
          </dd></dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-contexts" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for contexts (Context: Calendar, CryptoKey, Directory, EmailAddress,
                  LanguagePref, Link, Media, Nickname, OnlineService, Organization, Phone, Pronouns, SchedulingAddress)
                </name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">private</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="prop-contexts" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">work</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="prop-contexts" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>features</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Phone</dd>
	    </dl>

	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-phone-features" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for features (Context: Phone)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">fax</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">main-number</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">mobile</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">pager</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">text</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">textphone</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">video</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">voice</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="phones" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>grammaticalGender</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>SpeakToAs</dd>
	   </dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-speaktoas-grammaticalgender" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for grammaticalGender (Context: SpeakToAs)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">animate</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">common</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">feminine</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">inanimate</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">masculine</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">neuter</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="speakToAs" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>AddressComponent</dd>
	  </dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-addresscomponent-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: AddressComponent)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">apartment</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">block</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">building</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">country</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">direction</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">district</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">floor</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">landmark</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">locality</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">name</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">number</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">postcode</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">postOfficeBox</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">region</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">room</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">separator</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">subdistrict</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="addresscomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Anniversary</dd>
	     </dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-anniversary-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: Anniversary)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">birth</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">death</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">wedding</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="anniversaries" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Calendar</dd>
	     </dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-calendarresource-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: Calendar)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">calendar</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="calendars" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">freeBusy</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="calendars" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Card</dd>
	     </dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-card-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: Card)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">application</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="kind" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">device</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="kind" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">group</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="kind" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">individual</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="kind" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">location</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="kind" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">org</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="kind" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Directory</dd>
	     </dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-directoryresource-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: Directory)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">directory</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="directories" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">entry</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="directories" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Link</dd>
	     </dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-linkresource-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: Link)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">contact</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="links" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Media</dd>
	     </dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-mediaresource-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: Media)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">logo</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="media" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">photo</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="media" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">sound</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="media" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>NameComponent</dd>
	     </dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-namecomponent-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: NameComponent)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">credential</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="namecomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">generation</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="namecomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">given</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="namecomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">given2</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="namecomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">separator</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="namecomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">surname</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="namecomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">surname2</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="namecomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">title</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="namecomponent" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>PersonalInfo</dd>
	     </dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-personalinformation-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: PersonalInfo)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">expertise</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">hobby</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">interest</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>kind</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Title</dd>
	     </dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-title-kind" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for kind (Context: Title)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">role</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="titles" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">title</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="titles" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>level</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>PersonalInfo</dd>
	     </dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-personalinformation-level" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for level (Context: PersonalInfo)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">high</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">low</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">medium</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="personalInfo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>phoneticSystem</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Address, Name</dd>
	     </dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-pronounce-system" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for phoneticSystem (Context: Address, Name)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">ipa</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="prop-phonetic" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">jyut</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="prop-phonetic" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">piny</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="prop-phonetic" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Property Name:</dt>
            <dd>relation</dd>
            <dt>Context:</dt>
            <dd>Relation</dd>
	     </dl>
	    <dl spacing="compact" newline="false" indent="20">
            <dt>Initial Contents:</dt>
            <dd>
              <table anchor="tab-iana-enum-relation-relation" align="left">
                <name>JSContact Enum Values for relation (Context: Relation)</name>
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="left">Enum Value</th>
                    <th align="left">Reference/Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">acquaintance</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">agent</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">child</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">colleague</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">contact</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">co-resident</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">co-worker</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">crush</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">date</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">emergency</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">friend</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">kin</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">me</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">met</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">muse</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">neighbor</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">parent</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">sibling</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">spouse</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left">sweetheart</td>
                    <td align="left">
                      <xref target="relatedTo" format="default"/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>Contact information is very privacy sensitive. It can reveal the identity, location, credentials information,
        employment status, interests and hobbies, and social network of a user. Its transmission and storage must be
        done carefully to protect it from possible threats such as eavesdropping, replay, message insertion, deletion,
        modification, and on-path attacks.
      </t>
      <t>The data being stored and transmitted may be used in systems with real-world consequences. For example, a
        malicious actor might provide JSContact data that uses the name of another person but insert their contact
        details to impersonate the unknown victim. Such systems must be careful to authenticate all data they receive to
        prevent them from being subverted and ensure the change comes from an authorized entity.
      </t>
      <t>This document only defines the data format; such considerations are primarily the concern of the API or method
        of storage and transmission of such files.
      </t>
      <section anchor="json-parsing" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>JSON Parsing</name>
        <t>The security considerations of
          <xref target="RFC8259" format="default"/>
          apply to the use of JSON as the data interchange format.
        </t>
        <t>As for any serialization format, parsers need to thoroughly check the syntax of the supplied data. JSON uses
          opening and closing brackets for several types and structures, and it is possible that the end of the supplied
          data will be reached when scanning for a matching closing bracket; this is an error condition, and
          implementations need to stop scanning at the end of the supplied data.
        </t>
        <t>JSON also uses a string encoding with some escape sequences to encode special characters within a string.
          Care is needed when processing these escape sequences to ensure that they are fully formed before the special
          processing is triggered, with special care taken when the escape sequences appear adjacent to other
          (non-escaped) special characters or adjacent to the end of data (as in the previous paragraph).
        </t>
        <t>If parsing JSON into a non-textual structured data format, implementations may need to allocate storage to
          hold JSON string elements. Since JSON does not use explicit string lengths, the risk of denial of service due
          to resource exhaustion is small, but implementations may still wish to place limits on the size of allocations
          they are willing to make in any given context, to avoid untrusted data causing excessive memory allocation.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="uri-values" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>URI Values</name>
        <t>Several JSContact properties contain URIs as values, and processing these properties requires extra care.
          <xref target="RFC3986" sectionFormat="of" section="7"/>
          discusses security risks related to URIs.
        </t>
        <t>Fetching remote resources carries inherent risks. Connections must only be allowed on well-known ports, using
          allowed protocols (generally, just HTTP/HTTPS on their default ports). The URL must be resolved externally and
          not allowed to access internal resources. Connecting to an external source reveals IP (and therefore often
          location) information.
        </t>
        <t>A maliciously constructed JSContact object may contain a very large number of URIs. In the case of published
          address books with a large number of subscribers, such objects could be widely distributed. Implementations
          should be careful to limit the automatic fetching of linked resources to reduce the risk of this being an
          amplification vector for a denial-of-service attack.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2046.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2426.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3339.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4648.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5322.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5646.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5870.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6350.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6901.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7493.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7529.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8141.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8259.xml"/>
       
        <reference anchor="ISO.3166-1">
          <front>
            <title>Codes for the representation of names of countries and their subdivisions -- Part 1: Country codes
            </title>
            <author>
              <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="August" year="2020"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="3166-1:2020"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="IANA-TZ" target="https://www.iana.org/time-zones">
          <front>
            <title>Time Zone Database</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IANA</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="IANA-vCard" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/vcard-elements">
          <front>
            <title>vCard Elements</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IANA</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3966.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3987.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6351.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6473.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6474.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6715.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6869.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7095.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9499.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8605.xml"/>
	
        <!--[I-D.ietf-uuidrev-rfc4122bis] in AUTH48 state; will be RFC 9562. This doc is waiting on it to be published in order to include the RFC number.-->
        <reference anchor="RFC9562" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9562">
          <front>
            <title>Universally Unique IDentifiers (UUIDs)</title>
            <author fullname="Kyzer R. Davis" initials="K." surname="Davis">
              <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Brad G. Peabody" initials="B." surname="Peabody">
              <organization>Uncloud</organization>
            </author>
            <author fullname="P. Leach" initials="P." surname="Leach">
              <organization>University of Washington</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="May" year="2024"/>
          </front>
         <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9562"/>
         <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9562"/>
        </reference>
	
        <!--[I-D.ietf-calext-vcard-jscontact-extensions] in AUTH48-DONE; companion doc-->
	<!-- This is going to be RFC 9554 -->
<reference anchor="RFC9554" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9554">
          <front>
            <title>vCard Format Extensions for JSContact</title>
            <author fullname="Robert Stepanek" initials="R." surname="Stepanek">
              <organization>Fastmail</organization>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Mario Loffredo" initials="M." surname="Loffredo">
              <organization>IIT-CNR</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="May" year="2024"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9554"/>
	  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9554"/>
        </reference>
	
        <!--[I-D.ietf-calext-jscontact-vcard] in AUTH48-DONE; companion doc-->
	<!-- This is going to be RFC 9555 -->
        <reference anchor="RFC9555" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9555">
          <front>
            <title>JSContact: Converting from and to vCard</title>
            <author fullname="Robert Stepanek" initials="R." surname="Stepanek">
              <organization>Fastmail</organization>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Mario Loffredo" initials="M." surname="Loffredo">
              <organization>IIT-CNR</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="May" year="2024"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9555"/>
	   <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9555"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="IPA" target="https://www.internationalphoneticalphabet.org/">
          <front>
            <title>International Phonetic Alphabet</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IPA</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="UBiDi" target="https://www.unicode.org/reports/tr9/">
          <front>
            <title>Unicode Standard Annex #9: Unicode Bidirectional Algorithm</title>
            <author>
              <organization>The Unicode Consortium</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="August" year="2023"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Unicode" value="15.1.0"/>
          <refcontent>Revision 48</refcontent>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="WHATWG-URL" target="https://url.spec.whatwg.org">
          <front>
            <title>URL Living Standard</title>
            <author>
              <organization>WHATWG
              </organization>
            </author>
            <date month="January" year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
