<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-lamps-automation-keyusages-08" number="9809" updates="" obsoletes="" category="std" consensus="true" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" tocDepth="3" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="false" symRefs="true" version="3">

  <front>
    
    <title abbrev="EKU for Configuration, Updates, and Safety">X.509 Certificate Extended Key Usage (EKU) for Configuration, Updates, and Safety-Critical Communication</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9809"/>
    <author initials="H." surname="Brockhaus" fullname="Hendrik Brockhaus">
      <organization abbrev="Siemens">Siemens</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Werner-von-Siemens-Strasse 1</street>
          <city>Munich</city>
          <code>80333</code>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>hendrik.brockhaus@siemens.com</email>
        <uri>https://www.siemens.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Goltzsche" fullname="David Goltzsche">
      <organization>Siemens Mobility</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Ackerstrasse 22</street>
          <city>Braunschweig</city>
          <code>38126</code>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>david.goltzsche@siemens.com</email>
        <uri>https://www.mobility.siemens.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2025" month="July"/>

    <area>SEC</area>
    <workgroup>lamps</workgroup>

    <keyword>Industrial Automation</keyword>
    <keyword>ERJU</keyword>
    <keyword>extended key usage</keyword>
    <keyword>extension</keyword>
    <keyword>PKI</keyword>
    <abstract>

<t>RFC 5280 defines the Extended Key Usage (EKU) extension and specifies several extended key purpose identifiers (KeyPurposeIds) for use with that extension in X.509 certificates.  This document defines KeyPurposeIds for general-purpose and trust anchor configuration files, for software and firmware update packages, and for safety-critical communication to be included in the EKU extension of X.509 v3 public key certificates.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

<section anchor="Intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Key purpose identifiers (KeyPurposeIds) added to the certificate's EKU extension <xref target="RFC5280"/> are meant to express intent as to the purpose of the named usage, for humans and complying libraries. A full list of KeyPurposeIds is maintained in the IANA registry "SMI Security for PKIX Extended Key Purpose" <xref target="SMI-PKIX-PURPOSE"/>. The use of the anyExtendedKeyUsage KeyPurposeId, as defined in <xref section="4.2.1.12" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC5280"/>, is generally considered a poor practice.</t>
      <t>This document defines KeyPurposeIds for certificates that are used for the following purposes, among others:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t>Validating signatures of general-purpose software configuration files.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Validating signatures of trust anchor configuration files.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Validating signatures of software and firmware update packages.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Authenticating communication endpoints authorized for safety-critical communication.</t>
        </li>
      </ul>

      <t>If the purpose of an issued certificate is not restricted (i.e., the operations of the public key contained in the certificate can be used in unintended ways), the risk of cross-application attacks is increased. Failure to ensure adequate segregation of duties means that an application or system that generates the public/private keys and applies for a certificate to the operator Certification Authority (CA) could obtain a certificate that can be misused for tasks that this application or system is not entitled to perform. For example, management of trust anchors is a particularly critical task. A device could potentially accept a trust anchor configuration file signed by a service that uses a certificate with no EKU or with the KeyPurposeIds id-kp-codeSigning (<xref section="4.2.1.12" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC5280"/>) or id-kp-documentSigning <xref target="RFC9336"/>. A device should only accept trust anchor configuration files if the file is verified with a certificate that has been explicitly issued for this purpose.</t>
      <t>The KeyPurposeId id-kp-serverAuth (<xref section="4.2.1.12" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC5280"/>) can be used to identify that the certificate is for a TLS WWW server, and the KeyPurposeId id-kp-clientAuth (<xref section="4.2.1.12" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC5280"/>) can be used to identify that the certificate is for a TLS WWW client. However, there are currently no KeyPurposeIds for usage with X.509 certificates for safety-critical communication.</t>
      <t>This document addresses the above problems by defining KeyPurposeIds for the EKU extension of X.509 public key certificates. These certificates are used either for signing files (general-purpose configuration files, trust anchor configuration files, and software and firmware update packages) or for safety-critical communication.</t>
      <t>Vendor-defined KeyPurposeIds used within a PKI governed by vendors typically do not pose interoperability concerns, as non-critical extensions can be safely ignored if unrecognized. However, using KeyPurposeIds outside of their intended vendor-controlled environment or in ExtendedKeyUsage extensions that have been marked critical can lead to interoperability issues. Therefore, it is advisable not to rely on vendor-defined KeyPurposeIds. Instead, this specification defines standard KeyPurposeIds to ensure interoperability across various vendors and industries.</t>
      <t>The definitions of these KeyPurposeIds are intentionally broad to allow their use in different deployments even though they were initially motivated by industrial automation and rail automation (see <xref target="UseCases"/>). The details for each deployment need to be described in the relevant technical standards and certificate policies.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="conventions">
      <name>Conventions and Definitions</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be
    interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref
    target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as
    shown here.
        </t>

<t>This document uses terms defined in <xref target="RFC5280"/>. X.509 certificate extensions are defined using ASN.1 <xref target="X.680"/> <xref target="X.690"/>.</t>
      <t>The term "safety-critical communication" refers to communication that could, under certain conditions, lead to a state in which human life, health, property, or the environment is endangered. For the definition of "safety", see <xref target="NIST.SP.800-160"/> and <xref target="ISO.IEC.IEEE_12207"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="EKU">
      <name>Extended Key Purpose for Configuration Files, Update Packages, and Safety-Critical Communication</name>
      
      <t>This specification defines the following KeyPurposeIds:</t>
<ul>
  <li>id-kp-configSigning: Used for signing general-purpose configuration
   files.</li>
  <li>id-kp-trustAnchorConfigSigning: Used for signing trust anchor
   configuration files.</li>
  <li>id-kp-updatePackageSigning: Used for signing software or firmware
   update packages.</li>
  <li>id-kp-safetyCommunication: Used for authenticating communication peers
   for safety-critical communication.</li>
</ul>
<t>As described in <xref section="4.2.1.12" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC5280"/>,
"[i]f the [extended key usage] extension is present, then the certificate <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only be used for one of the purposes indicated", and "[i]f multiple [key] purposes are indicated the application need not recognize all purposes indicated, as long as the intended purpose is present".</t>

      <t>None of the KeyPurposeIds specified in this document are intrinsically mutually exclusive.  Instead, the acceptable combinations of those KeyPurposeIds with others specified in this document and with other KeyPurposeIds specified elsewhere are left to the technical standards of the respective application and the certificate policy of the respective PKI.  For example, a technical standard may specify the following: "Different keys and certificates must be used for safety-critical communication and for trust anchor updates, and a relying party must ignore the KeyPurposeId id-kp-trustAnchorConfigSigning if id-kp-safetyCommunication is one of the specified key purposes in a certificate." For example, the certificate policy may specify the following: "The id-kp-safetyCommunication KeyPuposeId should not be included in an issued certificate together with the KeyPurposeId id-kp-trustAnchorConfigSigning." Technical standards and certificate policies of different applications may specify other rules.  Further considerations on prohibiting combinations of KeyPurposeIds is described in <xref target="security"/>.</t>
      <t>Systems or applications that verify the signature of a general-purpose configuration file or trust anchor configuration file, the signature of a software or firmware update package, or the authentication of a communication peer for safety-critical communication <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> require that corresponding KeyPurposeIds be specified by the EKU extension. If the certificate requester knows the certificate users are mandated to use these KeyPurposeIds, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> enforce their inclusion. Additionally, such a certificate requester <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ensure that the Key Usage extension be set to digitalSignature for signature verification, to keyEncipherment for public key encryption, and keyAgreement for key agreement.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="include-EKU">
      <name>Including the Extended Key Purpose in Certificates</name>
      <t><xref target="RFC5280"/> specifies the EKU X.509 certificate extension for use on end-entity certificates. The extension indicates one or more purposes for which the certified public key is valid. The EKU extension can be used in conjunction with the Key Usage (KU) extension, which indicates the set of basic cryptographic operations for which the certified key may be used. The EKU extension syntax is repeated here for convenience:</t>
      <sourcecode type="asn.1"><![CDATA[
   ExtKeyUsageSyntax  ::=  SEQUENCE SIZE (1..MAX) OF KeyPurposeId

   KeyPurposeId  ::=  OBJECT IDENTIFIER
]]></sourcecode>

      <t>As described in <xref target="RFC5280"/>, the EKU extension may, at the option of the certificate issuer, be either critical or non-critical. The inclusion of KeyPurposeIds id-kp-configSigning, id-kp-trustAnchorConfigSigning, id-kp-updatePackageSigning, and id-kp-safetyCommunication in a certificate indicates that the public key encoded in the certificate has been certified for the following usages:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t>id-kp-configSigning</t>
          <t>A public key contained in a certificate containing the KeyPurposeId id-kp-configSigning may be used for verifying signatures of general-purpose configuration files of various formats (e.g., XML, YAML, or JSON). Configuration files are used to configure hardware or software.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>id-kp-trustAnchorConfigSigning</t>
          <t>A public key contained in a certificate containing the KeyPurposeId id-kp-trustAnchorConfigSigning may be used for verifying signatures of trust anchor configuration files of various formats (e.g., XML, YAML, or JSON).
Trust anchor configuration files are used to add or remove trust anchors to the trust store of a device.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>id-kp-updatePackageSigning</t>
          <t>A public key contained in a certificate containing the KeyPurposeId id-kp-updatePackageSigning may be used for verifying signatures of software or firmware update packages. Update packages are used to install software (including bootloader, firmware, safety-related applications, and others) on systems.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>id-kp-safetyCommunication</t>
          <t>A public key contained in a certificate containing the KeyPurposeId id-kp-safetyCommunication may be used to authenticate a communication peer for safety-critical communication based on TLS or other protocols.</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <sourcecode type="asn.1"><![CDATA[
   id-kp  OBJECT IDENTIFIER  ::=
       { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1)
         security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) 3 }

   id-kp-configSigning             OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 41 }
   id-kp-trustAnchorConfigSigning  OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 42 }
   id-kp-updatePackageSigning      OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 43 }
   id-kp-safetyCommunication       OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 44 }
]]></sourcecode>

    </section>
    <section anchor="ca-implication">
      <name>Implications for a Certification Authority</name>
      <t>The procedures and practices employed by a certification authority must ensure that the correct values for the EKU extension and the KU extension are inserted in each certificate that is issued. The inclusion of the id-kp-configSigning, id-kp-trustAnchorConfigSigning, id-kp-updatePackageSigning, and id-kp-safetyCommunication KeyPurposeIds does not preclude the inclusion of other KeyPurposeIds.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The security considerations of <xref target="RFC5280"/> are applicable to this document. These EKU key purposes do not introduce new security risks but instead reduce existing security risks by providing the means to identify if a certificate is generated to verify the signature of a general-purpose or trust anchor configuration file, the signature of a software or firmware update package, or the authentication of a communication peer for safety-critical communication.</t>
      <t>To reduce the risk of specific cross-protocol attacks, the relying party may additionally prohibit use of specific combinations of KeyPurposeIds.  The procedure for allowing or disallowing combinations of KeyPurposeIds using excluded KeyPurposeId and permitted KeyPurposeId, as carried out by a relying party, is defined in <xref section="4" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC9336"/>.  The technical standards and certificate policies of the application should explicitly enumerate requirements for excluded or permitted KeyPurposeIds or their combinations. It is out of scope of this document to enumerate those, but an example of excluded KeyPurposeIds can be the presence of the anyExtendedKeyUsage KeyPurposeId. Examples of allowed KeyPurposeIds combinations can be the presence of id-kp-safetyCommunication together with id-kp-clientAuth or id-kp-serverAuth.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="privacy">
      <name>Privacy Considerations</name>
      <t>In some protocols (e.g., TLS 1.2 <xref target="RFC5246"></xref>), certificates are exchanged in the clear. In other protocols (e.g., TLS 1.3 <xref target="RFC8446"></xref>), certificates are encrypted. The inclusion of the EKU extension can help an observer determine the purpose of the certificate. In addition, if the certificate is issued by a public certification authority, the inclusion of an EKU extension can help an attacker to monitor the Certificate Transparency logs <xref target="RFC9162"/> to identify the purpose of the certificate, which may reveal private information of the certificate subject.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>IANA has registered the following ASN.1 <xref target="X.680"/> module OID in the "SMI Security for PKIX Module Identifier" registry <xref target="SMI-PKIX-MOD"/>. This OID is defined in <xref target="asn1"/>.</t>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Decimal</th>
            <th align="left">Description</th>
            <th align="left">Reference</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">117</td>
            <td align="left">id-mod-config-update-sc-eku</td>
            <td align="left">RFC 9809</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>IANA has also registered the following OIDs in the "SMI Security for PKIX Extended Key Purpose" registry <xref target="SMI-PKIX-PURPOSE"/>.  These OIDs are defined in <xref target="include-EKU"/>.</t>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Decimal</th>
            <th align="left">Description</th>
            <th align="left">Reference</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">41</td>
            <td align="left">id-kp-configSigning</td>
            <td align="left">RFC 9809</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">42</td>
            <td align="left">id-kp-trustAnchorConfigSigning</td>
            <td align="left">RFC 9809</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">43</td>
            <td align="left">id-kp-updatePackageSigning</td>
            <td align="left">RFC 9809</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">44</td>
            <td align="left">id-kp-safetyCommunication</td>
            <td align="left">RFC 9809</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references anchor="sec-combined-references">
      <name>References</name>
      <references anchor="sec-normative-references">
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="X.680" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-X.680-202102-I/en">
          <front>
            <title>Information Technology - Abstract Syntax Notation One (ASN.1): Specification of basic notation</title>
            <author>
              <organization>ITU-T</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2021" month="February"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ITU-T Recommendation"  value="X.680"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="X.690" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-X.690-202102-I/en">
          <front>
            <title>Information Technology - ASN.1 encoding rules: Specification of Basic Encoding Rules (BER), Canonical Encoding Rules (CER) and Distinguished Encoding Rules (DER)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>ITU-T</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2021" month="February"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ITU-T Recommendation" value="X.690"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references anchor="sec-informative-references">
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9162.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9336.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9509.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="Directive-2016_797" target="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/dir/2016/797/2020-05-28">
          <front>
            <title>Directive (EU) 2016/797 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 11 May 2016 on the interoperability of the rail system within the European Union</title>
            <author>
              <organization>European Parliament, Council of the European Union</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2020" month="May"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="ERJU" target="https://rail-research.europa.eu/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/ERJU-SP-Cybersecurity-Specifications-V1.0.zip">
          <front>
            <title>Shared Cybersecurity Services Specification - SP-SEC-ServSpec - V1.0</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Europe's Rail Joint Undertaking</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2025" month="February"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="ERJU-web" target="https://rail-research.europa.eu/system_pillar/">
          <front>
            <title>Europe's Rail Joint Undertaking - System Pillar</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Europe's Rail Joint Undertaking</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="EU-CRA" target="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2024/2847/oj">
          <front>
            <title>Regulation (EU) 2024/2847 of the European Parliament and of
            the Council of 23 October 2024 on horizontal cybersecurity
            requirements for products with digital elements and amending
            Regulations (EU) No 168/2013 and (EU) 2019/1020 and Directive (EU)
            2020/1828 (Cyber Resilience Act)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>European Commission</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024" month="November"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="EU-STRATEGY" target="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/library/eus-cybersecurity-strategy-digital-decade-0">
          <front>
            <title>The EU's Cybersecurity Strategy for the Digital Decade</title>
            <author>
              <organization>European Commission</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2020" month="December"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

	
        <reference anchor="NIST.SP.800-160" target="">
          <front>
            <title>Engineering Trustworthy Secure Systems</title>
            <author initials="R" surname="Ross" fullname="Ron Ross" />
            <author initials="M" surname="Winstead" fullname="Mark Winstead" />
	    <author initials="M" surname="McEvilley" fullname="Michael McEvilley" />
	  <date year="2022" month="November"/>
          </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="NIST SP" value="800-160v1r1"/>
	  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.6028/NIST.SP.800-160v1r1"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="ISO.IEC.IEEE_12207" target="https://www.iso.org/standard/63712.html">
          <front>
            <title>Systems and software engineering - Software life cycle processes</title>
            <author>
              <organization>ISO/IEC/IEEE</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2017" month="November"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC/IEEE" value="12207:2017"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="NIS2" target="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/policies/nis2-directive">
          <front>
            <title>Directive (EU) 2022/2555 of the European Parliament and of the Council</title>
            <author>
              <organization>European Commission</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024" month="December"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="IEC.62443-4-2" target="https://webstore.iec.ch/publication/34421">
          <front>
            <title>Security for industrial automation and control systems - Part 4-2: Technical security requirements for IACS components</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IEC</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2019" month="February"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="IEC" value="62443-4-2:2019"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="IEC.62443-3-3" target="https://webstore.iec.ch/publication/7033">
          <front>
            <title>Industrial communication networks - Network and system security - Part 3-3: System security requirements and security levels</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IEC</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2013" month="August"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="IEC" value="62443-3-3:2013"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="CE-marking" target="https://single-market-economy.ec.europa.eu/single-market/ce-marking_en">
          <front>
            <title>CE marking</title>
            <author>
              <organization>European Commission</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="SMI-PKIX-PURPOSE" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/smi-numbers">
          <front>
            <title>SMI Security for PKIX Extended Key Purpose</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IANA</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="SMI-PKIX-MOD" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/smi-numbers">
          <front>
            <title>SMI Security for PKIX Module Identifier</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IANA</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>

<section anchor="asn1">
      <name>ASN.1 Module</name>
      <t>The following module adheres to ASN.1 specifications <xref target="X.680"/> and
<xref target="X.690"/>.</t>
      <sourcecode type="asn.1"><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS>

Automation-EKU
  { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1)
    security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) id-mod(0)
    id-mod-config-update-sc-eku (117) }

DEFINITIONS IMPLICIT TAGS ::=
BEGIN

-- OID Arc

id-kp OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::=
  { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1)
    security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) kp(3) }

-- Extended Key Usage Values

id-kp-configSigning            OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 41 }
id-kp-trustAnchorConfigSigning OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 42 }
id-kp-updatePackageSigning     OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 43 }
id-kp-safetyCommunication      OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 44 }

END

<CODE ENDS>
]]></sourcecode>
    </section>
    <section anchor="UseCases">
      <name>Use Cases</name>
      <t>These use cases are only for informational purposes.</t>
      <t>Automation hardware and software products strive to become more safe and secure by fulfilling mandatory, generic system requirements related to cybersecurity, e.g., driven by federal offices like the European Union Cyber Resilience Act <xref target="EU-CRA"></xref> governed by the European Commission and the High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy.
        Automation products connected to the Internet and sold in the EU after
  2027 must bear the so-called "CE marking" <xref target="CE-marking"></xref> to indicate that they
  comply with the EU-CRA.
  Such regulation was announced in the 2020 EU Cybersecurity Strategy <xref target="EU-STRATEGY"></xref> and complements other legislation in this area, like the directive on measures for
  a high common level of cybersecurity for network and information
  systems (NIS) across the European Union 
      <xref target="NIS2"></xref>.</t>
<t>The 2020 EU Cybersecurity Strategy <xref target="EU-STRATEGY"></xref> suggests implementing and extending international standards such as <xref target="IEC.62443-4-2"></xref> and <xref target="IEC.62443-3-3"></xref>. Automation hardware and software products of diverse vendors that are connected on automation networks and the Internet can be used to build common automation solutions. Standardized attributes would allow transparency of security properties and interoperability for vendors in the context of software and firmware updates, general-purpose configuration, trust anchor configuration, and safety-critical communication.</t>

<t>A concrete example for automation is a rail automation system. The Europe's Rail web page <xref target="ERJU-web"></xref> states: </t> 
<blockquote>The System Pillar brings rail sector representatives under a single coordination body.  To achieve this, the System Pillar will deliver a unified operational concept and a functional, safe and secure system architecture, with due consideration of cyber-security aspects, focused on the European railway network to which Directive 2016/797 applies (i.e. the heavy rail network) as well as associated specifications and/or standards.</blockquote>
<t>See <xref target="Directive-2016_797"/>. For details about the System Pillar, see <xref target="ERJU"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="acknow" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>We would like to thank the authors of <xref target="RFC9336"/> and <xref target="RFC9509"/> for  their excellent template.</t>
      <t>We also thank all reviewers of this document for their valuable feedback.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="contributors" numbered="false">
      <name>Contributors</name>
      <contact initials="S." surname="Fazekas-Zisch" fullname="Szofia Fazekas-Zisch">
        <organization abbrev="Siemens">Siemens AG</organization>
        <address>
          <postal>
            <street>Breslauer Str. 5</street>
            <city>Fuerth</city>
            <code>90766</code>
            <country>Germany</country>
          </postal>
          <email>szofia.fazekas-zisch@siemens.com</email>
          <uri>https://www.siemens.com</uri>
        </address>
      </contact>
      <contact initials="B." surname="Fouques" fullname="Baptiste Fouques">
        <organization>Alstom</organization>
        <address>
          <email>baptiste.fouques@alstomgroup.com</email>
        </address>
      </contact>
      <contact initials="D. G." surname="Orta" fullname="Daniel Gutierrez Orta">
        <organization>CAF Signalling</organization>
        <address>
          <email>daniel.gutierrez@cafsignalling.com</email>
        </address>
      </contact>
      <contact initials="M." surname="Weller" fullname="Martin Weller">
        <organization>Hitachi Rail</organization>
        <address>
          <email>martin.weller@urbanandmainlines.com</email>
        </address>
      </contact>
      <contact initials="N." surname="Poyet" fullname="Nicolas Poyet">
        <organization>SNCF</organization>
        <address>
          <email>nicolas.poyet@sncf.fr</email>
        </address>
      </contact>
    </section>
  </back>

</rfc>
