<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" docName="draft-ietf-pce-binding-label-sid-16" number="9604" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="true" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="4" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Binding Label/SID">Carrying Binding Label/SID in PCE-Based Networks</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9604"/>
    <author fullname="Siva Sivabalan" initials="S." surname="Sivabalan">
      <organization>Ciena Corporation</organization>
      <address>
        <email>msiva282@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Clarence Filsfils" initials="C." surname="Filsfils">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <extaddr>Pegasus Parc</extaddr>
          <street>De Kleetlaan 6a</street>
	  <city>Brabant</city>
          <code>1831</code>
          <country>Belgium</country>
        </postal>
        <email>cfilsfil@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Jeff Tantsura" initials="J." surname="Tantsura">
      <organization>Nvidia</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jefftant.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Stefano Previdi" initials="S." surname="Previdi">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <email>stefano@previdi.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Cheng Li" initials="C." role="editor">
    <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code>100095</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>c.l@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="August" year="2024"/>
    <area>rtg</area>
    <workgroup>pce</workgroup>

<keyword>PCEP</keyword>
<keyword>BSID</keyword>
<keyword>Binding</keyword>
<keyword>Binding Label</keyword>

    <abstract>

      <t>In order to provide greater scalability, network confidentiality, and
      service independence, Segment Routing (SR) utilizes a Binding Segment Identifier (BSID),
      as described in RFC 8402. It is possible to associate a BSID to an
      RSVP-TE-signaled Traffic Engineering (TE) Label Switched Path (LSP) or
      an SR TE path. The BSID can be used by an upstream node for steering
      traffic into the appropriate TE path to enforce SR policies. This
      document specifies the concept of binding value, which can be either an
      MPLS label or a Segment Identifier (SID). It further specifies an extension to Path Computation
      Element Communication Protocol (PCEP) for reporting the binding value by
      a Path Computation Client (PCC) to the Path Computation Element (PCE) to
      support PCE-based TE policies.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>A Path Computation Element (PCE) can compute Traffic Engineering (TE)
      paths through a network where those paths are subject to
      various constraints. Currently, TE paths are set up using either the
      RSVP-TE signaling protocol or Segment Routing (SR). We refer to such
      paths as "RSVP-TE paths" and "SR-TE paths", respectively, in this
      document.</t>
      <t>As per <xref target="RFC8402" format="default"/>, SR allows a
      head-end node to steer a packet flow along a given path via an SR
      Policy.  As per <xref target="RFC9256" format="default"/>, an SR Policy
      is a framework that enables the instantiation of an ordered list of
      segments on a node for implementing a source routing policy with a
      specific intent for traffic steering from that node.</t>
      <t>As described in <xref target="RFC8402" format="default"/>, a Binding
      SID (BSID) is bound to an SR Policy, instantiation of
      which may involve a list of Segment Identifiers (SIDs).  Any packets
      received with an active segment equal to a BSID are steered onto the
      bound SR Policy. A BSID may be either a local (SR Local Block (SRLB)) or
      a global (SR Global Block (SRGB)) SID. As per <xref target="RFC9256"
      sectionFormat="of" section="6.4"/>, a BSID can also be associated with
      any type of interface or tunnel to enable the use of a non-SR interface
      or tunnel as a segment in a SID list. In this document, the term
      "binding label/SID" is used to generalize the allocation of a binding
      value for both SR and non-SR paths.</t>
      <t><xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/> describes the PCEP for communication between
      a Path Computation Client (PCC) and a PCE or between a pair of PCEs as
      per <xref target="RFC4655" format="default"/>. <xref target="RFC8231" format="default"/> specifies
      extensions to PCEP that allow a PCC to delegate its Label Switched Paths
      (LSPs) to a stateful PCE. A stateful PCE can then update the state of
      LSPs delegated to it. <xref target="RFC8281" format="default"/> specifies a mechanism
      allowing a PCE to dynamically instantiate an LSP on a PCC by sending the
      path and characteristics. This document specifies an extension to PCEP
      to manage the binding of label/SID that can be applied to SR, RSVP-TE,
      and other path setup types.</t>
      <t><xref target="RFC8664" format="default"/> provides a mechanism for a PCE (acting as a
      network controller) to instantiate SR-TE paths (candidate paths) for an
      SR Policy onto a head-end node (acting as a PCC) using PCEP. For more
      information on the SR Policy Architecture, see <xref target="RFC9256" format="default"/>.</t>
      <section anchor="Motivation" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Motivation and Example</name>
        <t>A binding label/SID has local significance to the ingress node of
        the corresponding TE path. When a stateful PCE is deployed for setting
        up TE paths, a binding label/SID reported from the PCC to the stateful
        PCE is useful for enforcing an end-to-end TE/SR policy. A
        sample Data Center (DC) and IP/MPLS WAN use case is illustrated in
        <xref target="figure1" format="default"/> with a multi-domain PCE. In the IP/MPLS WAN,
        an SR-TE LSP is set up using the PCE. The list of SIDs of the SR-TE
        LSP is {A, B, C, D}. The gateway Node-1 (which is the PCC) allocates a
        binding SID X and reports it to the PCE. In the MPLS DC network, an
        end-to-end SR-TE LSP is established. In order for the access node to
        steer the traffic towards Node-1 and over the SR-TE path in WAN, the
        PCE passes the SID stack {Y, X} where Y is the node SID of the gateway
        Node-1 to the access node and X is the BSID. In the absence of the
        BSID X, the PCE would need to pass the SID stack {Y, A, B, C, D} to
        the access node. This example also illustrates the additional benefit
        of using the binding label/SID to reduce the number of SIDs imposed by
        the access nodes with a limited forwarding capacity.</t>
        <figure anchor="figure1">
          <name>A Sample Use Case of Binding SID</name>
          <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
           SID stack
           {Y, X}              +--------------+
                               | Multi-domain |
    _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _|     PCE      |
   |                           +--------------+
   |                              ^
   |                              | Binding
   |           .-----.            | SID (X)     .-----.
   |          (       )           |            (       )
   V       .--(         )--.      |        .--(         )--.
+------+  (                 )  +-------+  (                 )  +-------+
|Access|_(  MPLS DC Network  )_|Gateway|_(    IP/MPLS WAN    )_|Gateway|
| Node | (  ==============>  ) |Node-1 | ( ================> ) |Node-2 |
+------+  (    SR-TE path   )  +-------+  (    SR-TE path   )  +-------+
           '--(         )--'    Node       '--(         )--'
               (       )        SID of         (       )
                '-----'         Node-1          '-----'
                                is Y            SIDs for SR-TE LSP:
                                                {A, B, C, D}
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>Using the extension defined in this document, a PCC could report to
        the stateful PCE the binding label/SID it allocated via a Path
        Computation LSP State Report (PCRpt) message. It is also possible for
        a stateful PCE to request a PCC to allocate a specific binding
        label/SID by sending a Path Computation LSP Update Request (PCUpd)
        message. If the PCC can successfully allocate the specified binding
        value, it reports the binding value to the PCE. Otherwise, the PCC
        sends an error message to the PCE indicating the cause of the failure.
        A local policy or configuration at the PCC <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> dictate if the
        binding label/SID needs to be assigned.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="Summary" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Summary of the Extension</name>
        <t>To implement the needed changes to PCEP, this document
        introduces a new <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> TLV that allows a PCC to report the
        binding label/SID associated with a TE LSP or a PCE to request a PCC
        to allocate any or a specific binding label/SID value. This TLV is
        intended for TE LSPs established using RSVP-TE, SR-TE, or any other
        future method. In the case of SR-TE LSPs, the TLV can carry a binding
        label (for SR-TE paths with the MPLS data plane) or a binding IPv6 SID
        (e.g., IPv6 address for SR-TE paths with the IPv6 data plane). Throughout
        this document, the term "binding value" means either an MPLS label or
        a SID.</t>
        <t>As another way to use the extension specified in this document, to
        support the PCE-based central controller <xref target="RFC8283" format="default"/>
        operation where the PCE would take responsibility for managing some
        part of the MPLS label space for each of the routers that it controls,
        the PCE could directly make the binding label/SID allocation and
        inform the PCC. See <xref target="PCECC" format="default"/> for details.</t>
        <t>In addition to specifying a new TLV, this document specifies how
        and when a PCC and PCE can use this TLV, how they can allocate a
        binding label/SID, and the associated error handling.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be
    interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref
    target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as
    shown here.
        </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <t>The following terminologies are used in this document: </t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>BSID:</dt>
        <dd>Binding SID</dd>
        <dt>binding label/SID:</dt>
        <dd>a generic term used for the binding segment for both SR and non-SR
        paths</dd>
        <dt>binding value:</dt>
        <dd>a generic term used for the binding segment as it can be encoded
        in various formats (as per the Binding Type (BT))</dd>
        <dt>LSP:</dt>
        <dd>Label Switched Path</dd>
        <dt>PCC:</dt>
        <dd>Path Computation Client</dd>
        <dt>PCEP:</dt>
        <dd>Path Computation Element Communication Protocol</dd>
        <dt>RSVP-TE:</dt>
        <dd>Resource Reservation Protocol - Traffic Engineering </dd>
        <dt>SID:</dt>
        <dd>Segment Identifier</dd>
        <dt>SR:</dt>
        <dd>Segment Routing</dd>
        </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="TE-PATH-BINDING-TLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Path Binding TLV</name>
      <t>The new optional TLV called "TE-PATH-BINDING TLV" (the format is
      shown in <xref target="BINDING-LABEL-TLV-FORMAT" format="default"/>) is defined to carry
      the binding label/SID for a TE path. This TLV is associated with the LSP
      object specified in <xref target="RFC8231" format="default"/>. This TLV can also be
      carried in the PCEP-ERROR object <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/> in case of
      error. Multiple instances of TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be present in the
      LSP and PCEP-ERROR object. The type of this TLV is 55. The length is variable.</t>

      <figure anchor="BINDING-LABEL-TLV-FORMAT">
        <name>TE-PATH-BINDING TLV</name>
        <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|           Type = 55           |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      BT       |    Flags      |            Reserved           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
~            Binding Value (variable length)                    ~
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>The TE-PATH-BINDING TLV is a generic TLV such that it is able to carry
      binding label/SID (i.e., MPLS label or SRv6 SID). It is formatted
      according to the rules specified in <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/>. The value
      portion of the TLV comprises:</t>
<ul>
      <li><t>Binding Type (BT): A one-octet field that identifies the type of
      binding included in the TLV. This document specifies the following BT
      values:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>BT = 0: The binding value is a 20-bit MPLS label value. The TLV is
        padded to 4-bytes alignment. The Length <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to
        7 (the padding is not included in the length, as per <xref
        target="RFC5440" sectionFormat="comma" section="7.1"/>), and the first
        20 bits are used to encode the MPLS label value.</li>
        <li>BT = 1: The binding value is a 32-bit MPLS Label Stack Entry as
        per <xref target="RFC3032" format="default"/> with Label, Traffic
        Class (TC) <xref target="RFC5462" format="default"/>, S, and TTL
        values encoded. Note that the receiver <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> choose to
        override TC, S, and TTL values according to its local policy. The
        Length <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to 8.</li>
        <li>BT = 2: The binding value is an SRv6 SID with the format of a
        16-octet IPv6 address, representing the binding SID for SRv6. The
        Length <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to 20.</li>
        <li>BT = 3: The binding value is a 24-octet field, defined in <xref
        target="Behavior-Structure" format="default"/>, that contains the SRv6
        SID as well as its Behavior and Structure. The Length
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to 28.</li>
      </ul>
      <t><xref target="IANA-TLV" format="default"/> defines the IANA registry used to maintain
      these binding types as well as any future ones. Note that multiple
      TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs with the same or different binding types <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be present
      for the same LSP. A PCEP speaker could allocate multiple TE-PATH-BINDING
      TLVs (of the same BT) and use different binding values in different
      domains or use cases based on a local policy.</t></li>
      <li><t>Flags: 1 octet of flags. The following flag is defined in the new
      "TE-PATH-BINDING TLV Flag field" registry as described in <xref target="IANA-TLV" format="default"/>:</t>
      <figure anchor="BINDING-LABEL-FLAGS">
        <name>Flags</name>
        <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|R|             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>Where: </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>R (Removal - 1 bit): When set, the requesting PCEP peer requires
        the removal of the binding value for the LSP. When unset, the PCEP
        peer indicates that the binding value is added or retained for the
        LSP. This flag is used in the PCRpt and PCUpd messages. It is ignored
        in other PCEP messages.</li>
        <li>The unassigned flags <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to 0 while sending
        and ignored on receipt.</li>
      </ul></li>

      <li><t>Reserved: <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to 0 while sending and ignored on receipt.</t></li>
      <li><t>Binding Value: A variable-length field, padded with trailing zeros to
      a 4-octet boundary. When the BT is 0, the 20 bits represent the MPLS
      label. When the BT is 1, the 32 bits represent the MPLS label stack
      entry as per <xref target="RFC3032" format="default"/>. When the BT is 2, the 128 bits
      represent the SRv6 SID. When the BT is 3, the binding value also
      contains the SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure, defined in <xref target="Behavior-Structure" format="default"/>. In this document, the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV
      is considered to be empty if no binding value is present. Note that the
      length of the TLV would be 4 in such a case.</t></li>
    </ul>
      <section anchor="Behavior-Structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure</name>
        <t>This section specifies the format of the binding value in the
        TE-PATH-BINDING TLV when the BT is set to 3 for the SRv6 Binding SIDs
        <xref target="RFC8986" format="default"/>. The format is shown in <xref target="SID-BEHAVIOR-AND-STRUCTURE" format="default"/>.</t>
        <figure anchor="SID-BEHAVIOR-AND-STRUCTURE">
          <name>SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure</name>
          <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                 SRv6 Binding SID (16 octets)                  |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|         Reserved              |      Endpoint Behavior        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    LB Length  |    LN Length  | Fun. Length   |  Arg. Length  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>The Binding Value consists of:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>SRv6 Binding SID: 16 octets. The 128-bit IPv6 address,
          representing the binding SID for SRv6.</li>
          <li>Reserved: 2 octets. It <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to 0 on
          transmit and ignored on receipt.</li>
          <li>Endpoint Behavior: 2 octets. The Endpoint Behavior code point
          for this SRv6 SID as defined by the "SRv6 Endpoint
          Behaviors" registry <xref target="RFC8986"
          format="default"/>. When the field is set with the value 0, the
          Endpoint Behavior is considered unknown.</li>
          <li>
            <t><xref target="RFC8986" format="default"/> defines an SRv6 SID
            as consisting of LOC:FUNCT:ARG, where a locator (LOC) is encoded
            in the L most significant bits of the SID, followed by F bits of
            function (FUNCT) and A bits of arguments (ARG). A locator may be
            represented as B:N, where B is the SRv6 SID locator block (IPv6
            prefix allocated for SRv6 SIDs by the operator) and N is the
            identifier of the parent node instantiating the SID, called "locator
            node". The following fields are used to advertise the length of
            each individual part of the SRv6 SID:</t>

	    <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>LB Length: 1 octet. SRv6 SID Locator Block length in
              bits.</li>
              <li>LN Length: 1 octet. SRv6 SID Locator Node length in
              bits.</li>
              <li>Function Length: 1 octet. SRv6 SID Function length in
              bits.</li>
              <li>Arguments Length: 1 octet. SRv6 SID Arguments length in
              bits.</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>The total of the locator block, locator node, function, and
        arguments lengths <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be less than or equal to 128 bits. If this condition
        is not met, the corresponding TE-PATH-BINDING TLV is considered
        invalid. Also, if the Endpoint Behavior is found to be unknown or
        inconsistent, it is considered invalid. A PCErr message with
        Error-Type = 10 ("Reception of an invalid object") and Error-value =
        37 ("Invalid SRv6 SID Structure") <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be sent in such cases.</t>
        <t>The SRv6 SID Structure could be used by the PCE for ease of
        operations and monitoring. For example, this information could be used
        for validation of SRv6 SIDs being instantiated in the network and
        checked for conformance to the SRv6 SID allocation scheme chosen by
        the operator as described in <xref target="RFC8986" sectionFormat="of" section="3.2"/>.
        In the future, PCE could also be used for verification and for
        automatically securing the SRv6 domain by provisioning filtering
        rules at SR domain boundaries as described in <xref target="RFC8754" sectionFormat="of" section="5"/>. The details of these potential applications are
        outside the scope of this document.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Operation" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Operation</name>
      <t>The binding value is usually allocated by the PCC and reported to a
      PCE via a PCRpt message (see <xref target="PCECC" format="default"/> where PCE performs the
      allocation). If a PCE does not recognize the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV, it
      would ignore the TLV in accordance with <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/>. If a
      PCE recognizes the TLV but does not support the TLV, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a
      PCErr with Error-Type = 2 ("Capability not supported").</t>
      <t>Multiple TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs are allowed to be present in the same
      LSP object. This signifies the presence of multiple binding SIDs for the
      given LSP. In the case of multiple TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs, the existing
      instances of TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be included in the LSP object. In
      case of an error condition, the whole message is rejected, and the
      resulting PCErr message <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> include the offending TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in
      the PCEP-ERROR object.</t>
      <t>If a PCE recognizes an invalid binding value (e.g., label value from
      the reserved MPLS label space), it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a PCErr message with
      Error-Type = 10 ("Reception of an invalid object") and Error-value = 2
      ("Bad label value") as specified in <xref target="RFC8664" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>For SRv6 BSIDs, it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> to always explicitly specify the
      SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure in the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV by
      setting BT to 3. This can enable the sender to have
      control of the SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure. A sender <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>
      choose to set the BT to 2, in which case the receiving implementation
      chooses how to interpret the SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure
      according to local policy.</t>
      <t>If a PCC wishes to withdraw a previously reported binding value, it
      <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a PCRpt message with the specific TE-PATH-BINDING TLV with R
      flag set to 1. If a PCC wishes to modify a previously reported binding,
      it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> withdraw the former binding value (with R flag set in the former
      TE-PATH-BINDING TLV) and include a new TE-PATH-BINDING TLV containing
      the new binding value. Note that other instances of TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs
      that are unchanged <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> also be included. If the unchanged instances are
      not included, they will remain associated with the LSP.</t>
      <t>If a PCE requires a PCC to allocate one (or several) specific binding
      value(s), it may do so by sending a PCUpd or PCInitiate message
      containing one or more TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs. If the values can be successfully
      allocated, the PCC reports the binding values to the PCE. If the PCC
      considers the binding value specified by the PCE invalid, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a
      PCErr message with Error-Type = 32 ("Binding label/SID failure") and
      Error-value = 1 ("Invalid SID"). If the binding value is valid but
      the PCC is unable to allocate the binding value, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a PCErr
      message with Error-Type = 32 ("Binding label/SID failure") and Error-value = 2 ("Unable to allocate the specified binding value"). Note
      that, in case of an error, the PCC rejects the PCUpd or PCInitiate
      message in its entirety and can include the offending TE-PATH-BINDING
      TLV in the PCEP-ERROR object.</t>
      <t>If a PCE wishes to request the withdrawal of a previously reported
      binding value, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a PCUpd message with the specific
      TE-PATH-BINDING TLV with R flag set to 1. If a PCE wishes to modify a
      previously requested binding value, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> request the withdrawal of
      the former binding value (with R flag set in the former TE-PATH-BINDING
      TLV) and include a new TE-PATH-BINDING TLV containing the new binding
      value. If a PCC receives a PCUpd message with TE-PATH-BINDING TLV where
      the R flag is set to 1, but either the binding value is missing (empty
      TE-PATH-BINDING TLV) or the binding value is incorrect, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a
      PCErr message with Error-Type = 32 ("Binding label/SID failure") and
      Error-value = 4 ("Unable to remove the binding value").</t>

      <t>In some cases, a stateful PCE may want to request that the PCC
      allocate a binding value of the PCC's own choosing. It instructs the PCC
      by sending a PCUpd message containing an empty TE-PATH-BINDING TLV,
      i.e., no binding value is specified (bringing the Length field of the
      TLV to 4). A PCE can also request that a PCC allocate a binding value at
      the time of initiation by sending a PCInitiate message with an empty
      TE-PATH-BINDING TLV.  Only one such instance of empty TE-PATH-BINDING
      TLV, per BT, <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be included in the LSP object; others
      should be ignored on receipt.  If the PCC is unable to allocate a new
      binding value as per the specified BT, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a
      PCErr message with Error-Type = 32 ("Binding label/SID failure") and
      Error-value = 3 ("Unable to allocate a new binding label/SID").</t>
      <t>As previously noted, if a message contains an invalid TE-PATH-BINDING
      TLV that leads to an error condition, the whole message is rejected
      including any other valid instances of TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs, if any. The
      resulting error message <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> include the offending TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in
      the PCEP-ERROR object.</t>
      <t>If a PCC receives a TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in any message other than
      PCUpd or PCInitiate, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> close the corresponding PCEP session with
      the reason "Reception of a malformed PCEP message" (according to <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/>). Similarly, if a PCE receives a TE-PATH-BINDING TLV
      in any message other than a PCRpt or if the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV is
      associated with any object other than an LSP or PCEP-ERROR object, the
      PCE <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> close the corresponding PCEP session with the reason "Reception
      of a malformed PCEP message" (according to <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/>).</t>
      <t>If a TE-PATH-BINDING TLV is absent in the PCRpt message and no
      binding values were previously reported, the PCE <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> assume that the
      corresponding LSP does not have any binding. Similarly, if
      TE-PATH-BINDING TLV is absent in the PCUpd message and no binding values
      were previously reported, the PCC's local policy dictates how the binding
      allocations are made for a given LSP.</t>
      <t>Note that some binding types have similar information but different
      binding value formats. For example, BT=(2 or 3) is used for the SRv6 SID,
      and BT=(0 or 1) is used for the MPLS Label. In case a PCEP speaker
      receives multiple TE-PATH-BINDING TLVs with the same SRv6 SID or MPLS
      Label but different BT values, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a PCErr message with
      Error-Type = 32 ("Binding label/SID failure") and Error-value = 5
      ("Inconsistent binding types").</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="SR-ERO" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Binding SID in SR-ERO</name>
      <t>In PCEP messages, LSP route information is carried in the Explicit
      Route Object (ERO), which consists of a sequence of subobjects. <xref
      target="RFC8664" format="default"/> defines the "SR-ERO subobject"
      capable of carrying a SID as well as the identity of the Node or
      Adjacency Identifier (NAI) represented by the SID. The NAI Type (NT)
      field indicates the type and format of the NAI contained in the
      SR-ERO. In case of binding SID, the NAI <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be
      included and NT <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero. <xref
      target="RFC8664" sectionFormat="of" section="5.2.1"/> specifies bit
      settings and error handling in the case when NT=0.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="SRv6-ERO" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Binding SID in SRv6-ERO</name>
      <t><xref target="RFC9603" format="default"/> defines the "SRv6-ERO
      subobject" for an SRv6 SID. Similarly to SR-ERO (<xref target="SR-ERO"
      format="default"/>), the NAI <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be included and
      the NT <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero. <xref target="RFC8664"
      sectionFormat="of" section="5.2.1"/> specifies bit settings and error
      handling in the case when NT=0.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="PCECC" toc="default" numbered="true">
      <name>PCE Allocation of Binding Label/SID</name>
      <t><xref target="Operation" format="default"/> already includes the scenario where a PCE
      requires a PCC to allocate a specified binding value by sending a PCUpd
      or PCInitiate message containing a TE-PATH-BINDING TLV. This section
      specifies an <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> feature for the PCE to allocate the binding
      label/SID of its own accord in the case where the PCE also controls the
      label space of the PCC and can make the label allocation on its own as
      described in <xref target="RFC8283" format="default"/>. Note that the act of requesting a
      specific binding value (<xref target="Operation" format="default"/>) is different from
      the act of allocating a binding label/SID as described in this
      section.</t>
      <t><xref target="RFC8283" format="default"/> introduces the architecture for PCE as a
      central controller as an extension of the architecture described in
      <xref target="RFC4655" format="default"/> and assumes the continued use of PCEP as the
      protocol used between PCE and PCC. <xref target="RFC9050" format="default"/> specifies
      the procedures and PCEP extensions for using the PCE as the central
      controller. It assumes that the exclusive label range to be used by a
      PCE is known and set on both PCEP peers. A future extension could add
      the capability to advertise this range via a possible PCEP extension as
      well (see <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-controlled-id-space" format="default"/>).</t>
      <t>When PCE as a Central Controller (PCECC) operations are supported as per <xref target="RFC9050" format="default"/>,
      the binding label/SID <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> also be allocated by the PCE itself. Both
      peers need to exchange the PCECC capability as described in <xref target="RFC9050" format="default"/> before the PCE can allocate the binding label/SID on
      its own.</t>
      <t>A new P flag in the LSP object <xref target="RFC8231" format="default"/> is introduced
      to indicate that the allocation needs to be made by the PCE. Note that
      the P flag could be used for other types of allocations (such as path
      segments <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-sr-path-segment" format="default"/>) in the future. </t>

        <t indent="3">P (PCE-allocation): If the bit is set to 1, it indicates
        that the PCC requests that the PCE make allocations for this LSP. The
        TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in the LSP object identifies that the allocation
        is for a binding label/SID. A PCC <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> set this bit to
        1 and include a TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in the LSP object if it wishes to
        request an allocation for a binding label/SID by the PCE in the PCEP
        message. A PCE <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> also set this bit to 1 and include
        a TE-PATH-BINDING TLV to indicate that the binding label/SID is
        allocated by PCE and encoded in the PCEP message towards the
        PCC. Further, if the binding label/SID is allocated by the PCC, the
        PCE <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> set this bit to 0 and follow the procedure
        described in <xref target="Operation" format="default"/>.</t>

      <t>Note that: </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">

        <li>A PCE could allocate the binding label/SID of its own accord for
          a PCE-initiated or PCE-delegated LSP and inform the PCC in the
          PCInitiate message or PCUpd message by setting P=1 and including
          TE-PATH-BINDING TLV in the LSP object.</li>
        <li>To let the PCC allocate the binding label/SID, a PCE <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> set P=0
          and include an empty TE-PATH-BINDING TLV (i.e., no binding value is
          specified) in the LSP object in the PCInitiate/PCUpd message.</li>
        <li>To request that the PCE allocate the binding label/SID, a PCC
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> set P=1, D=1, and include an empty TE-PATH-BINDING
        TLV in the PCRpt message.  The PCE will attempt to allocate it and
        respond to the PCC with a PCUpd message that includes the allocated
        binding label/SID in the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV and P=1 and D=1 in the
        LSP object. If the PCE is unable to allocate the binding label/SID, it
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a PCErr message with Error-Type = 32
        ("Binding label/SID failure") and Error-value = 3 ("Unable to allocate
        a new binding label/SID").</li>
        <li>
          <t>If one or both speakers (PCE and PCC) have not indicated support
          and willingness to use the PCEP extensions for the PCECC as per
          <xref target="RFC9050" format="default"/> and a PCEP peer receives P=1 in the LSP
          object, they <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>: </t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>send a PCErr message with Error-Type = 19 ("Invalid Operation")
              and Error-value = 16 ("Attempted PCECC operations when PCECC
              capability was not advertised") and</li>
            <li>terminate the PCEP session.</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>A legacy PCEP speaker that does not recognize the P flag in the
          LSP object would ignore it in accordance with <xref target="RFC8231" format="default"/>.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>It is assumed that the label range to be used by a PCE is known and
      set on both PCEP peers. The exact mechanism is out of the scope of <xref target="RFC9050" format="default"/> and this document. Note that the specific BSID could
      be from the PCE-controlled or the PCC-controlled label space. The PCE
      can directly allocate the label from the PCE-controlled label space
      using P=1 as described above, whereas the PCE can request the allocation
      of a specific BSID from the PCC-controlled label space with P=0 as
      described in <xref target="Operation" format="default"/>.</t>

      <t>Note that the P flag in the LSP object <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be set to 1
      without the presence of TE-PATH-BINDING TLV or any other future TLV
      defined for PCE allocation. On receipt of such an LSP object, the P flag
      is ignored. The presence of TE-PATH-BINDING TLV with P=1 indicates the
      allocation is for the binding label/SID. In the future, some other TLV
      (such as one defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-sr-path-segment" format="default"/>)
      could also be used alongside P=1 to indicate allocation of a different
      attribute. A future document should not attempt to assign semantics to
      P=1 without limiting the scope to one that both PCEP peers can agree on.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The security considerations described in <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/>,
      <xref target="RFC8231" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC8281" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC8664" format="default"/>, and <xref target="RFC9050" format="default"/> are applicable to this
      specification. No additional security measure is required.</t>
      <t>As described in <xref target="RFC8402" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC8664" format="default"/>, SR intrinsically involves an entity (whether
      head-end or a central network controller) controlling and instantiating
      paths in the network without the involvement of (other) nodes along
      those paths. Binding SIDs are in effect shorthand aliases for longer
      path representations, and the alias expansion is in principle known only
      by the node that acts on it. In this document, the expansion of the
      alias is shared between PCC and PCE, and rogue actions by either PCC or
      PCE could result in shifting or misdirecting traffic in ways that are
      hard for other nodes to detect. In particular, when a PCE propagates
      paths of the form {A, B, BSID} to other entities, the BSID values are
      opaque, and a rogue PCE can substitute a BSID from a different LSP in
      such paths to move traffic without the recipient of the path knowing the
      ultimate destination.</t>
      <t>The case of BT=3 provides additional opportunities for malfeasance,
      as it purports to convey information about internal SRv6 SID Structure.
      There is no mechanism defined to validate this internal structure
      information, and mischaracterizing the division of bits into locator
      block, locator node, function, and argument can result in different
      interpretation of the bits by PCC and PCE. Most notably, shifting bits
      into or out of the "argument" is a direct vector for affecting
      processing, but other attacks are also possible.</t>

      <t>Thus, as per <xref target="RFC8231" format="default"/>, it is
      <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that these PCEP extensions only be activated
      on authenticated and encrypted sessions across PCEs and PCCs belonging
      to the same administrative authority, using Transport Layer Security
      (TLS) <xref target="RFC8253" format="default"/>, as per the
      recommendations and best current practices in RFC 9325 <xref target="BCP195"/>
      (unless explicitly set aside in
      <xref target="RFC8253" format="default"/>).</t>
    </section>
    <section toc="default" numbered="true">
      <name>Manageability Considerations</name>
      <t>All manageability requirements and considerations listed in <xref format="default" target="RFC5440"/>, <xref format="default" target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref target="RFC8664" format="default"/> apply to PCEP protocol extensions defined in this
      document. In addition, requirements and considerations listed in this
      section apply.</t>
      <section toc="default" numbered="true">
        <name>Control of Function and Policy</name>
        <t>A PCC implementation <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> allow the operator to configure the
        policy the PCC needs to apply when allocating the binding
        label/SID.</t>
        <t>If BT is set to 2, the operator needs to have local policy set to
        decide the SID structure and the SRv6 Endpoint Behavior of the
        BSID.</t>
      </section>
      <section toc="default" numbered="true">
        <name>Information and Data Models</name>
        <t>The PCEP YANG module <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang" format="default"/> will
        be extended to include policy configuration for binding label/SID
        allocation.</t>
      </section>
      <section toc="default" numbered="true">
        <name>Liveness Detection and Monitoring</name>
        <t>The mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new
        liveness detection and monitoring requirements in addition to those
        already listed in <xref format="default" target="RFC5440"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section toc="default" numbered="true">
        <name>Verify Correct Operations</name>
        <t>The mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new
        operation verification requirements in addition to those already
        listed in <xref format="default" target="RFC5440"/>,
        <xref format="default" target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref target="RFC8664" format="default"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section toc="default" numbered="true">
        <name>Requirements on Other Protocols</name>
        <t>The mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new
        requirements on other protocols.</t>
      </section>
      <section toc="default" numbered="true">
        <name>Impact on Network Operations</name>
        <t>The mechanisms defined in <xref format="default" target="RFC5440"/>, <xref format="default" target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref target="RFC8664" format="default"/> also apply to the
        PCEP extensions defined in this document.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>IANA has allocated code points for the protocol elements described in this document in the "Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) Numbers" registry group.</t>
      <section anchor="TLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>PCEP TLV Type Indicators</name>
        <t>This document defines a new PCEP TLV. IANA has allocated the following in the  "PCEP TLV Type Indicators" registry within the PCEP Numbers registry group:</t>
        <table anchor="TLV-Type" align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="center">Value</th>
              <th align="left">Description</th>
              <th align="left">Reference</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">55</td>
              <td align="left">TE-PATH-BINDING</td>
              <td align="left">RFC 9604</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>

        <section anchor="IANA-TLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>TE-PATH-BINDING TLV</name>
          <t>IANA has created the "TE-PATH-BINDING TLV BT Field" registry 
          to manage the values of the binding type field in the
          TE-PATH-BINDING TLV. Initial values are shown
          below. New values are assigned by Standards Action <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>.</t>
          <table anchor="BT" align="center">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="center">Value</th>
                <th align="left">Description</th>
                <th align="left">Reference</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="center">0</td>
                <td align="left">MPLS Label</td>
                <td align="left">RFC 9604</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center">1</td>
                <td align="left">MPLS Label Stack Entry</td>
                <td align="left">RFC 9604</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center">2</td>
                <td align="left">SRv6 SID</td>
                <td align="left">RFC 9604</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center">3</td>
                <td align="left">SRv6 SID with Behavior and Structure</td>
                <td align="left">RFC 9604</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center">4-255</td>
                <td align="left">Unassigned</td>
                <td align="left"></td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <t>IANA has created a new "TE-PATH-BINDING
          TLV Flag Field" registry to manage the Flag field in the TE-PATH-BINDING TLV.
          New values are to be assigned by Standards Action <xref
          target="RFC8126" format="default"/>. Each bit should be tracked with
          the following qualities:</t>
          <ul spacing="compact">
            <li>Bit number (count from 0 as the most significant bit)</li>
            <li>Description</li>
            <li>Reference</li>
          </ul>
          <table anchor="BF" align="center">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="center">Bit</th>
                <th align="left">Description</th>
                <th align="left">Reference</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="center">0</td>
                <td align="left">R (Removal)</td>
                <td align="left">RFC 9604</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="center">1-7</td>
                <td align="left">Unassigned</td>
                <td align="left"></td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="LSP" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>LSP Object</name>
        <t>IANA has allocated a 
        code point in the "LSP Object Flag Field" registry for the new P
        flag as follows:</t>
        <table anchor="LSP-Flag" align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="center">Bit</th>
              <th align="left">Description</th>
              <th align="left">Reference</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">0</td>
              <td align="left">PCE-allocation</td>
              <td align="left">RFC 9604</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>
      <section anchor="Error-Type" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>PCEP Error Type and Value</name>
        <t>This document defines a new Error-Type and associated Error-values
        for the PCErr message. IANA has allocated a new Error-Type
        and Error-values within the "PCEP-ERROR Object Error Types and Values"
        registry of the PCEP Numbers registry group, as follows:</t>
       <table anchor="Error">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Error-Type</th>
              <th>Meaning</th>
              <th>Error-value</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="6">32</td>
              <td rowspan="6">Binding label/SID failure</td>
              <td>0: Unassigned</td>
	    </tr>
              <tr><td>1: Invalid SID</td></tr>
              <tr><td>2: Unable to allocate the specified binding value</td></tr>
              <tr><td>3: Unable to allocate a new binding label/SID</td></tr>
              <tr><td>4: Unable to remove the binding value</td></tr>
              <tr><td>5: Inconsistent binding types</td></tr>

          </tbody>
        </table>

      </section>
    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>

    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang" to="PCEP-YANG"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-pce-controlled-id-space" to="PCE-ID-SPACE"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-pce-sr-path-segment" to="PCEP-SR"/>
    
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3032.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5440.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5462.xml"/>
<referencegroup anchor="BCP195" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/bcp195">
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8996.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9325.xml"/>
</referencegroup>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8231.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8253.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8281.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8402.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8664.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8986.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9050.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9603.xml"/>


      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4655.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8283.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8754.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9256.xml"/>

	<reference anchor="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-ietf-pce-pcep-yang-25">
	  <front>
	    <title>A YANG Data Model for Path Computation Element Communications Protocol (PCEP)</title>
	    <author initials="D." surname="Dhody" fullname="Dhruv Dhody" role="editor">
	      <organization>Huawei</organization>
	    </author>
	    <author initials="V." surname="Beeram" fullname="Vishnu Pavan Beeram">
	      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
	    </author>
	    <author initials="J." surname="Hardwick" fullname="Jonathan Hardwick">
	      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
	    </author>
	    <author initials="J." surname="Tantsura" fullname="Jeff Tantsura">
	      <organization>Nvidia</organization>
	    </author>
	    <date month="May" day="21" year="2024"/>
	  </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-pce-pcep-yang-25"/>
	</reference>

	<reference anchor="I-D.ietf-pce-controlled-id-space" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-ietf-pce-controlled-id-space-00">
	  <front>
	    <title>Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP) extension to advertise the PCE Controlled Identifier Space</title>
	    <author initials="C." surname="Li" fullname="Cheng Li">
	      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
	    </author>
	    <author initials="H." surname="Shi" fullname="Hang Shi" role="editor">
	      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
	    </author>
	    <author initials="A." surname="Wang" fullname="Aijun Wang">
	      <organization>China Telecom</organization>
	    </author>
	    <author initials="W." surname="Cheng" fullname="Weiqiang Cheng">
	      <organization>China Mobile</organization>
	    </author>
	    <author initials="C." surname="Zhou" fullname="Chao Zhou">
	      <organization>HPE</organization>
	    </author>
	    <date month="June" day="4" year="2024"/>
	  </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-pce-controlled-id-space-00"/>
	</reference>
	
        <xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pce-sr-path-segment.xml"/>

      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgement" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>We would like to thank <contact fullname="Milos Fabian"/>, <contact
      fullname="Mrinmoy Das"/>, <contact fullname="Andrew Stone"/>, <contact
      fullname="Tom Petch"/>, <contact fullname="Aijun Wang"/>, <contact
      fullname="Olivier Dugeon"/>, and <contact fullname="Adrian Farrel"/> for
      their valuable comments.</t>
      <t>Thanks to <contact fullname="Julien Meuric"/> for shepherding. Thanks
      to <contact fullname="John Scudder"/> for the AD review.</t>
      <t>Thanks to <contact fullname="Theresa Enghardt"/> for the GENART review.</t>
      <t>Thanks to <contact fullname="Martin Vigoureux"/>, <contact
      fullname="Benjamin Kaduk"/>, <contact fullname="ric Vyncke"/>, <contact
      fullname="Lars Eggert"/>, <contact fullname="Murray Kucherawy"/>, and
      <contact fullname="Erik Kline"/> for the IESG reviews.</t>
    </section>

    <section toc="default" numbered="false">
      <name>Contributors</name>

      <contact fullname="Jonathan Hardwick">
	<organization>Microsoft</organization>
	<address>
          <postal>
            <country>United Kingdom</country>
          </postal>
          <email>jonhardwick@microsoft.com</email>
	</address>
      </contact>

      <contact fullname="Dhruv Dhody">
	<organization>Huawei Technologies </organization>
	<address>
          <postal>
	    <street>Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield</street>
	    <city>Bangalore</city><region>Karnataka</region>
            <country>India</country>
	    <code>560066</code>
          </postal>
          <email>dhruv.ietf@gmail.com</email>
	</address>
      </contact>

      <contact fullname="Mahendra Singh Negi">
	<organization>RtBrick India</organization>
	<address>
          <postal>
	    <street>N-17L, Floor-1, 18th Cross Rd, HSR Layout Sector-3</street>
	    <city>Bangalore</city><region>Karnataka</region>
            <country>India</country>
	    <code>560102</code>
          </postal>
          <email>mahend.ietf@gmail.com</email>
	</address>
      </contact>

      <contact fullname="Mike Koldychev">
	<organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
	<address>
          <postal>
	    <street>2000 Innovation Drive</street>
	    <city>Kanata</city><region>Ontario</region><code>K2K 3E8</code>
            <country>Canada</country>
          </postal>
          <email>mkoldych@cisco.com</email>
	</address>
      </contact>

      <contact fullname="Zafar Ali">
	<organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
	<address>
          <email>zali@cisco.com</email>
	</address>
      </contact>

    </section>

  </back>

</rfc>
