<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
category="std" 
consensus="true" 
number="9534"
docName="draft-ietf-ippm-stamp-on-lag-06" 
ipr="trust200902" 
sortRefs="true" 
submissionType="IETF" 
tocInclude="true" 
obsoletes="" 
updates="" 
xml:lang="en" 
tocDepth="3" 
symRefs="true" 
version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="STAMP PM on LAG">Simple Two-Way Active Measurement Protocol
    Extensions for Performance Measurement on a Link Aggregation Group</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9534"/>
    <author fullname="Zhenqiang Li" initials="Z." surname="Li">
      <organization>China Mobile</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>No. 29 Finance Avenue</street>
          <cityarea>Xicheng District</cityarea>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code/>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>li_zhenqiang@hotmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Tianran Zhou" initials="T." surname="Zhou">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>zhoutianran@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Jun Guo" initials="J." surname="Guo">
      <organization>ZTE Corp.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>guo.jun2@zte.com.cn</email>
        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Greg Mirsky" initials="G." surname="Mirsky">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>gregimirsky@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Rakesh Gandhi" initials="R." surname="Gandhi">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>rgandhi@cisco.com</email>
        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="January" year="2024"/>

    <area>Transport Area</area>
    <workgroup>IPPM</workgroup>

<keyword>STAMP</keyword>
<keyword>Performance Measurement</keyword>
<keyword>LAG</keyword>
<keyword>Micro Session</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document extends Simple Two-way Active Measurement Protocol
      (STAMP) to implement performance measurement on every member link of a
      Link Aggregation Group (LAG). Knowing the measured metrics of each
      member link of a LAG enables operators to enforce a performance-based
      traffic steering policy across the member links.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>A Link Aggregation Group (LAG), as defined in <xref target="IEEE802.1AX" format="default"/>, provides mechanisms to combine multiple physical
      links into a single logical link. This logical link offers higher
      bandwidth and better resiliency because, if one of the physical member
      links fails, the aggregate logical link can continue to forward traffic
      over the remaining operational physical member links.</t>
      <t>Usually, when forwarding traffic over a LAG, a hash-based mechanism is
      used to load balance the traffic across the LAG member links. The link
      delay might vary between member links because of different transport
      paths, especially when a LAG is used in a wide area network. To provide
      low-latency service for time-sensitive traffic, we need to explicitly steer
      the traffic across the LAG member links based on the link delay, loss,
      and so on. That requires a solution to measure the performance metrics
      of each member link of a LAG. Hence, the measured performance metrics
      can work together with <xref target="RFC8668" format="default">Layer 2 bundle member link
      attributes advertisement</xref> for traffic steering.</t>
      <t>According to the classifications in <xref target="RFC7799" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC8762" format="default">Simple Two-way Active Measurement Protocol
      (STAMP)</xref> is an active measurement method, and it can complement
      passive and hybrid methods. It provides a mechanism to measure both
      one-way and round-trip performance metrics, like delay, delay variation,
      and packet loss. A STAMP test session over the LAG can be used to measure the
      performance of a member link using a specially constructed 5-tuple. The session can be used to measure
      an average of some or all member links of the LAG by varying one or more elements of that
      5-tuple. However, without the knowledge of each member link, a STAMP test
      session cannot measure the performance of every physical member
      link.</t>
      <t>This document extends STAMP to implement performance measurement on
      every member link of a LAG. It can provide the same metrics as <xref target="RFC4656" format="default">One-Way Active Measurement Protocol (OWAMP)</xref> and <xref target="RFC5357" format="default">Two-Way Active Measurement Protocol (TWAMP)</xref>
      can measure, such as delay, jitter, and packet loss.</t>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Requirements Language</name>
      <t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be
    interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref
    target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as
    shown here.</t>
    </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Micro Sessions on a LAG</name>
      <t>This document addresses the scenario where a LAG directly connects
      two nodes. An example of this is in <xref target="PMonLAG"/>, where the LAG consisting
      of four links connects nodes A and B. The goal is to measure the
      performance of each link of the LAG.</t>
      <figure anchor="PMonLAG">
        <name>Performance Measurement on a LAG</name>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[                  +---+                       +---+
                  |   |-----------------------|   | 
                  | A |-----------------------| B | 
                  |   |-----------------------|   |
                  |   |-----------------------|   |
                  +---+                       +---+ 
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>To measure the performance metrics of every member link of a LAG,
      multiple sessions (one session for each member link) need to be
      established between the two endpoints that are connected by the LAG.
      These sessions are called "micro sessions" in the remainder of this
      document. Although micro sessions are in fact STAMP sessions established
      on member links of a LAG, test packets of micro sessions <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> carry
      member link information for validation.</t>
      <t>All micro sessions of a LAG share the same Sender IP Address and
      Receiver IP Address. As for the UDP port, the micro sessions
      may share the same Sender Port and Receiver Port pair or each micro
      session may be configured with a different Sender Port and Receiver Port
      pair. From the operational point of view, the former is simpler and
      is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>.</t>
      <t>Test packets of a micro session <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> carry the member link
      information for validation checks. For example, when a micro STAMP
      Session-Sender receives a reflected test packet, it checks whether the
      test packet is from the expected member link. The member link
      information is encoded in the Micro-session ID TLV introduced in <xref target="validation"/>,
      which also provides a detailed description about  member link
      validation.</t>
      <t>A micro STAMP Session-Sender <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> include the <xref target="RFC8972" format="default">Follow-Up Telemetry TLV</xref> to request information
      from the micro Session-Reflector. This timestamp might be important for
      the micro Session-Sender, as it improves the accuracy of network delay
      measurement by minimizing the impact of egress queuing delays on the
      measurement.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default" anchor="validation">
      <name>Member Link Validation</name>
      <t>Test packets <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> carry member link information in the Micro-session ID
      TLV introduced in this section for validation checks. The micro
      Session-Sender verifies whether the test packet is received from the
      expected member link. It also verifies whether the packet is sent from
      the expected member link at the Reflector side. The micro
      Session-Reflector verifies whether the test packet is received from the
      expected member link.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Micro-session ID TLV</name>
        <t>The <xref target="RFC8972" format="default">STAMP TLV mechanism</xref> extends STAMP
        test packets with one or more optional TLVs. This document defines the
        TLV Type (value 11) for the Micro-session ID TLV that carries the
        micro STAMP Session-Sender member link identifier and
        Session-Reflector member link identifier in the Sender Micro-session ID
        field and the Reflector Micro-session ID field, respectively. The format of
        the Micro-session ID TLV is shown as follows:</t>
        <figure anchor="STAMPSender">
          <name>Micro-session ID TLV</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |STAMP TLV Flags|  Type = 11    |           Length              |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     Sender Micro-session ID   |   Reflector Micro-session ID  |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <dl spacing="normal">
          <dt>Type (1 octet in length):</dt>
          <dd>This field is defined to indicate this TLV
            is a Micro-session ID TLV. Value 11 has been allocated by IANA
            (<xref target="IANA"/>).</dd>
          <dt>Length (2 octets in length):</dt> 
          <dd>This field is defined to carry the length
            of the Value field in octets. The Length field value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
            4.</dd>
            <dt>Sender Micro-session ID (2 octets in length):</dt> 
            <dd>This field is defined
            to carry the LAG member link identifier of the Sender side. In the
            future, it may be used generically to cover use cases beyond LAGs.
            The value of this field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be unique within a STAMP session at
            the Session-Sender.</dd>
            <dt>Reflector Micro-session ID (2 octets in length):</dt>
            <dd>This field is
            defined to carry the LAG member link identifier of the Reflector
            side. In the future, it may be used generically to cover use cases
            beyond LAGs. The value of this field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be unique within a STAMP
            session at the Session-Reflector.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Micro STAMP-Test Procedures</name>
        <t>The micro STAMP-Test reuses the procedures as defined in Section 
        <xref target="RFC8762" sectionFormat="bare" section="4" format="default"/> of 
        <xref target="RFC8762" format="default">STAMP</xref> with the following
        additions.</t>
        <t>The micro STAMP Session-Sender <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send the micro STAMP-Test
        packets over the member link with which the session is associated. The
        mapping between a micro STAMP session and the Sender/Reflector member
        link identifiers can be configured by augmenting the <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-ippm-stamp-yang" format="default">STAMP
        YANG</xref>. The detailed augmentation is not in the scope of this
        document.</t>
        <t>When sending a test packet, the micro STAMP Session-Sender <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> set
        the Sender Micro-session ID field with the member link identifier
        associated with the micro STAMP session. If the Session-Sender knows
        the Reflector member link identifier, the Reflector Micro-session ID
        field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set. Otherwise, the Reflector Micro-session ID field
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be zero. The Reflector member link identifier can be obtained
        from preconfiguration or learned from data plane (e.g., the reflected
        test packet). This document does not specify the way to obtain the
        Reflector member link identifier.</t>
        <t>When the micro STAMP Session-Reflector receives a test packet, if
        the Reflector Micro-session ID is not zero, the micro STAMP
        Session-Reflector <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the Reflector member link identifier to
        check whether it is associated with the micro STAMP session. If the
        validation fails, the test packet <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be discarded. If the Reflector
        Micro-session ID is zero, it will not be verified. If all validations
        passed, the Session-Reflector sends a reflected test packet to the
        Session-Sender. The micro STAMP Session-Reflector <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> put the Sender
        and Reflector member link identifiers that are associated with the
        micro STAMP session in the Sender Micro-session ID and Reflector
        Micro-session ID fields, respectively. The Sender member link
        identifier is copied from the received test packet.</t>
        <t>When receiving a reflected test packet, the micro Session-Sender
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the Sender Micro-session ID to validate whether the reflected
        test packet is correctly received from the expected member link. If
        the validation fails, the test packet <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be discarded. The micro
        Session-Sender <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the Reflector Micro-session ID to validate the
        Reflector's behavior. If the validation fails, the test packet <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
        discarded.</t>
        <t>Two modes of the STAMP Session-Reflector, stateless and stateful,
        characterize the expected behavior as described in Section <xref target="RFC8762" sectionFormat="bare" section="4" format="default"/> of <xref target="RFC8762" format="default">STAMP</xref>. The micro STAMP-Test also supports both
        stateless and stateful modes. However, the micro STAMP-Test does not
        introduce any additional state to STAMP, i.e., any procedure with
        regard to the Micro-session ID is stateless.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Applicability</name>
      <t>The micro STAMP Session-Sender sends micro Session-Sender packets
      with the Micro-session ID TLV. The micro Session-Reflector checks
      whether a test packet is received from the member link associated with
      the correct micro STAMP session if the Reflector Micro-session ID field
      is set. When reflecting, the micro STAMP Session-Reflector copies the
      Sender Micro-session ID from the received micro Session-Sender packet to
      the micro Session-Reflector packet and sets the Reflector Micro-session
      ID field with the member link identifier that is associated with the
      micro STAMP session. When receiving the micro Session-Reflector packet,
      the micro Session-Sender uses the Sender Micro-session ID to check
      whether the packet is received from the member link associated with the
      correct micro STAMP session. The micro Session-Sender also use the
      Reflector Micro-session ID to validate the Reflector's behavior.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>IANA has allocated the following STAMP 
      TLV Type for the Micro-session ID TLV in the "STAMP TLV Types" registry <xref target="RFC8972" format="default"/>:</t>
      <table anchor="reg_table">
        <name>New STAMP TLV Type</name>
        <thead>
	  <tr>
            <th>Value</th>
            <th>Description</th>
            <th>Reference</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>11</td>
            <td>Micro-session ID</td>
            <td>This Document</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The STAMP extension defined in this document is intended for
      deployment in the LAG scenario where Session-Sender and Session-Reflector
      are directly connected. As such, it's assumed that a node involved in
      a STAMP operation has previously verified the integrity of the
      LAG connection and the identity of its one-hop-away peer node.</t>
      <t>This document does not introduce any additional security issues, and
      the security mechanisms defined in <xref target="RFC8762" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC8972" format="default"/> apply in this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>

    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-ippm-stamp-yang" to="STAMP-YANG"/>

    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8762.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8972.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

        <reference anchor="IEEE802.1AX" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9105034">
          <front>
            <title>IEEE Standard for Local and Metropolitan Area Networks -- Link
          Aggregation</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IEEE</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="May" year="2020"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="IEEE Std" value="802.1AX-2020"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/IEEESTD.2020.9105034"/>
        </reference>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7799.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8668.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4656.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5357.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ippm-stamp-yang.xml"/>

      </references>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>The authors would like to thank <contact fullname="Mach Chen"/>, <contact fullname="Min Xiao"/>, <contact fullname="Fang Xin"/>, <contact fullname="Marcus Ihlar"/>, and <contact fullname="Richard Foote"/> for the valuable comments to this work.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
