<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc version 1.6.10 (Ruby 2.7.0) -->
<?rfc docmapping="yes"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="bcp" ipr="pre5378Trust200902" number="9245" docName="draft-eggert-bcp45bis-08" consensus="true" submissionType="IETF" obsoletes="3005" updates="3683" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.12.8 -->
  <front>
    <title>IETF Discussion List Charter</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9245"/>
    <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="45"/>
    <author initials="L." surname="Eggert" fullname="Lars Eggert">
      <organization>NetApp</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Stenbergintie 12 B</street>
          <city>Kauniainen</city>
          <code>02700</code>
          <country>FI</country>
        </postal>
        <email>lars@eggert.org</email>
        <uri>https://eggert.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="S." surname="Harris" fullname="Susan Harris">
      <organization/>
      <address>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="2022"/>

<keyword>mail list</keyword>
<keyword>mailing list</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) discussion mailing list furthers the
development and specification of Internet technology through the general
discussion of technical, procedural, operational, and other topics for which no
dedicated mailing lists exist. As this is the most general IETF mailing list,
considerable latitude in terms of topics is allowed, but there are posts and
topics that are unsuitable for this mailing list. This document defines the
charter for the IETF discussion list and explains its scope.</t>
      <t>This document obsoletes RFC 3005 and updates RFC 3683.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>The IETF discussion list <xref target="IETF-DISCUSS"/> furthers the development and
specification of Internet technology through the general discussion of
technical, procedural, operational, and other topics for which no dedicated
mailing lists exist. As this is the most general IETF mailing list,
considerable latitude in terms of topics is allowed. However, there are posts
and topics that are unsuitable for this mailing list. This document defines the
charter for the IETF discussion list and explains its scope.</t>
      <t>The IETF Note Well <xref target="NOTE-WELL"/> applies to discussions on the IETF discussion
list and all other IETF mailing lists, and requires conformance with the IETF
Guidelines for Conduct <xref target="RFC7154"/> and the Anti-Harassment Policy <xref target="RFC7776"/>,
among others.</t>
      <t>This document obsoletes <xref target="RFC3005"/>, as it documents the use of other mailing
lists for discussions that were previously in scope for the IETF discussion list,
refers to applicable policies such as the Guidelines for Conduct
<xref target="RFC7154"/> and the Anti-Harassment Policy <xref target="RFC7776"/>, and clarifies
moderation procedures. It also updates part of <xref section="1" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC3683"/>, which
copies the list of "inappropriate postings" from <xref target="RFC3005"/>. The list in
<xref target="RFC3683"/> is hence updated by the new list in <xref target="charter"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="charter">
      <name>Charter for the IETF Discussion List</name>
      <t>The IETF discussion list is meant for discussions for which a more appropriate
list does not exist, such as discussions that do not fall within the scope of
any working group, area, or other established list. When there is an existing venue 
for discussion, this should be noted and discussion should be moved there.</t>
      <t>When no dedicated mailing list exists for a topic, it may be preferable to
request that one be created <xref target="NON-WG-LISTS"/> rather than discuss it on
the IETF discussion list.  Availability of the new list
may be announced on the IETF discussion list and on other
related lists, such as area lists.</t>
      <t>Appropriate postings to the IETF discussion list include:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>Initial discussion of technical issues that are candidates for IETF work, but
appropriate mailing lists have not yet been identified.</li>
        <li>Questions and clarifications concerning practical aspects of IETF meetings,
although most of these topics are better brought up on the discussion list for
IETF LLC administrative issues <xref target="ADMIN-DISCUSS"/> or the attendee discussion
list for a given IETF meeting.</li>
        <li>Announcements of conferences, events, or activities that are sponsored or
endorsed by the IETF, IRTF, IAB or the Internet Society, although the IETF
announcement list <xref target="IETF-ANNOUNCE"/> is the preferred list for these.</li>
        <li>Discussions of IETF direction, policy, and the standards process in general,
when a more suitable list (such as the discussion list for IETF LLC
administrative issues <xref target="ADMIN-DISCUSS"/>, the IAB discussion list for
architectural issues <xref target="ARCH-DISCUSS"/>, a meeting attendees list, a
process-oriented WG list, etc.) cannot be identified.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>These topics used to be in scope for the IETF discussion list, but have since
moved to dedicated lists:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>Last Call discussions of documents now take place on the IETF
Last Calls mailing list <xref target="LAST-CALLS"/>.</li>
        <li>Discussion of IETF administrative policies now takes place on the discussion
list for IETF LLC administrative issues <xref target="ADMIN-DISCUSS"/>.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>Inappropriate postings include:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>Advertising and other unsolicited bulk e-mail</li>
        <li>Discussion of subjects unrelated to IETF policy, meetings, activities, or
technical topics</li>
        <li>Uncivil commentary, regardless of the general subject, per the IETF Note Well
<xref target="NOTE-WELL"/></li>
        <li>Announcements of conferences, events, or activities that are not sponsored or
endorsed by the IETF, IRTF, IAB, or the Internet Society.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section anchor="mod">
      <name>Moderation</name>
      <t>The IETF Chair appoints <em>Moderators</em> (previously known as
the "sergeant-at-arms") for the IETF discussion list that are empowered to
restrict posting by a person, or to an email thread, when the content is
inappropriate and represents a pattern of abuse. They are encouraged to take
into account the overall nature of the postings by an individual and whether
particular postings are typical or an aberration.</t>
      <t>Moderation of the IETF discussion list, including the handling of any appeals,
is guided by the IETF discussion list charter specified in
<xref target="charter"/>, and the related guidance from <xref target="intro"/> that applies to all mailing
lists. The moderators are selected from within the community to moderate the community. Because the IESG and IAB are in the appeals
chain for moderator decisions (see below), the IETF Chair therefore should not
appoint a moderator who is serving in such a role. If a moderator is selected
for the IESG or IAB, they will step down from the moderator team.</t>
      <t>Apart from appointing moderators, the IETF Chair should refrain from the
day-to-day operation and management of the moderator team. The moderator team
will independently define, publish, and execute their role; see the current set
of operating procedures <xref target="MOD-SOP"/> and abuse patterns <xref target="MOD-UPC"/>.
The moderator team should reach out to the
IETF Chair for any conflict resolution in a timely manner.</t>
      <t>Because a moderator serves at the discretion of the IETF Chair -- even if the
IETF Chair is not otherwise involved in the operation of the moderator team --
any moderator decision can be appealed to the IETF Chair, per
<xref target="RFC2026"/>. Decisions by the IETF Chair can be appealed to the IESG as whole,
again per <xref target="RFC2026"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The usual security considerations <xref target="RFC3552"/> do not apply to this document.</t>
      <t>Potential abuse of the moderation process for the suppression of undesired
opinions is counteracted by the availability of an appeals process, per
<xref target="mod"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document does not request any IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>

<xi:include href="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2026.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="MOD-SOP" target="https://github.com/ietf/saa/blob/main/sop.md">
          <front>
            <title>Sergeant-at-Arms Standard Operating Procedures</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IETF</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2019" month="October" day="09"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="commit c1abcb0" value=""/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="MOD-UPC" target="https://github.com/ietf/saa/blob/main/unprofessional-commentary.md">
          <front>
            <title>Unprofessional commentary</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IETF</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2019" month="October" day="08"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="commit e120305" value=""/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="LAST-CALLS" target="https://ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/last-call">
          <front>
            <title>last-call -- IETF Last Calls</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IETF</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="IETF-DISCUSS" target="https://ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/ietf">
          <front>
            <title>ietf -- IETF-Discussion</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IETF</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="IETF-ANNOUNCE" target="https://ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/ietf-announce">
          <front>
            <title>IETF-Announce -- IETF announcement list. No discussions.</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IETF</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="ADMIN-DISCUSS" target="https://ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/admin-discuss">
          <front>
            <title>admin-discuss -- Discussion list for IETF LLC administrative issues</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IETF</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="NOTE-WELL" target="https://ietf.org/about/note-well/">
          <front>
            <title>Note Well</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IETF</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="NON-WG-LISTS" target="https://ietf.org/how/lists/nonwglist-guidelines/">
          <front>
            <title>Non-Working Group Email List Guidelines</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IETF</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="ARCH-DISCUSS" target="https://ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/architecture-discuss">
          <front>
            <title>Architecture-discuss -- open discussion forum for long/wide-range architectural issues</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IAB</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7154.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7776.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3005.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3683.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3184.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3160.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section numbered="false" anchor="acknowledgements">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t><contact fullname="Susan R. Harris"/> authored <xref target="RFC3005"/>, which this document replaces. In addition
to many technical contributions to the IETF, Susan authored a number of other
foundational documents, such as the original "IETF Guidelines for Conduct"
<xref target="RFC3184"/> and the original "Tao of the IETF" <xref target="RFC3160"/>.  Susan R. Harris
passed away in early 2022. This document is dedicated to her
memory, as a small token of appreciation of her many contributions.</t>
      <t>The following people have made other contributions to this document:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li><t><contact fullname="Adrian Farrel"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Barry Leiba"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Ben Kaduk"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Brian Carpenter"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Carsten Bormann"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Christian Huitema"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Dhruv Dhody"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Eric Rescorla"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Eric Vyncke"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Francesca Palombini"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="John Scudder"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Lloyd Wood"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Martin Thomson"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Robert Wilton"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Subramanian Moonesamy"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Stephen Farrell"/></t></li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
