<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="true" docName="draft-ietf-bess-evpn-lsp-ping-11" number="9489" ipr="trust200902" updates="" obsoletes="" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">

<!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.17.2 -->
  <front>
<title abbrev="LSP Ping for EVPN and PBB-EVPN">Label Switched Path (LSP) Ping Mechanisms for EVPN and Provider Backbone Bridging EVPN (PBB-EVPN)</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9489"/>
    <author fullname="Parag Jain" initials="P." surname="Jain">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>paragj@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Ali Sajassi" initials="A." surname="Sajassi">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sajassi@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Samer Salam" initials="S." surname="Salam">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ssalam@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Sami Boutros" initials="S." surname="Boutros">
      <organization>Ciena</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sboutros@ciena.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Greg Mirsky" initials="G." surname="Mirsky">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>gregimirsky@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2023" month="November"/>
    <area>rtg</area>
    <workgroup>bess</workgroup>
    <keyword>EVPN</keyword>
    <keyword>LSP Ping</keyword>
    <keyword>MPLS OAM</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Label Switched Path (LSP) Ping is a widely deployed Operations, Administration, and 
   Maintenance (OAM) mechanism in MPLS networks. 
This document describes mechanisms for detecting data plane failures using LSP
Ping in MPLS-based Ethernet VPN (EVPN) and Provider Backbone Bridging EVPN (PBB-EVPN) networks.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t><xref target="RFC7432" format="default"/> describes MPLS-based EVPN
      technology.  An EVPN comprises one or more Customer Edge devices (CEs) connected to one or more
      Provider Edge devices (PEs). The PEs provide Layer 2 (L2) EVPN among the
      CE(s) over the MPLS core infrastructure.  In EVPN networks, the PEs
      advertise the Media Access Control (MAC) addresses learned from the
      locally connected CE(s), along with the MPLS label, to remote PE(s)
      in the control plane using multiprotocol BGP <xref target="RFC4760"
      format="default"/>. EVPN enables multihoming of CE(s) connected to
      multiple PEs and load balancing of traffic to and from multihomed
      CE(s).</t>
      <t><xref target="RFC7623" format="default"/> describes the use of
      Provider Backbone Bridging EVPN. PBB-EVPN maintains the Customer
      MAC (C-MAC) learning in the data plane and only advertises Backbone MAC
      (B-MAC) addresses in a control plane using BGP.</t>
      <t>Procedures for simple and efficient mechanisms to detect data plane 
   failures using LSP Ping in MPLS networks are well defined in 
   <xref target="RFC8029" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC6425" format="default"/>. 
   The basic idea for the LSP Ping mechanism is to send an MPLS Echo Request packet
   along the same data path as data packets belonging to the same Forwarding 
   Equivalent Class (FEC). The Echo Request packet carries the FEC being verified 
   in the Target FEC Stack TLV <xref target="RFC8029" format="default"/>. Once the Echo Request packet reaches the end of 
   the MPLS path, it is sent to the control plane of the egress PE. 
   The Echo Request packet contains sufficient information to verify the correctness 
   of data plane operations and validate the data plane against the control plane.
   The egress PE sends the results of the validation in an Echo Reply packet to the 
   originating PE of the Echo Request packet.</t>
      <t>This document defines procedures to detect data 
   plane failures using LSP Ping in MPLS networks deploying EVPN and 
   PBB-EVPN. This document defines four new sub-TLVs for the Target FEC Stack TLV 
   with the purpose of identifying the FEC on the egress PE.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Specification of Requirements</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>
<dl>
      <dt>A-D:</dt><dd>Auto-Discovery</dd>
      <dt>B-MAC:</dt><dd>Backbone MAC</dd>
      <dt>BUM:</dt><dd>Broadcast, Unknown Unicast, and Multicast</dd>
      <dt>CE:</dt><dd>Customer Edge device</dd>
      <dt>C-MAC:</dt><dd>Customer MAC</dd>
      <dt>DF:</dt><dd>Designated Forwarder</dd>
      <dt>ES:</dt><dd>Ethernet Segment</dd>
      <dt>ESI:</dt><dd>Ethernet Segment Identifier</dd>
      <dt>EVI:</dt><dd>EVPN Instance Identifier that globally identifies the EVPN Instance</dd>
      <dt>EVPN:</dt><dd>Ethernet Virtual Private Network</dd>
      <dt>FEC:</dt><dd>Forwarding Equivalent Class</dd>
      <dt>G-ACh:</dt><dd>Generic Associated Channel</dd>
      <dt>GAL:</dt><dd>G-ACh Label</dd>
      <dt>MAC-VRF:</dt><dd>A Virtual Routing and Forwarding table for MAC
      addresses on a PE</dd>
      <dt>ND:</dt><dd>Neighbor Discovery</dd> 
      <dt>OAM:</dt><dd>Operations, Administration, and Maintenance</dd>
      <dt>P2MP:</dt><dd>Point-to-Multipoint</dd>
      <dt>PBB-EVPN:</dt><dd>Provider Backbone Bridging EVPN</dd>
      <dt>PE:</dt><dd>Provider Edge device</dd>
      <dt>VPWS:</dt><dd>Virtual Private Wire Service</dd>
</dl>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Target FEC Stack Sub-TLVs</name>
      <t>This document introduces four new Target FEC Stack sub-TLVs that 
   are included in the MPLS Echo Request packet. The Echo Request packets 
   are used for connectivity checks in the data plane in EVPN and PBB-EVPN networks. 
   The Target FEC Stack sub-TLVs <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be used to validate that an identifier 
   for a given EVPN is programmed at the target node.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>EVPN MAC/IP Sub-TLV</name>
        <t>The EVPN MAC/IP sub-TLV identifies the target MAC, MAC/IP binding for ARP/ND, 
        or IP address for an EVI under test at an egress PE.
        This sub-TLV is included in the Echo Request sent by an
        EVPN/PBB-EVPN PE to a peer PE.</t>

        <t>The fields of the EVPN MAC/IP sub-TLV are derived from the MAC/IP Advertisement 
   route defined in <xref target="RFC7432" sectionFormat="of" section="7.2"/> and have the format 
   shown in <xref target="fig1"/>. The fields of the EVPN MAC/IP sub-TLV should be set according to the 
   following, which is consistent with <xref target="RFC7432" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC7623" format="default"/>:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>The Ethernet Tag ID field can be 0 or a valid VLAN ID for EVPN VLAN-aware bundle 
         service <xref target="RFC7432" format="default"/>. For PBB-EVPN, the value of this field is always 0 as 
         per <xref target="RFC7623" sectionFormat="of" section="5.2"/>.</li>
          <li>The Ethernet Segment Identifier field is a 10-octet field. For EVPN, it is set to 0 for a
         single-homed ES or to a valid ESI ID for a multihomed ES. For PBB-EVPN, the Ethernet 
         Segment Identifier field must be set to either 0 (for single-homed segments or multihomed segments with per-I-SID load balancing) or to MAX-ESI (for multihomed segments with per-flow load balancing) as
         described in <xref target="RFC7623" sectionFormat="of" section="5.2"/>.</li>
          <li>The MAC Addr Len field specifies the MAC length in bits. Only 48-bit MAC addresses
         are supported as this document follows the MAC address length supported by <xref target="RFC7432" format="default"/>.</li>
          <li>The MAC Address field is set to the 6-octet MAC address.</li>

          <li>The IP Address field is optional. When the IP Address field is not present, 
         the IP Addr Len field is set to 0. When the IP Address field is present, the IP Addr Len field is in
         bits and is set to either 32 for IPv4 addresses or 128 for IPv6 addresses. </li>
          <li>The Must Be Zero fields are set to 0. The receiving PE should ignore the 
         Must Be Zero fields. </li>
        </ul>

<figure anchor="fig1" title="EVPN MAC/IP Sub-TLV Format">  
      <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|                    Route Distinguisher                        | 
|                        (8 octets)                             | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|                     Ethernet Tag ID                           | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|               Ethernet Segment Identifier                     | 
|                     (10 octets)                               | 
+                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|                               | Must Be Zero  |  MAC Addr Len | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|                MAC Address                                    | 
+                 (6 octets)    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|                               | Must Be Zero  |  IP Addr Len  |          
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|                IP Address (0, 4 or 16 octets)                 | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork></figure>
        <t>The MPLS Echo Request is sent by the ingress PE using the EVPN MPLS label(s) associated with the MAC/IP Advertisement route announced by the egress PE and the MPLS transport label(s) to reach the egress PE.</t>
<t>In EVPN, the MAC/IP Advertisement route has multiple uses and is used for
the following cases:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>This route with only a MAC address and MPLS Label1 is used for populating MAC-VRF and performing MAC forwarding.</li>
          <li>This route with MAC and IP addresses and only MPLS Label1 is used for populating both MAC-VRF and ARP/ND tables (for ARP suppression) as well as for performing MAC forwarding.</li>
          <li>This route with MAC and IP addresses and both MPLS Label1 and Label2 is used for populating MAC-VRF and IP-VRF tables as well as for both MAC and IP forwarding in the case of symmetric Integrated Routing and Bridging (IRB).</li>
        </ul>
        <t>When an MPLS Echo Request is sent by an ingress PE, the contents of the Echo Request and the egress PE mode of operation (i.e., IRB mode or L2 mode) along with EVPN MPLS label of the packet determine which of the three cases above this Echo Request is for. When the egress PE receives the EVPN MAC/IP sub-TLV containing only the MAC address, the egress PE validates the MAC state and forwarding.  When the egress PE receives the EVPN MAC/IP sub-TLV containing both MAC and IP addresses and if the EVPN label points to a MAC-VRF, then the egress PE validates the MAC state and forwarding. If the egress PE is not configured in symmetric IRB mode, it also validates ARP/ND state. However, if the EVPN label points to an IP-VRF, then the egress PE validates IP state and forwarding. 
Any other combinations (e.g., the egress PE receiving
   the EVPN MAC/IP sub-TLV containing only the MAC address but with the EVPN label
   pointing to an IP-VRF) should be considered invalid, 
   and the egress PE should send an Echo Reply with the appropriate Return          
   Code to the ingress PE.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>EVPN Inclusive Multicast Sub-TLV</name>
        <t>The fields of the EVPN Inclusive Multicast sub-TLV are based on the EVPN 
   Inclusive Multicast Tag route defined in <xref target="RFC7432" sectionFormat="of" section="7.3"/>.
   This TLV is included in the Echo Request sent to the EVPN 
   peer PE by the originator of the request to verify the multicast 
   connectivity state on the peer PE(s) in EVPN and PBB-EVPN networks.
        </t>
        <t>The EVPN Inclusive Multicast sub-TLV has the format shown in 
   <xref target="fig2"/>. The fields of this sub-TLV should be set according to the 
   following, which is consistent with <xref target="RFC7432" format="default"/> and 
   <xref target="RFC7623" format="default"/>:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>The Route Distinguisher (RD) field is a 10-octet field and is set to the RD
         of the MAC-VRF on the peer PE.</li>
          <li>For EVPN, the Ethernet Tag ID field can be set to 0 or a valid VLAN ID for 
         EVPN VLAN-aware bundle service <xref target="RFC7432" format="default"/>.
         For PBB-EVPN, the value of this field is set to the Service 
         Instance Identifier (I-SID) value as per <xref target="RFC7623" sectionFormat="of" section="5.3"/>.</li>
          <li>The IP Addr Len field specifies the length of the Originating Router's IP Addr field in bits and is set to either 32 for IPv4 addresses or 128 for IPv6 addresses.</li>
          <li>The Originating Router's IP Addr field is set to the IPv4 or IPv6 address of the peer PE.</li>
        </ul>

	<figure anchor="fig2" title="EVPN Inclusive Multicast Sub-TLV Format">
        <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|                    Route Distinguisher                        | 
|                        (8 octets)                             | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|                     Ethernet Tag ID                           |       
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
| IP Addr Len |                                                 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                                 |
~               Originating Router's IP Addr                    ~
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork></figure>
        <t>BUM traffic can be sent using ingress replication or P2MP P-tree in
        EVPN and PBB-EVPN networks.  When using ingress replication, the Echo
        Request is sent using a label stack of [Transport label, Inclusive
        Multicast label] to each egress PE participating in EVPN or
        PBB-EVPN. The Inclusive Multicast label is the downstream-assigned
        label announced by the egress PE to which the Echo Request is being
        sent. The Inclusive Multicast label is the inner label in the MPLS
        label stack.</t>
        <t>When using P2MP P-tree in EVPN or PBB-EVPN, the Echo Request is 
   sent using a P2MP P-tree transport label for the Inclusive P-tree 
   arrangement or using a label stack of [P2MP P-tree Transport label,
   upstream-assigned EVPN Inclusive Multicast label] for the Aggregate 
   Inclusive P2MP P-tree arrangement as described in <xref target="operations"/>.</t>

<t> In an EVPN network, to emulate traffic coming from a multihomed site, an
additional EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV in the Target FEC Stack TLV
and an ESI Split Horizon Group MPLS label as the bottom label are also
included in the Echo Request packet.  When using P2MP P-tree, the ESI Split
Horizon Group MPLS label is upstream assigned. Please see <xref
target="p2mp-ptree"/> for operations using P2MP P-trees.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>EVPN Ethernet Auto-Discovery (A-D) Sub-TLV</name>
        <t>The fields in the EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV are based on the 
   EVPN Ethernet A-D route advertisement defined in <xref target="RFC7432" sectionFormat="of" section="7.1"/>.  The EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV only applies to EVPN.</t>

   <t>The EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV has the format shown in <xref target="fig3"/>.
      The fields of this sub-TLV should be set according to the 
          following, which is consistent with <xref target="RFC7432" format="default"/>:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>The Route Distinguisher (RD) field is a 10-octet field and is set to the RD
         of the MAC-VRF on the peer PE. Please see <xref target="adroute"/> for the case when a
         per-ES A-D route is announced with different RDs.</li>
          <li>The Ethernet Tag ID field can be 0, MAX-ET, or a valid VLAN ID as described in 
         <xref target="etagvalue"/>.</li>
          <li>The Ethernet Segment Identifier field is a 10-octet field and is set to 0 for 
        a single-homed ES or to a valid ESI ID for a multihomed ES.</li>
          <li>The Must Be Zero field is set to 0. The receiving PE should ignore the 
         Must Be Zero field. </li>
        </ul>

	<figure anchor="fig3" title="EVPN Ethernet A-D Sub-TLV Format">
        <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|                    Route Distinguisher                        | 
|                        (8 octets)                             | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|                     Ethernet Tag ID                           |    
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|               Ethernet Segment Identifier                     | 
|                     (10 octets)                               | 
+                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|                               |      Must Be Zero             | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork></figure>
        <section anchor="etagvalue" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Ethernet Tag Value</name>
          <t>The EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV can be sent in the context of per-ES or per-EVI.
When an operator performs a connectivity check for the BUM L2 service, 
         an Echo Request packet is sent and <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> contain the EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV to emulate traffic 
         coming from a multihomed site.  In this case, the EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV is 
         added in the per-ES context. When an Echo Request packet is sent for the connectivity 
         check for EVPN Aliasing state, the context for the EVPN Ethernet A-D 
         sub-TLV is per-EVI.</t>
          <t>The Ethernet Tag field value in the EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set according 
         to the context:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>For the per-ES context, the Ethernet Tag field in the sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to 
         the reserved MAX-ET value <xref target="RFC7432" format="default"/>.</li>
            <li>For the per-EVI context, the Ethernet Tag field in the sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to 
         the non-reserved value.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>
        <section anchor="adroute" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Per-ES EVPN Auto-Discovery Route with Different RDs</name>
          <t><xref target="RFC7432" sectionFormat="of" section="8.2"/> specifies that a per-ES EVPN A-D route for 
        a given multihomed ES may be advertised more than once with different RD values 
        because many EVIs may be associated with the same ES and Route Targets for all these 
        EVIs may not fit in a single BGP Update message.  In this case, the RD value used 
        in the EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the RD value received for the EVI in the 
        per-ES EVPN A-D route.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>EVPN VPWS</name>
          <t>LSP Ping can also be used to detect data plane failures for the EVPN VPWS described in <xref target="RFC8214" format="default"/>. 
        The Echo Request packet carries the EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV with fields populated from 
        the EVPN Ethernet A-D per-EVI route announced by the egress PE for the EVPN VPWS under test.
        The Echo Request is sent by the ingress 
        PE using the EVPN MPLS label associated with the EVPN Ethernet A-D route announced by the 
        egress PE and the MPLS transport label(s) to reach the egress PE.</t>
          <t>The egress PE processes the Echo Request packet and performs
          checks for the EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV present in the Target FEC
          Stack TLV as described in <xref target="RFC8029" sectionFormat="of"
          section="4.4"/> and responds according to processing rules in <xref
          target="RFC8029" format="default"/>.  The egress PE can identify
          that the Echo Request is for the EVPN VPWS instance as EVI
          (identified by the RD) for EVPN VPWS is different from EVI assigned
          for EVPN. The egress PE will use the information from the EVPN
          Ethernet A-D sub-TLV in the Target FEC Stack TLV and validate the
          VLAN state for the EVPN VPWS under test.  For the success case, the
          egress PE will reply with Return Code 3 ("Replying router is an
          egress for the FEC at stack-depth &lt;RSC&gt;").</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>EVPN IP Prefix Sub-TLV</name>
        <t>The EVPN IP Prefix sub-TLV identifies the IP prefix for an EVI under 
   test at a peer PE.</t>
        <t>The EVPN IP Prefix sub-TLV fields are derived from the IP Prefix route (RT-5) 
          advertisement defined in <xref target="RFC9136" format="default"/>. This sub-TLV only applies to 
          EVPN.</t>
        <t>The EVPN IP Prefix sub-TLV has the format shown in <xref target="fig4"/>.  The
           total length (not shown) of this sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be either 32 bytes (if
           IPv4 addresses are carried) or 56 bytes (if IPv6 addresses are carried).
          The IP prefix and gateway IP address <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be from the same IP address
          family, as described in <xref target="RFC9136" sectionFormat="of" section="3.1"/>.</t>
        <t>The fields of the EVPN IP Prefix sub-TLV should be set according to the 
          following, which is consistent with <xref target="RFC9136" format="default"/>:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>The Route Distinguisher (RD) field is a 10-octet field and is set to the RD
         of the IP-VRF on the peer PE.</li>
          <li>The Ethernet Tag ID field can be 0 or a valid VLAN ID for EVPN VLAN-aware bundle 
         service <xref target="RFC7432" format="default"/>.</li>
         <li>The Ethernet Segment Identifier field is a 10-octet field and is set to 
         a valid ESI ID if the ESI is used as an Overlay Index as per <xref target="RFC9136" sectionFormat="of" section="3.1"/>.
         Otherwise, the Ethernet Segment Identifier field is set to 0.</li>
          <li>The IP Prefix Len field specifies the number of bits in the IP Prefix field. It 
        is set to a value between 0 and 32 for IPv4 or between 0 to 128 for IPv6.</li>
          <li>The IP Prefix field is set to a 4-octet IPv4 address (with
         trailing 0 bits to make 32 bits in all) or a 16-octet IPv6 address
         (with trailing 0 bits to make 128 bits in all). The address family
         of this field is inferred from the sub-TLV length field, as
         discussed above.</li>
          <li> The Gateway (GW) IP Address field is set to a 4-octet IPv4 address
          or a 16-octet IPv6 address if it's used as an Overlay Index for the
         IP prefixes.  If the GW IP Address is not being used, it must be
         set to 0 as described in <xref target="RFC9136" sectionFormat="of" section="3.1"/>. The address
         family of this field is inferred from the sub-TLV length field, as
         discussed above.</li>
          <li>The Must Be Zero field is set to 0. The receiving PE should ignore the 
         Must Be Zero field. </li>
        </ul>

	<figure anchor="fig4" title="EVPN IP Prefix Sub-TLV Format">
        <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3 
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|                    Route Distinguisher                        | 
|                        (8 octets)                             | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|                     Ethernet Tag ID                           |     
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|               Ethernet Segment Identifier                     | 
|                     (10 octets)                               | 
+                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
|                               | Must Be Zero  | IP Prefix Len |      
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
~                 IP Prefix  (4 or 16 octets)                   ~ 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
~                GW IP Address (4 or 16 octets)                 ~ 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork></figure>
        <t>The MPLS Echo Request is sent by the ingress PE using the EVPN MPLS label(s) 
   associated with the IP Prefix route announced by the egress PE and the MPLS 
   transport label(s) to reach the egress PE.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Encapsulation of OAM Ping Packets</name>
      <t>The MPLS Echo Request IP/UDP packets <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be encapsulated 
         with the Transport and EVPN label(s) followed by the
         GAL <xref target="RFC5586" format="default"/>, which is the bottommost label.
         The GAL is followed by a G-ACh header carrying the 
         IPv4(0x0021) or IPv6(0x0057) Channel Type. The code points for IPv4 and 
         IPv6 channels are defined in the "Generic Associated Channel (G-ACh) Parameters" IANA registry.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="operations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Operations</name>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Unicast Data Plane Connectivity Checks</name>
        <t><xref target="fig5"/> is an example of a PBB-EVPN network. CE1 is dual-homed to 
  PE1 and PE2. Assume that PE1 announced a MAC route with RD 192.0.2.1:00 and 
  B-MAC 00-AA-00-BB-00-CC and with MPLS label 16001 for EVI 10. Similarly, 
  PE2 announced a MAC route with RD 203.0.113.2:00 and B-MAC 00-AA-00-BB-00-CC 
  and with MPLS label 16002.</t>
        <t>On PE3, when an operator performs a connectivity check for the B-MAC 
  address 00-AA-00-BB-00-CC on PE1, the operator initiates an LSP Ping
  request with the Target FEC Stack TLV containing the EVPN MAC/IP sub-TLV in 
  the Echo Request packet. The Echo Request packet is sent with the 
  {Transport label(s) to reach PE1, EVPN label = 16001, GAL} MPLS label 
  stack and IP ACH Channel header. Once the Echo Request packet reaches PE1, 
  PE1 will use the GAL and the IP ACH Channel header
  to determine if the packet is an IPv4 or IPv6 OAM packet. The PE1 will process the 
  packet and perform checks for the EVPN MAC/IP sub-TLV present in the 
  Target FEC Stack TLV as described in <xref target="RFC8029" sectionFormat="of" section="4.4"/> and 
  respond according to the processing rules in <xref target="RFC8029" format="default"/>.</t>

	<figure anchor="fig5" title="PBB-EVPN Network">
        <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
                  +-----------------+
                  |                 |
                  |                 |
+----+ AC1  +-----+                 +-----+     +----+
| CE1|------|     |                 | PE3 |-----| CE2|
+----+\     | PE1 |     IP/MPLS     |     |     +----+
       \    +-----+     Network     +-----+
        \         |                 |
      AC2\  +-----+                 |
          \ |     |                 |
           \| PE2 |                 |
            +-----+                 |
                  |                 |
                  +-----------------+

  <-802.1Q->  <------PBB over MPLS------>  <-802.1Q->
]]></artwork></figure>
        <t>Similarly, on PE3, when an operator performs a connectivity check for 
  the B-MAC address 00-AA-00-BB-00-CC on PE2, the operator initiates an 
  LSP Ping request with the Target FEC Stack TLV containing the EVPN MAC/IP 
  sub-TLV in the Echo Request packet. The Echo Request packet is sent 
  with the {MPLS Transport label(s) to reach PE2, EVPN label = 16002, GAL} 
  MPLS label stack and IP ACH Channel header.</t>
        <t>LSP Ping operations for unicast data plane connectivity checks in EVPN
  are similar to those described above for PBB-EVPN, except that the 
  checks are for C-MAC addresses instead of B-MAC addresses.</t>
        <t> In EVPN networks, an operator can also perform a MAC state test using an aliasing 
    label for the MAC to verify the MAC state on the egress multihoming PE that did 
    not learn the MAC from the multihomed CE on a local ESI but has announced Ethernet 
    A-D per-EVI and per-ESI routes for the ESI. This is due to the fact that
    MAC state on multihoming PEs that did not learn the MAC locally get created
    from EVPN MAC/IP route advertisement from the multihoming PE that has
    learned the CE's MAC address locally.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Inclusive Multicast Data Plane Connectivity Checks</name>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Ingress Replication</name>
          <t>Assume PE1 announced an Inclusive Multicast route for EVI 10, with 
   RD 192.0.2.1:00, Ethernet Tag (ISID 10), PMSI tunnel attribute Tunnel 
   type set to ingress replication, and downstream-assigned Inclusive 
   Multicast MPLS label 17001. Similarly, PE2 announced an Inclusive 
   Multicast route for EVI 10, with RD 203.0.113.2:00, Ethernet Tag (ISID 
   10), PMSI tunnel attribute Tunnel type set to ingress replication, 
   and downstream-assigned Inclusive Multicast MPLS label 17002.</t>
          <t>Given CE1 is dual-homed to PE1 and PE2, assume that PE1 is the DF 
   for ISID 10 for the port corresponding to the ESI 11aa.22bb.33cc. 
   44dd.5500.</t>
          <t>When an operator at PE3 initiates a connectivity check for the 
   Inclusive Multicast on PE1, the operator initiates an LSP Ping 
   request with the Target FEC Stack TLV containing the EVPN Inclusive 
   Multicast sub-TLV in the Echo Request packet. The Echo Request 
   packet is sent with the {Transport label(s) to reach PE1, EVPN 
   Inclusive Multicast label = 17001, GAL} MPLS label stack and IP ACH Channel header. 
   Once the Echo Request packet reaches PE1, 
   PE1 will use the GAL and the IP ACH Channel header
   to determine if the packet is an IPv4 or IPv6 OAM packet. 
   The packet will have the EVPN Inclusive Multicast label. 
   PE1 will process the packet and perform checks for the EVPN 
   Inclusive Multicast sub-TLV present in the Target FEC Stack TLV as 
   described in <xref target="RFC8029" sectionFormat="of" section="4.4"/> and respond according to 
   the processing rules in <xref target="RFC8029" format="default"/>. For the success case, PE1 will reply 
   with Return Code 3 ("Replying router is an egress for the FEC at stack-depth &lt;RSC&gt;"). </t>
          <t>Similarly, an operator at PE3 may initiate an LSP Ping to PE2 with 
   the Target FEC Stack TLV containing the EVPN Inclusive Multicast sub-TLV in the 
   Echo Request packet. The Echo Request packet is sent with 
   the {Transport label(s) to reach PE2, EVPN Inclusive Multicast label = 
   17002, GAL} MPLS label stack and IP ACH Channel header. 
   Once the Echo Request packet reaches PE2, 
   PE2 will use the GAL and the IP ACH Channel header
   to determine if the packet is an IPv4 or IPv6 OAM packet. The processing on PE2 will be similar 
   to that on PE1 as described above. For the success case, PE2 will 
   reply with Return Code 3 ("Replying 
   router is an egress for the FEC at stack-depth &lt;RSC&gt;") as per <xref target="RFC8029" format="default"/>.</t>
          <t>In an Echo Request packet for EVPN, a combination of an EVPN
          Ethernet A-D sub-TLV and the associated MPLS Split Horizon label,
          immediately preceding the GAL in the MPLS label stack, may be used
          to emulate traffic coming from a multihomed site.  The Split Horizon
          label is used by leaf PE(s) attached to the same multihomed site to
          prevent forwarding of packets back to the multihomed site. If the
          behavior on a leaf PE is to not forward the packet to the multihomed
          site on the ESI identified by the EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV because
          of Split Horizon filtering, the PE will reply with Return Code 37 (see <xref target="iana"/>) and drop the BUM packets on the ES corresponding to the ESI received in the EVPN
Ethernet A-D sub-TLV because of the Split Horizon Group filtering.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="p2mp-ptree" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Using P2MP P-Tree</name>
          <t>Both Inclusive P-tree and Aggregate Inclusive P-tree can be used in 
  EVPN or PBB-EVPN networks.</t>
          <t>When using an Inclusive P-tree arrangement, the P2MP P-tree transport 
  label itself is used to identify the L2 service associated with the 
  Inclusive Multicast route. This L2 service could be a Customer 
  Bridge or a Provider Backbone Bridge.</t>
          <t>For an Inclusive P-tree arrangement, when an operator performs a 
  connectivity check for the multicast L2 service, the operator 
  initiates an LSP Ping request with the Target FEC Stack TLV 
  containing the EVPN Inclusive Multicast sub-TLV in the Echo Request 
  packet. The Echo Request packet is sent over P2MP LSP
  with the {P2MP P-tree Transport label, GAL} 
  MPLS label stack and IP ACH Channel header.</t>
          <t>When using an Aggregate Inclusive P-tree arrangement, a PE announces an upstream-assigned MPLS label along with the P-tree ID, so both the 
  P2MP P-tree MPLS transport label and the upstream MPLS label can be 
  used to identify the L2 service.</t>
          <t>For an Aggregate Inclusive P-tree arrangement, when an operator 
  performs a connectivity check for the multicast L2 service, the 
  operator initiates an LSP Ping request with the Target FEC Stack TLV 
  containing the EVPN Inclusive Multicast sub-TLV in the Echo Request 
  packet. The Echo Request packet is sent over P2MP LSP using the 
  IP-ACH Control channel with the {P2MP P-tree Transport label, 
  EVPN upstream-assigned Multicast label, GAL} MPLS label stack and
  IP ACH Channel header.</t>

  <t>The leaf PE(s) of the P2MP P-tree will process the packet and perform 
  checks for the EVPN Inclusive Multicast sub-TLV present in the 
  Target FEC Stack TLV as described in <xref target="RFC8029" sectionFormat="of" section="4.4"/> and 
  respond according to the processing rules in <xref target="RFC8029" format="default"/>. 
  For the success case, the leaf PE will reply with Return Code 3 
  ("Replying router is an egress for the FEC at stack-depth &lt;RSC&gt;").</t>
          <t>In an Echo Request packet for EVPN, a combination of an EVPN
          Ethernet A-D sub-TLV and the associated MPLS Split Horizon label,
          immediately preceding the GAL in the MPLS label stack, may be used
          to emulate traffic coming from a multihomed site.  When using P2MP
          P-tree, the Split Horizon label is upstream assigned and is received
          by all the leaf PEs of the P2MP P-tree. The Split Horizon label is
          used by leaf PE(s) attached to the same multihomed site so that
          packets will not be forwarded back to the multihomed site. If the
          behavior on a leaf PE is to not forward the packet to the multihomed
          site on the ESI in the EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV because of Split
          Horizon filtering, the PE will reply with Return Code 37 (see <xref target="iana"/>) and drop the BUM packets on the ES
corresponding to the ESI received in the EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV
because of the Split Horizon Group filtering.
          
          If the leaf PE does not have the ESI identified in the
          EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV, the PE <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> reply with Return Code 38 (see <xref target="iana"/>), and the BUM packets are forwarded
because there is no ES corresponding to the
ESI received in the EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Controlling Echo Responses When Using P2MP P-Tree</name>
          <t>The procedures described in <xref target="RFC6425"/> for preventing congestion of
   Echo Responses (Echo Jitter TLV) and limiting the Echo Reply to a
   single egress node (P2MP Responder Identifier TLV with either the
   IPv4 Node Address P2MP Responder sub-TLV or the IPv6 Node Address P2MP
   Responder sub-TLV) can
   be applied to LSP Ping in EVPN and PBB-EVPN when using P2MP P-trees
   for BUM traffic.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>EVPN Aliasing Data Plane Connectivity Check</name>
        <t>Assume PE1 announced an Ethernet A-D per-EVI route with the ESI 
   set to CE1 system ID and MPLS label 19001. Additionally, assume PE2 announced an Ethernet A-D per-EVI route 
   with the ESI set to CE1 system ID and MPLS label 19002.</t>
        <t>At PE3, when an operator performs a connectivity check for the 
   aliasing aspect of the EVPN Ethernet A-D route on PE1, the operator 
   initiates an LSP Ping request with the Target FEC Stack TLV 
   containing the EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV in the Echo Request packet. The 
   Echo Request packet is sent with the {Transport label(s) to reach 
   PE1, EVPN Ethernet A-D label 19001, GAL} MPLS label stack and 
   IP ACH Channel header.</t>
        <t>When PE1 receives the packet, it will process the packet and perform 
   checks for the EVPN Ethernet A-D sub-TLV present in the Target FEC 
   Stack TLV as described in <xref target="RFC8029" sectionFormat="of" section="4.4"/> and respond 
   according to the processing rules in <xref target="RFC8029" format="default"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>EVPN IP Prefix (RT-5) Data Plane Connectivity Check</name>
        <t>Assume PE1 in <xref target="fig5"/> announced an IP Prefix route (RT-5) with an IP prefix  
   reachable behind CE1 and MPLS label 20001. When an operator on PE3 performs a 
   connectivity check for the IP prefix on PE1, the operator 
   initiates an LSP Ping request with the Target FEC Stack TLV 
   containing the EVPN IP Prefix sub-TLV in the Echo Request packet. The 
   Echo Request packet is sent with the {Transport label(s) to reach 
   PE1, EVPN IP Prefix label 20001 } MPLS label stack.</t>
        <t>When PE1 receives the packet, it will process the packet and perform 
   checks for the EVPN IP Prefix sub-TLV present in the Target FEC 
   Stack TLV as described in <xref target="RFC8029" sectionFormat="of" section="4.4"/> and respond 
   according to the processing rules in <xref target="RFC8029" format="default"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>  This document does not introduce any new 
           security considerations beyond those that apply in
           <xref target="RFC7432" format="default"/>, 
           <xref target="RFC7623" format="default"/>, and  
           <xref target="RFC6425" format="default"/>.

          Furthermore, the security considerations 
          discussed in <xref target="RFC8029" format="default"/> apply to this document and need to be 
          considered. As described in <xref target="RFC8029" format="default"/>, these security considerations 
          are:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>A Denial-of-Service (DoS) attack by sending MPLS Echo 
                Requests/Replies to Label Switching Routers (LSRs) and thereby increasing their workload.</li>
        <li>Obfuscating the state of the MPLS data plane liveness by spoofing, 
                 hijacking, replaying, or otherwise tampering with MPLS Echo Requests 
                 and Replies.</li>
        <li>Obtaining information about the network through an unauthorized source 
                using an LSP Ping.</li>
      </ul>
      <t> There are mitigations described in <xref target="RFC8029" format="default"/>.  The same mitigations  
            can be applied to the LSP Ping procedures described in this document; thus, this document 
            doesn't require additional security considerations beyond the ones described 
            in <xref target="RFC8029" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t> This document does not introduce any new privacy concerns because these TLVs contain the same information that are present in data packets and EVPN routes. 
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Sub-TLV Type</name>
        <t>   This document defines four new sub-TLV types to be included in the Target 
   FEC Stack TLV (TLV types 1, 16, and 21) <xref target="RFC9041" format="default"/> in Echo Request and Echo 
   Reply messages in EVPN and PBB-EVPN networks.</t>
        <t>IANA has assigned the following values
        from the "Standards Action" (0-16383) range in the "Sub-TLVs for TLV
        Types 1, 16, and 21" subregistry within the "TLVs" registry of the
        "Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) Label Switched Paths (LSPs)
        Ping Parameters" name space. </t>

<table anchor="iana1">
  <name></name>    
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Sub-Type</th>    
      <th>Sub-TLV Name</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>          
    <tr>
      <td>42</td>
      <td>EVPN MAC/IP</td>
      <td>RFC 9489</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>43</td>
      <td>EVPN Inclusive Multicast</td>
      <td>RFC 9489</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>44</td>
      <td>EVPN Ethernet Auto-Discovery</td>
      <td>RFC 9489</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>45</td>
      <td>EVPN IP Prefix</td>
      <td>RFC 9489</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
	
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>New Return Codes</name>
        <t><xref target="RFC8029" format="default"/> defines values for the Return Code field of Echo Reply messages. 
   This document defines two new Return Codes that <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be 
   included in the Echo Reply message by a PE in response to  
   an Echo Request message in EVPN and PBB-EVPN networks. </t>
        <t> IANA has assigned the following values in the "Return Codes"
        registry of the "Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) Label Switched
        Paths (LSPs) Ping Parameters" name space.</t>

<table anchor="iana2">
  <name></name>    
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Value</th>    
      <th>Meaning</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>          
    <tr>
      <td>37</td>
      <td>Replying router is egress for the FEC at the stack depth. In
      addition, the BUM packets are dropped on the ES corresponding to the ESI
      received in the EVPN Ethernet Auto-Discovery sub-TLV because of the Split Horizon Group
      filtering.</td>
      <td>RFC 9489</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>38</td>
      <td>Replying router is egress for the FEC at the stack depth. In
      addition, the BUM packets are forwarded because there is no ES
      corresponding to the ESI received in the EVPN Ethernet Auto-Discovery sub-TLV.</td>
      <td>RFC 9489</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4760.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7623.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8029.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6425.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5586.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7432.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9136.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8214.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9041.xml"/>
    </references>
    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>The authors would like to thank <contact fullname="Loa Andersson"/>,
      <contact fullname="Alexander Vainshtein"/>, <contact fullname="Ron
      Sdayoor"/>, <contact fullname="Jim Guichard"/>, <contact fullname="Lars
      Eggert"/>, <contact fullname="John Scudder"/>, <contact fullname="Éric
      Vyncke"/>, <contact fullname="Warren Kumari"/>, <contact
      fullname="Patrice Brissette"/>, and <contact fullname="Weiguo Hao"/> for
      their valuable comments.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
