<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="true" docName="draft-ietf-lamps-nf-eku-05" number="9509" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="3" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="EKUs for 5G Network Functions">X.509 Certificate Extended Key Usage (EKU)
    for 5G Network Functions</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9509"/>
    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy.K" initials="T." surname="Reddy.K">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>kondtir@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Jani Ekman" initials="J." surname="Ekman">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jani.ekman@nokia.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Daniel Migault" initials="D." surname="Migault">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>daniel.migault@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2024" month="March"/>
    <area>sec</area>
    <workgroup>lamps</workgroup>
    <keyword>3GPP</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>RFC 5280 specifies several extended key purpose identifiers
      (KeyPurposeIds) for X.509 certificates. This document defines encrypting
      JSON objects in HTTP messages, using JSON Web Tokens (JWTs), and signing
      the OAuth 2.0 access tokens KeyPurposeIds for inclusion in the Extended
      Key Usage (EKU) extension of X.509 v3 public key certificates used by
      Network Functions (NFs) for the 5G System.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>The operators of 5G ("fifth generation") systems as defined by 3GPP
      make use of an internal PKI to generate X.509 PKI certificates for the
      Network Functions (NFs) (Section 6 of <xref target="TS23.501"
      format="default"/>) in a 5G System. The certificates are used for the
      following purposes:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>Client and Server certificates for NFs in 5G Core (5GC) Service Based
        Architecture (SBA) (see Section 6.1.3c of <xref target="TS33.310"
        format="default"/> and Section 6.7.2 of <xref target="TS29.500"
	format="default"/>)</li>
        <li>Client Credentials Assertion (CCA) uses JSON Web Tokens (JWTs)
        <xref target="RFC7519" format="default"/> and is secured with digital
        signatures based on the JSON Web Signature (JWS) <xref
        target="RFC7515" format="default"/> (see Section 13.3.8.2 of <xref
        target="TS33.501" format="default"/>, and Section 6.7.5 of <xref
        target="TS29.500" format="default"/>).</li>
        <li>Certificates for encrypting JSON objects in HTTP messages between
        Security Edge Protection Proxies (SEPPs) using JSON Web Encryption
        (JWE) <xref target="RFC7516" format="default"/> (see Section 13.2.4.4
        of <xref target="TS33.501" format="default"/>, Section 6.3.2 of <xref
        target="TS33.210" format="default"/>, Section 6.7.4 of <xref
        target="TS29.500" format="default"/>, and Section 5.3.2.1 of <xref
        target="TS29.573" format="default"/>).</li>
        <li>Certificates for signing the OAuth 2.0 access tokens for service
        authorization to grant temporary access to resources provided by NF
        producers using JWS (see Section 13.4.1 of <xref target="TS33.501"
        format="default"/> and Section 6.7.3 of <xref target="TS29.500"
        format="default"/>).</li>
      </ul>
      <t><xref target="RFC5280" format="default"/> specifies several key usage
      extensions, defined via KeyPurposeIds, for X.509 certificates. Key usage
      extensions added to a certificate are meant to express intent as to the
      purpose of the named usage, for humans and for complying libraries. In
      addition, the IANA registry "SMI Security for PKIX Extended Key Purpose"
      <xref target="RFC7299" format="default"/> contains additional
      KeyPurposeIds. The use of the anyExtendedKeyUsage KeyPurposeId, as
      defined in <xref target="RFC5280" sectionFormat="of"
      section="4.2.1.12"/>, is generally considered a poor practice. This is
      especially true for publicly trusted certificates, whether they are
      multi-purpose or single-purpose, within the context of 5G Systems and
      the 5GC Service Based Architecture.</t>
      <t>If the purpose of the issued certificates is not restricted, i.e.,
      the type of operations for which a public key contained in the
      certificate can be used are not specified, those certificates could be
      used for another purpose than intended, increasing the risk of
      cross-protocol attacks. Failure to ensure proper segregation of duties
      means that a NF that generates the public/private keys and applies for a
      certificate to the operator certification authority could obtain a
      certificate that can be misused for tasks that this NF is not entitled
      to perform. For example, a NF service consumer could potentially
      impersonate NF service producers using its certificate. Additionally, in
      cases where the certificate's purpose is intended for use by the NF
      service consumer as a client certificate, it's essential to ensure that
      the NF with this client certificate and the corresponding private key
      are not allowed to sign the Client Credentials Assertion (CCA). When a
      NF service producer receives the signed CCA from the NF service
      consumer, the NF should only accept the token if the CCA is signed with
      a certificate that has been explicitly issued for this purpose.</t>
      <t>The KeyPurposeId id-kp-serverAuth (<xref target="RFC5280"
      sectionFormat="of" section="4.2.1.12"/>) can be used to identify that
      the certificate is for a server (e.g., NF service producer), and the
      KeyPurposeId id-kp-clientAuth (<xref target="RFC5280"
      sectionFormat="of" section="4.2.1.12"/>) can be used to identify that
      the certificate is for a client (e.g., NF service consumer). However,
      there are currently no KeyPurposeIds for the other usages of
      certificates in a 5G System. This document addresses the above problem by
      defining the EKU extension of X.509 public key certificates for signing
      the JWT Claims Set using JWS, encrypting JSON objects in HTTP messages
      using JWE, and signing the OAuth 2.0 access tokens using JWS.</t>
      <t>Vendor-defined KeyPurposeIds used within a PKI governed by the vendor
      or a group of vendors typically do not pose interoperability concerns,
      as non-critical extensions can be safely ignored if unrecognized.
      However, using or misusing KeyPurposeIds outside of their intended
      vendor-controlled environment can lead to interoperability issues.
      Therefore, it is advisable not to rely on vendor-defined KeyPurposeIds.
      Instead, the specification defines standard KeyPurposeIds to ensure
      interoperability across various implementations.</t>
      <t>Although the specification focuses on a 5G use case, the standard
      KeyPurposeIds defined in this document can be used in other
      deployments.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="notation" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>
        <t> The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
        NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document
        are to be interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref
        target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they
        appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Extended Key Purpose for Network Functions</name>
      <t>This specification defines the KeyPurposeIds id-kp-jwt,
      id-kp-httpContentEncrypt, and id-kp-oauthAccessTokenSigning
      and uses these, respectively, for: signing the JWT Claims Set
      of CCA using JWS, encrypting JSON objects in HTTP messages between
      Security Edge Protection Proxies (SEPPs) using JWE, and signing the
      OAuth 2.0 access tokens for service authorization to grant temporary
      access to resources provided by NF producers using JWS. As described in
      <xref target="RFC5280" format="default"/>, "[i]f the [Extended Key
      Usage] extension is present, then the certificate <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
      only be used for one of the purposes indicated." <xref target="RFC5280"
      format="default"/> also notes that "[i]f multiple [key] purposes are
      indicated the application need not recognize all purposes indicated, as
      long as the intended purpose is present."</t>
      <t>Network Functions that verify the signature of a CCA represented as a
      JWT, decrypt JSON objects in HTTP messages between Security Edge
      Protection Proxies (SEPPs) using JWE, or verify the signature of an
      OAuth 2.0 access tokens for service authorization to grant temporary
      access to resources provided by NF producers using JWS
      <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> require that corresponding
      KeyPurposeIds be specified by the EKU extension. If the certificate requester knows
      the certificate users are mandated to use these KeyPurposeIds, it
      <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> enforce their inclusion. Additionally, such
      a certificate requester <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ensure that the KeyUsage
      extension be set to digitalSignature or nonRepudiation (also designated
      as contentCommitment) for signature calculation and/or to
      keyEncipherment for secret key encryption.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default" anchor="purpose-in-certificates">
      <name>Including the Extended Key Purpose in Certificates</name>
      <t><xref target="RFC5280" format="default"/> specifies the EKU X.509
      certificate extension for use on end entity certificates. The extension
      indicates one or more purposes for which the certified public key is
      valid. The EKU extension can be used in conjunction with the key usage
      extension, which indicates the set of basic cryptographic operations for
      which the certified key may be used. The EKU extension syntax is
      repeated here for convenience:</t>

      <sourcecode type="asn.1"><![CDATA[
ExtKeyUsageSyntax ::= SEQUENCE SIZE (1..MAX) OF KeyPurposeId 

KeyPurposeId ::= OBJECT IDENTIFIER 
]]></sourcecode>

      <t>As described in <xref target="RFC5280" format="default"/>, the EKU
      extension may, at the option of the certificate issuer, be either
      critical or non-critical. The inclusion of KeyPurposeIds id-kp-jwt,
      id-kp-httpContentEncrypt, and id-kp-oauthAccessTokenSigning in a
      certificate indicates that the public key encoded in the certificate has
      been certified for use in the following: </t>

      <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
	<li>Validating the JWS Signature in JWT. The distinction between JWS
	and JWE is determined by the Key Usage (KU) that is set to
	digitalSignature or nonRepudiation for JWS and keyEncipherment for
	JWE.</li>
        <li>Encrypting JSON objects in HTTP messages (for example, encrypting
        the content-encryption key (CEK) with the recipient's public key using
        the RSAES-OAEP algorithm to produce the JWE Encrypted Key). KU is set
        to keyEncipherment.</li>
        <li>Signing OAuth 2.0 access tokens. In this case, KU is set to
        digitalSignature or nonRepudiation.</li>
      </ol>
      <sourcecode type="asn.1"><![CDATA[
     id-kp  OBJECT IDENTIFIER  ::= {
       iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1)
       security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) kp(3) }

id-kp-jwt OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 37 }
id-kp-httpContentEncrypt OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 38 }
id-kp-oauthAccessTokenSigning OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 39 }
]]></sourcecode>
    </section>
    <section anchor="solution" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Implications for a Certification Authority</name>
      <t>The procedures and practices employed by a certification authority
      <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ensure that the correct values for the EKU extension as well as the
      KU extension are inserted in each certificate that is issued. The
      inclusion of the id-kp-jwt, id-kp-httpContentEncrypt, and
      id-kp-oauthAccessTokenSigning KeyPurposeIds does not preclude the
      inclusion of other KeyPurposeIds.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The Security Considerations of <xref target="RFC5280"
      format="default"/> are applicable to this document. This extended key
      purpose does not introduce new security risks but instead reduces
      existing security risks by providing the means to identify if the
      certificate is generated to sign the JWT Claims Set, signing the OAuth
      2.0 access tokens using JWS, or encrypting the CEK in JWE for encrypting
      JSON objects in HTTP messages.</t>
      <t>To reduce the risk of specific cross-protocol attacks, the relying
      party or the relying party software may additionally prohibit use of
      specific combinations of KeyPurposeIds. The procedure for allowing or
      disallowing combinations of KeyPurposeIds using Excluded KeyPurposeId
      and Permitted KeyPurposeId, as carried out by a relying party, is
      defined in <xref target="RFC9336" sectionFormat="of"
      section="4"/>. Examples of Excluded KeyPurposeIds include the presence of
      the anyExtendedKeyUsage KeyPurposeId or the complete absence of the EKU
      extension in a certificate. Examples of Permitted KeyPurposeIds include
      the presence of id-kp-jwt, id-kp-httpContentEncrypt, or
      id-kp-oauthAccessTokenSigning KeyPurposeIds.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Privacy" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Privacy Considerations</name>
      <t>In some security protocols, such as TLS 1.2 <xref target="RFC5246"
      format="default"/>, certificates are exchanged in the clear. In other
      security protocols, such as TLS 1.3 <xref target="RFC8446"
      format="default"/>, the certificates are encrypted. The inclusion of the
      EKU extension can help an observer determine the purpose of the
      certificate. In addition, if the certificate is issued by a public
      certification authority, the inclusion of an EKU extension can help an
      attacker to monitor the Certificate Transparency logs <xref
      target="RFC9162" format="default"/> to identify the purpose of the
      certificate.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">

      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>IANA has registered the following OIDs in the "SMI Security
      for PKIX Extended Key Purpose" registry (1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3). These OIDs
      are defined in <xref target="purpose-in-certificates"/>.</t>

      <table anchor="iana-table-1" align="left">
	<thead>
	  <tr>
	    <th>Decimal</th>
	    <th>Description</th>
	    <th>References</th>
	  </tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <tr>
	    <td>37</td>
	    <td>id-kp-jwt</td>
	    <td>RFC 9509</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td>38</td>
	    <td>id-kp-httpContentEncrypt</td>
	    <td>RFC 9509</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td>39</td>
	    <td>id-kp-oauthAccessTokenSigning</td>
	    <td>RFC 9509</td>
	  </tr>
	</tbody>
      </table>

      <t>IANA has registered the following ASN.1<xref
      target="X.680" format="default"/> module OID in the "SMI Security for PKIX Module Identifier" registry (1.3.6.1.5.5.7.0). This OID is defined
      in <xref target="Appendix" format="default"/>.</t>

      <table anchor="iana-table-2" align="left">
	<thead>
	  <tr>
	    <th>Decimal</th>
	    <th>Description</th>
	    <th>References</th>
	  </tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <tr>
	    <td>108</td>
	    <td>id-mod-nf-eku</td>
	    <td>RFC 9509</td>
	  </tr>
	</tbody>
      </table>
    </section>


  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7515.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7519.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7516.xml"/>

      <reference anchor="X.680" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-X.680">
          <front>
            <title>Information technology - Abstract Syntax Notation One
            (ASN.1): Specification of basic notation</title>
            <author>
              <organization>ITU-T</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="February" year="2021"/>
          </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="ITU-T Recommendation" value="X.680"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="X.690" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-X.690">
          <front>
            <title>Information technology - ASN.1 encoding rules:
            Specification of Basic Encoding Rules (BER), Canonical Encoding
            Rules (CER) and Distinguished Encoding Rules (DER)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>ITU-T</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="February" year="2021"/>
          </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="ITU-T Recommendation" value="X.690"/>
        </reference>

      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7299.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9336.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9162.xml"/>

      <reference anchor="TS29.573" target="https://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/archive/29_series/29.573/29573-i50.zip">
	<front>
	  <title>5G System; Public Land Mobile Network (PLMN) Interconnection; Stage 3</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>3GPP</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date month="December" year="2023"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Release" value="18.5.0"/>
	<seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.573"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS33.501" target="https://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/archive/33_series/33.501/33501-i40.zip">
          <front>
            <title>Security architecture and procedures for 5G system</title>
            <author>
              <organization>3GPP</organization>
            </author>
            <date  month="December" year="2023"/>
          </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="Release" value="18.4.0"/>
	  <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="33.501"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="TS33.310" target="https://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/archive/33_series/33.310/33310-i20.zip">
          <front>
            <title>Network Domain Security (NDS); Authentication Framework
            (AF)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>3GPP</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="December" year="2023"/>
          </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="Release" value="18.2.0"/>
	  <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="33.310"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="TS33.210" target="https://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/archive/33_series/33.210/33210-h10.zip">
          <front>
            <title>Network Domain Security (NDS); IP network layer
            security</title>
            <author>
              <organization>3GPP</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="September" year="2022"/>
          </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="Release" value="17.1.0"/>
	  <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="33.210"/>
        </reference>


        <reference anchor="TS23.501" target="https://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/archive/23_series/23.501/23501-i40.zip">
          <front>
            <title>System architecture for the 5G System (5GS)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>3GPP</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="December" year="2023"/>
          </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="Release" value="18.4.0"/>
	  <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="23.501"/>
        </reference>

	<reference anchor="TS29.500" target="https://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/archive/29_series/29.500/29500-i40.zip">
	  <front>
	    <title>5G System; Technical Realization of Service Based Architecture; Stage 3</title>
	    <author>
	      <organization>3GPP</organization>
	    </author>
	    <date month="December" year="2023"/>
	  </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="Release" value="18.4.0"/>
	  <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="29.500"/>
	</reference>

      </references>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Appendix" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>ASN.1 Module</name>
      <t>The following module adheres to ASN.1 specifications <xref target="X.680" format="default"/> and <xref target="X.690" format="default"/>.</t>
      <sourcecode name="" type="asn.1" markers="true"><![CDATA[
NF-EKU
  { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1)
  security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) id-mod(0)
  id-mod-nf-eku (108) }

DEFINITIONS IMPLICIT TAGS ::=
BEGIN

-- OID Arc

id-kp OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::=
  { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1)
    security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) kp(3) }

-- Extended Key Usage Values

id-kp-jwt OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 37 }
id-kp-httpContentEncrypt OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 38 }
id-kp-oauthAccessTokenSigning OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 39 }

END
]]></sourcecode>

</section>

    <section anchor="acknowledgments" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>We would like to thank <contact fullname="Corey Bonnell"/>, <contact
      fullname="Ilari Liusvaara"/>, <contact fullname="Carl Wallace"/>, and
      <contact fullname="Russ Housley"/> for their useful feedback. Thanks to
      <contact fullname="Yoav Nir"/> for the secdir review, <contact
      fullname="Elwyn Davies"/> for the genart review, and <contact
      fullname="Benson Muite"/> for the intdir review.</t>
      <t>Thanks to <contact fullname="Paul Wouters"/>, <contact fullname="Lars
      Eggert"/>, and <contact fullname="Éric Vyncke"/> for the IESG
      review.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="contrib" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Contributor</name>
      <t>The following individual has contributed to this document:</t>      
      <contact fullname="German Peinado">
	<organization>Nokia</organization>
	<address>
	  <email>german.peinado@nokia.com</email>
	</address>
      </contact>
    </section>

  </back>

</rfc>
