<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>


<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="info" docName="draft-ietf-6man-sids-06" number="9602" consensus="true" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="4" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">

  <front>


    
    <title abbrev="SRv6 SIDs">Segment Routing over IPv6 (SRv6) Segment Identifiers in the IPv6 Addressing Architecture</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9602"/>
    <author fullname="Suresh Krishnan" initials="S." surname="Krishnan">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <email>suresh.krishnan@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2024"/>

    <area>INT</area>
    <workgroup>6man</workgroup>


    <abstract>
      <t>   Segment Routing over IPv6 (SRv6) uses IPv6 as the
   underlying data plane. Thus, Segment Identifiers (SIDs) used by SRv6 can resemble IPv6
      addresses and behave like them while exhibiting slightly different
      behaviors in some situations. This document explores the characteristics
      of SRv6 SIDs and focuses on the relationship of SRv6 SIDs to the IPv6
      Addressing Architecture. This document allocates and makes a dedicated
      prefix available for SRv6 SIDs.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
      Segment Routing over IPv6 (SRv6) <xref target="RFC8754" format="default"/> uses IPv6 as the underlying data plane. In SRv6, SR source nodes initiate packets with a Segment Identifier (SID) in the Destination Address of the IPv6 header, and SR segment endpoint nodes process a local segment present in the Destination Address of an IPv6 header. Thus, SIDs in SRv6 can, and do, appear in the Destination Address of IPv6 datagrams by design. This document explores the characteristics of SRv6 SIDs and focuses on the relationship of SRv6 SIDs to the IPv6 Addressing Architecture <xref target="RFC4291" format="default"/>. This document allocates and makes a dedicated prefix available for SRv6 SIDs.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref target="RFC8402" format="default"/>. 
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t>Segment Routing (SR)</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>SR Domain</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Segment</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Segment Identifier (SID)</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>SRv6</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>SRv6 SID</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref target="RFC8754" format="default"/>. 
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t>Segment Routing Header (SRH)</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>SR Source Node</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Transit Node</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>SR Segment Endpoint Node</t>
        </li>
      </ul>


        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be
    interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref
    target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as
    shown here.
        </t>

    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default" anchor="section3">
      <name>SRv6 SIDs and the IPv6 Addressing Architecture</name>
      <t>
      <xref target="RFC8754" format="default"/> defines the Segment List of the SRH as a contiguous array of 128-bit IPv6 addresses; further, it states that  each of the elements in this list are SIDs. But all of these elements are not necessarily made equal. Some of these elements may represent a local interface as described in <xref target="RFC8754" sectionFormat="of" section="4.3"/> as "A FIB entry that represents a local interface, not locally instantiated as an SRv6 SID". It follows that not all the SIDs that appear in the SRH are SRv6 SIDs as defined by <xref target="RFC8402" format="default"/>. 
      </t>
      <t>
   As stated above, the non-SRv6-SID elements that appear in
   the SRH SID list are simply IPv6 addresses assigned to local
   interfaces, and they need to conform to <xref target="RFC4291" format="default"/>. So, the following discussions are applicable solely to SRv6 SIDs that are not assigned to local interfaces.
      </t>
      <t>
      One of the key questions to address is how these SRv6 SIDs appearing as IPv6 Destination Addresses are perceived and treated by "transit nodes" (that are not required to be capable of processing a Segment or the Segment Routing Header). 
      </t>
      <t>
      <xref target="RFC8986" sectionFormat="of" section="3.1"/> describes the format of an SRv6 SID as being composed of three parts, LOC:FUNCT:ARG, where a locator (LOC) is encoded in the L most significant bits of the SID followed by F bits of function (FUNCT) and A bits of arguments (ARG). If L+F+A &lt; 128,
      the ARG is followed by enough zero bits to fill the 128-bit SID. Such an SRv6 SID is assigned to a node within a prefix defined as a Locator of length L.  When an SRv6 SID occurs in the IPv6 Destination Address of an IPv6 header, only the longest matching prefix corresponding to the Locator <xref target="BCP198" format="default"/> is used by the transit node to forward the packet to the node identified by the Locator.   
      </t>
      <t>
	It is clear that this format for SRv6 SIDs is not compliant with the requirements set forth in <xref target="RFC4291" format="default"/> for IPv6 addresses, but it is also clear that SRv6 SIDs are not intended for assignment onto interfaces on end hosts.


They look and act like other mechanisms that use IPv6 addresses with
different formats, such as those described in "<xref target="RFC6052" format="title"/>" <xref target="RFC6052" format="default"/> and "<xref target="RFC7343" format="title"/>" <xref target="RFC7343" format="default"/>. 
      </t>
      <t>
        While looking at the transit nodes, it becomes apparent that these
        addresses are used purely for forwarding and not
        for packet delivery to end hosts.
        Hence, the relevant specification to apply here is <xref target="BCP198" format="default"/>, which requires implementations to support the use of variable-length prefixes in forwarding while explicitly decoupling IPv6 routing and forwarding from the IPv6 address/prefix semantics described in <xref target="RFC4291" format="default"/>. Please note that <xref target="BCP198" format="default"/> does not override the rules in <xref target="RFC4291" format="default"/>: it merely limits where their impact is observed.
      </t>
      <t>
      Furthermore, in the SRv6 specifications, all SIDs assigned within a given Locator prefix are located inside the node identified by Locator.  Therefore, there does not appear to be a conflict with <xref target="RFC4291" sectionFormat="of" section="2.6.1"/> since subnet-router anycast addresses are neither required nor useful within a node.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Special Considerations for Compressed SIDs</name>
      <t>

	
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-spring-srv6-srh-compression" format="default"/> introduces an encoding for
  Compressed-SIDs (C-SIDs), and describes how to use a single entry in the Segment List as a container for multiple SIDs. A node taking part in this mechanism accomplishes this by using the ARG part <xref target="RFC8986" format="default"/> of the Destination Address of the IPv6 header to derive a new Destination Address. That is, the Destination Address field of the packet changes at a segment endpoint in a way similar to how the address changes as the result of processing a segment in the SRH. 
      </t>
      <t>
      One key thing to note here is that the Locator Block at the beginning of the address does not get modified by the operations needed for supporting C-SIDs. As we have established that the SRv6 SIDs are being treated simply as routing prefixes on transit nodes within the SR Domain, this does not constitute a modification to the IPv6 data plane on such transit nodes: any changes are restricted to SR-aware nodes.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default" anchor="section5">
      <name>Allocation of a Prefix for SIDs</name>
      <t>All of the SRv6-related specifications discussed above are intended to be applicable to a contained SR Domain or between collaborating SR Domains. Nodes either inside or outside the SR Domains that are not SR-aware
will not perform any special behavior for SRv6 SIDs and will treat
them solely as IPv6 routing prefixes.  
      </t>
      <t>
      As an added factor of security, it is desirable to allocate some address space that explicitly signals that the addresses within that space cannot be expected to comply with <xref target="RFC4291" format="default"/>. As described in <xref target="section3"/>, there is precedent for mechanisms that use IPv6 addresses in a manner different from that specified in <xref target="RFC4291" format="default"/>. This would be useful in identifying and potentially filtering packets at the edges of the SR Domains to make it simpler for the SR Domain to fail closed.
      </t>
      <t>
      At the time of writing, global DNS <xref target="RFC9499" format="default"/> <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> reference addresses assigned from this block. Further specifications are needed to describe the conventions and guidelines for the use of this newly allocated address block. The SRv6 operational community, which is the first intended user of this block, is requested to come up with such conventions and guidelines in line with their requirements. 
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>

      
      <t>IANA has assigned the following /16 address block for the purposes described in <xref target="section5"/> and recorded the allocation in the "IANA IPv6 Special-Purpose Address Registry" <xref target="SPECIAL"/> as follows:
      </t>
<dl newline="true">
    <dt>Address Block:</dt>  <dd>5f00::/16</dd>
    <dt>Name:</dt><dd>Segment Routing (SRv6) SIDs</dd>
    <dt>RFC:</dt> <dd>RFC 9602</dd>
    <dt>Allocation Date:</dt> <dd>2024-04</dd>
    <dt>Termination Date:</dt> <dd>N/A</dd>
    <dt>Source:</dt> <dd>True</dd>
    <dt>Destination:</dt> <dd>True</dd>
    <dt>Forwardable:</dt> <dd>True</dd>
    <dt>Globally Reachable:</dt> <dd>False</dd>
    <dt>Reserved-by-Protocol:</dt> <dd>False</dd></dl>


    
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The security considerations for the use of Segment Routing <xref target="RFC8402" format="default"/>, SRv6 <xref target="RFC8754" format="default"/>, and SRv6 network programming <xref target="RFC8986" format="default"/> 
      apply to the use of these addresses. The use of IPv6 tunneling mechanisms (including SRv6) also 
      brings up additional concerns such as those described in <xref target="RFC6169" format="default"/>. The usage of the prefix allocated by this document improves security by making it simpler to filter traffic at the edge of the SR Domains.
      </t>
      <t>
      In case the deployments do not use this allocated prefix, additional care needs to be exercised at network ingress and egress points so that SRv6 packets do not leak out of SR Domains and do not accidentally enter SR-unaware Domains. Similarly, as stated in <xref target="RFC8754" sectionFormat="of" section="5.1"/>, the SR Domain needs to be configured to filter out  packets entering that use the selected prefix.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>

    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-spring-srv6-srh-compression" to="CSID"/>

    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4291.xml"/>

<referencegroup anchor="BCP198" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/bcp198">
  <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7608.xml"/>
</referencegroup>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8402.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8754.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8986.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6052.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6169.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7343.xml"/>

<!-- [I-D.ietf-spring-srv6-srh-compression] IESG state: I-D Exists as of 04/17/24 -->
        <xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/draft-ietf-spring-srv6-srh-compression.xml"/>


        <reference anchor="SPECIAL" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/iana-ipv6-special-registry">
          <front>
            <title>IANA IPv6 Special-Purpose Address Registry</title>
            <author fullname="IANA"/>
          </front>
        </reference>



        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9499.xml"/>

      </references>
    </references>
   <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>The author would like to extend a special note of thanks to <contact fullname="Brian Carpenter"/> and  <contact fullname="Erik Kline"/> for their precisely summarized thoughts 
      on this topic that provided the seed of this document. The author would also like to thank  <contact fullname="Andrew Alston"/>, <contact fullname="Fred Baker"/>, <contact fullname="Ron Bonica"/>, <contact fullname="Nick Buraglio"/>, <contact fullname="Bruno Decraene"/>, <contact fullname="Dhruv Dhody"/>, <contact fullname="Darren Dukes"/>, <contact fullname="Linda Dunbar"/>, <contact fullname="Reese Enghardt"/>, <contact fullname="Adrian Farrel"/>, <contact fullname="Clarence Filsfils"/>, <contact fullname="Jim Guichard"/>, <contact fullname="Joel Halpern"/>, <contact fullname="Ted Hardie"/>, <contact fullname="Bob Hinden"/>, <contact fullname="Murray Kucherawy"/>, <contact fullname="Cheng Li"/>, <contact fullname="Acee Lindem"/>, <contact fullname="Jen Linkova"/>, <contact fullname="Gyan Mishra"/>, <contact fullname="Yingzhen Qu"/>, <contact fullname="Robert Raszuk"/>, <contact fullname="Alvaro Retana"/>, <contact fullname="Michael Richardson"/>, <contact fullname="John Scudder"/>, <contact fullname="Petr Spacek"/>, <contact fullname="Mark Smith"/>, <contact fullname="Dirk Steinberg"/>, <contact fullname="Ole Troan"/>, <contact fullname="Eduard Vasilenko"/>, <contact fullname="Éric Vyncke"/>, <contact fullname="Rob Wilton"/>, <contact fullname="Jingrong Xie"/>, <contact fullname="Chongfeng Xie"/>, and  <contact fullname="Juan Carlos Zuniga"/> for their ideas and comments to improve this document. 
      </t>
   </section>    
  </back>
</rfc>
