<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="true" docName="draft-ietf-pce-vn-association-11" number="9358" ipr="trust200902"
obsoletes="" updates="" xml:lang="en" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" tocInclude="true" version="3">

  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.15.1 -->
  <!-- Generated by id2xml 1.5.0 on 2020-01-02T21:47:46Z -->
    <front>

    <title abbrev="PCEP VN Association">Path Computation Element Communication
    Protocol (PCEP) Extensions for Establishing Relationships between Sets of
    Label Switched Paths and Virtual Networks</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9358"/>
    <author fullname="Young Lee" initials="Y." surname="Lee">
      <organization>Samsung Electronics</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Seoul</city>
          <region/>
          <code/>
          <country>Republic of Korea</country>
        </postal>
        <email>younglee.tx@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="H." surname="Zheng" fullname="Haomian Zheng">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
	  <street>H1, Huawei Xiliu Beipo Village Songshan Lake</street>
          <city>Dongguan</city>
          <region>Guangdong</region>
          <code>523808</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>zhenghaomian@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Ceccarelli" fullname="Daniele Ceccarelli">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Torshamnsgatan,48</street>
          <city>Stockholm</city>
          <region/>
          <code/>
          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>
        <email>daniele.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2023" month="February"/>
    <area>rtg</area>
    <workgroup>pce</workgroup>

    <abstract>

<t> This document describes how to extend the Path Computation Element
Communication Protocol (PCEP) association mechanism introduced by RFC 8697 to
further associate sets of Label Switched Paths (LSPs) with a higher-level
structure such as a Virtual Network (VN) requested by a customer or
application.  This extended association mechanism can be used to facilitate
control of a VN using the PCE architecture.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="sect-1" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t> The Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP) provides mechanisms for Path Computation Elements (PCEs) to perform path computations in response to requests from Path Computation Clients (PCCs) <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/>. </t>
      <t> <xref target="RFC8051" format="default"/> describes general considerations for a stateful PCE deployment and examines its applicability and benefits as well as its challenges and limitations through a number of use cases. <xref target="RFC8231" format="default"/> describes a set of extensions to PCEP to provide stateful control. For its computations, a stateful PCE has access to not only the information carried by the network's Interior Gateway Protocol (IGP) but also the set of active paths and their reserved resources.  The additional state allows the PCE to compute constrained paths while considering individual Label Switched Paths (LSPs) and their interactions. </t>
      <t> <xref target="RFC8281" format="default"/> describes the setup, maintenance, and teardown of PCE-initiated LSPs under the stateful PCE model. </t>
      <t> <xref target="RFC8697" format="default"/> introduces a generic mechanism to create a grouping of LSPs. This grouping can then be used to define associations between sets of LSPs or between a set of LSPs and a set of attributes. </t>
      <t> <xref target="RFC8453" format="default"/> introduces a framework for Abstraction and Control of TE Networks (ACTN) and describes various VN operations initiated by a customer or application.  A VN is a customer view of the TE network.  Depending on the agreement between client and provider, various VN operations and VN views are possible. </t>

<t> <xref target="RFC8637" format="default"/> examines the PCE and ACTN architectures and describes how the PCE architecture is applicable to ACTN.  <xref target="RFC6805" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC8751" format="default"/> describe a hierarchy of stateful PCEs with the parent PCE coordinating multi-domain path computation functions between child PCEs, thus making it the base for PCE applicability for ACTN.  As <xref target="RFC8751" format="default"/> explains, in the context of ACTN, the child PCE is identified with the Provisioning Network Controller (PNC), and the parent PCE is identified with the Multi-Domain Service Coordinator (MDSC).</t>

      <t> In this context, there is a need to associate a set of LSPs with a VN "construct" to facilitate VN operations in the PCE architecture.  This association allows a PCE to identify which LSPs belong to a certain VN.  The PCE could then use this association to optimize all LSPs belonging to the VN at once.  The PCE could further take VN-specific actions on the LSPs, such as relaxing constraints, taking policy actions, setting default behavior, etc. </t>
      <t> This document specifies a PCEP extension to associate a set of LSPs based on their VN.  </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-2" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>
<t>This document uses terminology from <xref target="RFC4655" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC6805" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC8231" format="default"/>, and <xref target="RFC8453" format="default"/>. </t>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are
    to be interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
    <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals,
    as shown here.
	</t>

    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-3" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Operation Overview</name>
      <t>As per <xref target="RFC8697" format="default"/>, LSPs are associated with other LSPs with which they interact by adding them to a common association group. </t>
      <t>An association group based on VN is useful for various optimizations that should be applied by considering all the LSPs in the association. This includes, but is not limited to, the following:</t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>Path Computation:</dt>
	<dd>When computing a path for an LSP, it is useful to analyze the
	impact of this LSP on the other LSPs belonging to the same VN.  The
	aim would be to optimize all LSPs belonging to the VN rather than a
	single LSP.  Also, the optimization criteria (such as minimizing the
	load of the most loaded link (MLL) <xref target="RFC5541"
	format="default"/>) could be applied for all the LSPs belonging to the
	VN identified by the VN association. </dd>
        <dt>Path Reoptimization:</dt>
	<dd>The PCE would like to use advanced path computation algorithms and
	optimization techniques that consider all the LSPs belonging to a VN
	and optimize them all together during the path reoptimization. </dd>
      </dl>
      <t>In this document, we define a new association group called the "VN Association Group (VNAG)".  This grouping is used to define the association between a set of LSPs and a VN. </t>
      <t> The ASSOCIATION object contains a field to identify the type of association, and this document defines a new Association Type value of 7 to indicate that the association is a "VN Association".  The Association Identifier in the ASSOCIATION object is the VNAG Identifier and is handled in the same way as the generic Association Identifier defined in <xref target="RFC8697" format="default"/>. </t>
      <t>  In this document, "VNAG object" refers to an ASSOCIATION object with the Association Type set to "VN Association" (7). </t>
      <t> Local policies on the PCE define the computational and optimization behavior for the LSPs in the VN. An LSP <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> belong to more than one VNAG. If an implementation encounters more than one VNAG object in a PCEP message, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> process the first occurrence, and it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ignore the others.  </t>
      <t> <xref target="RFC8697" format="default"/> specifies the mechanism by which a PCEP speaker can advertise which Association Types it supports.  This is done using the ASSOC-Type-List TLV carried within an OPEN object.  A PCEP speaker <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include the VN Association Type (7) in the ASSOC-Type-List TLV before using the VNAG object in a PCEP message. As per <xref target="RFC8697" format="default"/>, if the implementation does not support the VN Association Type, it will return a PCErr message with Error-Type=26 (Association Error) and Error-value=1 (Association Type is not supported). </t>

      <t> The Association Identifiers (VNAG IDs) for this Association Type are dynamic in nature and created by the parent PCE (MDSC) based on the VN operations for the LSPs belonging to the same VN.  Operator configuration of VNAG IDs is not supported, so there is no need for an Operator-configured Association Range to be set.  Thus, the VN Association Type (7) <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be present in the Operator-configured Association Range TLV if that TLV is present in the OPEN object.  If an implementation encounters the VN Association Type (7) in an Operator-configured Association Range TLV, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ignore the associated Start-Assoc-ID and Range values.
      </t>
      <t>This association is useful in a PCEP session between a parent PCE (MDSC) and a child PCE (PNC). When computing the path, the child PCE (PNC) refers to the VN association in the request from the parent PCE (MDSC) and maps the VN to the associated LSPs and network resources. From the perspective of the parent PCE, it receives a VN creation request from its customer, with the VN uniquely identified by the association parameters (<xref target="RFC8697" sectionFormat="of" section="6.1.4"/>) in the VNAG or the Virtual Network Identifier encoded in the VIRTUAL-NETWORK-TLV. This VN may comprise multiple LSPs in the network in a single domain or across multiple domains.  The parent PCE sends a PCInitiate message with this association information in the VNAG object. This in effect binds an LSP that is to be instantiated at the child PCE with the VN.  The VN association information <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be included as a part of the first PCRpt message. <xref target="vn-operations"/> shows an example of a typical VN operation using PCEP.  It is worth noting that in a multi-domain scenario, the different domains are controlled by different child PCEs. In order to set up the cross-domain tunnel, multiple segments need to be stitched by the border nodes in each domain that receive the instruction from their child PCE (PNC).
      </t>

      
      <figure anchor="vn-operations">
	<name>Example of VN Operations in H-PCE (Hierarchical PCE) Architecture</name>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                          ******
                ..........*MDSC*..............................
             .            ****** ..                   MPI    .
          .                .        .                        .
       .                   .          .   PCInitiate LSPx    .
     .                    .             .   with VNAG        .
    .                    .                .                  .
   .                    .                  .                 .
  .                    .                    .                .
  v                    v                    v                .
******               ******               ******             .
*PNC1*               *PNC2*               *PNC4*             .
******               ******               ******             .
+---------------+    +---------------+    +---------------+  .
|               |----|               |----|              C|  .
|               |    |               |    |               |  .
|DOMAIN 1       |----|DOMAIN 2       |----|DOMAIN 4       |  .
+---------------+    +---------------+    +---------------+  .
                                         /                   .
                    ******              /                    .
                    *PNC3*<............/......................
                    ******            /
                    +---------------+/
                    |               |
                    |               |
                    |DOMAIN 3       |
                    +---------------+

MDSC -> parent PCE
PNC  -> child  PCE
MPI  -> PCEP		    
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>Whenever changes occur with the instantiated LSP in a domain network, the domain child PCE reports the changes using a PCRpt message in which the VNAG object indicates the relationship between the LSP and the VN. </t>
      <t>Whenever an update occurs with VNs in the parent PCE (due to the customer's request), the parent PCE sends a PCUpd message to inform each affected child PCE of this change. </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-4" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Extensions to PCEP</name>

      <t>The VNAG uses the generic ASSOCIATION object <xref target="RFC8697" format="default"/>. </t>
      <t> This document defines one new mandatory TLV called the "VIRTUAL-NETWORK-TLV". Optionally, the new TLV can be jointly used with the existing VENDOR-INFORMATION-TLV specified in <xref target="RFC7470" format="default"/>  as described below: </t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>VIRTUAL-NETWORK-TLV:</dt>
	<dd>Used to communicate the Virtual Network Identifier.</dd>
        <dt>VENDOR-INFORMATION-TLV:</dt>
	<dd>Used to communicate arbitrary vendor-specific behavioral
	information, as described in <xref target="RFC7470"
	format="default"/>.</dd>
      </dl>
      <t>The format of the VIRTUAL-NETWORK-TLV is as follows.   </t>

<figure anchor="vn-tlv-formats">
   <name>Format of the VIRTUAL-NETWORK-TLV</name>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|           Type=65             |            Length             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
//                   Virtual Network Identifier                //
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
  <dt>Type (16 bits):</dt>
  <dd>65</dd>
  <dt>Length (16 bits):</dt>
  <dd>Indicates the length of the value portion of the TLV in octets and
  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be greater than 0. The TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
  zero-padded so that the TLV is 4-octet aligned.</dd>
  <dt>Virtual Network Identifier (variable):</dt>
  <dd>A symbolic name for the VN that uniquely identifies the VN. It
  <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be a string of printable ASCII <xref target="RFC0020"
  format="default"/> characters (i.e., 0x20 to 0x7E), without a NULL
  terminator. The Virtual Network Identifier is a human-readable string that
  identifies a VN. It can be specified with the association information, which
  may be conveyed in a VENDOR-INFORMATION-TLV. An implementation uses the
  Virtual Network Identifier to maintain a mapping to the VNAG
  and the LSPs associated with the VN. The Virtual Network Identifier
  <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be specified by the customer, set via an operator
  policy, or auto-generated by the PCEP speaker.</dd></dl>
      <t>The VIRTUAL-NETWORK-TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be included in VNAG object.  If a PCEP speaker receives the VNAG object without the VIRTUAL-NETWORK-TLV, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a PCErr message with Error-Type=6 (Mandatory Object missing) and Error-value=18 (VIRTUAL-NETWORK-TLV missing) and close the session.   </t>
      <t>The format of VENDOR-INFORMATION-TLV is defined in <xref target="RFC7470" format="default"/>. </t>
      <t>If a PCEP speaker receives a VNAG object with a TLV that violates the rules specified in this document, the PCEP speaker <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a PCErr message with Error-Type=10 (Reception of an invalid object) and Error-value=11 (Malformed object) and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> close the PCEP session. </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-6" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The security considerations described in <xref target="RFC5440"
      format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC8231" format="default"/>, and <xref
      target="RFC8281" format="default"/> apply to the extensions defined in
      this document as well.</t>
      <t>This document introduces the VN Association Type (7) for the ASSOCIATION object. Additional security
   considerations related to LSP associations due to a malicious PCEP speaker are described in <xref target="RFC8697" format="default"/> and apply to the VN Association Type.  Hence, securing the PCEP session using Transport Layer Security (TLS) <xref target="RFC8253" format="default"/> is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-7" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="sect-7.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>ASSOCIATION Object Type Indicator</name>
        <t>IANA has assigned the following new value in the "ASSOCIATION Type Field" subregistry within the "Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) Numbers" registry:  </t>
<table align="left">
  <name></name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Value</th>
      <th>Name</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>7</td>
      <td>VN Association</td>
      <td>RFC 9358</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-7.2" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>PCEP TLV Type Indicator</name>
        <t>IANA has assigned the following new value in the "PCEP TLV Type Indicators" subregistry within the "Path
   Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) Numbers" registry:
        </t>
<table align="left">
  <name></name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Value</th>
      <th>Name</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>65</td>
      <td>VIRTUAL-NETWORK-TLV</td>
      <td>RFC 9358</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-7.3" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>PCEP Error</name>
        <t> IANA has allocated the following new error value in the "PCEP-ERROR
        Object Error Types and Values" subregistry within the "Path
        Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) Numbers" registry:
        </t>
<table align="left">
  <name></name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Error-Type</th>
      <th>Meaning</th>
      <th>Error-value</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>6</td>
      <td>Mandatory Object missing</td>
      <td>18: VIRTUAL-NETWORK-TLV missing</td>
      <td>RFC 9358</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-8" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Manageability Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="sect-8.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Control of Function and Policy</name>
        <t>An operator <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be allowed to mark LSPs that belong to the same VN. This could also be done automatically based on the VN configuration.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-8.2" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Information and Data Models</name>
        <t>The PCEP YANG module <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang" format="default"/> should support the association between LSPs including VN association.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-8.3" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Liveness Detection and Monitoring</name>
        <t> Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new liveness detection and monitoring requirements in addition to those already listed in <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-8.4" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Verification of Correct Operations</name>
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new operation verification requirements in addition to those already listed in <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-8.5" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements on Other Protocols</name>
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new requirements on other protocols.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-8.6" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Impact on Network Operations</name>
        <t><xref target="RFC8637" format="default"/> describes the network operations when PCE is used for VN operations. <xref target="sect-3" format="default"/> further specifies the operations when VN associations are used.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>

    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang" to="PCE-PCEP-YANG"/>
    
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>

        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0020.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5440.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8231.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8253.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8281.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8697.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4655.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6805.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8453.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8637.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5541.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7470.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8051.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8751.xml"/>

<!-- [I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang] IESG state I-D Exists -->

<reference anchor="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang">
  <front>
    <title>A YANG Data Model for Path Computation Element Communications Protocol (PCEP)</title>
    <author initials="D." surname="Dhody" fullname="Dhruv Dhody" role="editor">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="V." surname="Beeram" fullname="Vishnu Pavan Beeram">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="J." surname="Hardwick" fullname="Jonathan Hardwick">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="J." surname="Tantsura" fullname="Jeff Tantsura">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="October" day="23" year="2022"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-pce-pcep-yang-20"/>
</reference>

      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="sect-10" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Contributors</name>
      <contact fullname="Dhruv Dhody">
	<organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
	<address>
	  <postal>
	    <street>Divyashree Technopark, Whitefield</street>
	    <city>Bangalore</city>
	    <region>Karnataka</region><code>560066</code>
	    <country>India</country>
	  </postal>
	  <email>dhruv.ietf@gmail.com</email>
	</address>
      </contact>

      <contact fullname="Qin Wu">
        <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
        <address>
          <postal>
            <street></street>
            <city></city>
            <region></region>
            <country>China</country>
          </postal>
          <email>bill.wu@huawei.com</email>
        </address>
      </contact>

      <contact fullname="Xian Zhang">
        <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
        <address>
          <postal>
            <street></street>
            <city></city>
            <region></region>
            <country>China</country>
          </postal>
          <email>zhang.xian@huawei.com</email>
        </address>
      </contact>

      <contact fullname="Adrian Farrel">
	<organization>Old Dog Consulting</organization>
        <address>
          <postal>
            <street></street>
            <city></city>
            <region></region>
            <country></country>
          </postal>
          <email>adrian@olddog.co.uk</email>
        </address>
      </contact>

    </section>
  </back>

</rfc>
