<?xml version="1.0" encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
 <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
 <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
 <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
 <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-pce-stateful-pce-vendor-13" number="9752" consensus="true" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" sortRefs="true" submissionType="IETF" symRefs="true" tocInclude="true" updates="7470" version="3" xml:lang="en">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Vendor-Specific Info for Stateful PCE">Conveying Vendor-Specific Information in
    the Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP)
    Extensions for Stateful PCE</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9752"/>

    <author fullname="Cheng Li" initials="C." surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code>100095</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>c.l@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Haomian Zheng" initials="H." surname="Zheng">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>H1, Huawei Xiliu Beipo Village, Songshan Lake</street>
          <city>Dongguan</city>
          <region>Guangdong</region>
          <code>523808</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>zhenghaomian@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Siva Sivabalan" initials="S." surname="Sivabalan">
      <organization>Ciena</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>385 Terry Fox Drive</street>
          <city>Kanata</city>
          <region>Ontario</region>
          <code>K2K 0L1</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>msiva282@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Samuel Sidor" initials="S." surname="Sidor">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ssidor@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Zafar Ali" initials="Z." surname="Ali">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>zali@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="April" year="2025"/>

    <area>RTG</area>
    <workgroup>pce</workgroup>

<keyword>PCE</keyword>
<keyword>Vendor specific</keyword>
<keyword>vendor-specific</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies extensions to the Path Computation Element
      Communication Protocol (PCEP) that enable the inclusion of
      vendor-specific information in stateful Path Computation Element (PCE) operations. These extensions
      allow vendors to incorporate proprietary data within PCEP messages,
      facilitating enhanced network optimization and functionality in
      environments requiring vendor-specific features. The extensions maintain
      compatibility with existing PCEP implementations and promote
      interoperability across diverse network deployments. RFC 7470 defines a
      facility to carry vendor-specific information in stateless PCEP messages. This document extends this
      capability for the stateful PCEP messages.</t>
<t>
   This document updates RFC 7470 to specify that Enterprise Numbers 
   are managed through the "Private Enterprise Numbers (PENs)" registry.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>

      <t>The Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP) <xref
      format="default" target="RFC5440"/> provides mechanisms for a Path
      Computation Element (PCE) to perform path computation in response to a
      Path Computation Client (PCC) request.</t>

      <t>A stateful PCE is capable of considering, for the purposes of 
      path computation, not only the network state in terms of links and nodes
      (referred to as the Traffic Engineering Database or TED) but also the
      status of active services (previously computed paths, and currently
      reserved resources, stored in the Label Switched Paths Database
      (LSP-DB)). <xref format="default" target="RFC8051"/> describes general
      considerations for a stateful PCE deployment and examines its
      applicability and benefits, as well as its challenges and limitations
      through a number of use cases.</t>

      <t><xref format="default" target="RFC8231"/> describes a set of
      extensions to PCEP to provide stateful control. A stateful PCE has
      access to not only the information carried by the network's Interior
      Gateway Protocol (IGP), but also the set of active paths and their
      reserved resources for its computations. The additional state allows the
      PCE to compute constrained paths while considering individual LSPs and
      their interactions. <xref format="default" target="RFC8281"/> describes
      the setup, maintenance, and teardown of PCE-initiated LSPs under the
      stateful PCE model. These extensions add new messages in PCEP for
      stateful PCE.</t>

      <t><xref format="default" target="RFC7470"/> defines the Vendor Information
     object, which can carry arbitrary, proprietary information, such as
      vendor-specific constraints, in stateless PCEP. It also defines the
      VENDOR-INFORMATION-TLV, which allows arbitrary information to be embedded
      within any existing or future PCEP object that supports TLVs.</t>

      <t>While originally designed for stateless PCEP, the Vendor Information
      object and VENDOR-INFORMATION-TLV are also useful in the stateful PCE model.
      The VENDOR-INFORMATION-TLV can already be included in any of the stateful PCEP
      objects per <xref format="default" target="RFC7470"/>. This
      document further extends stateful PCEP messages to support the use of the
      Vendor Information object.</t>

      <section anchor="Requirements" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>

        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be
    interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref
    target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as
    shown here.
        </t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="RBNF" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Use of RBNF</name>

        <t>The message formats in this document are illustrated using Routing
        Backus-Naur Form (RBNF) encoding, as specified in <xref
        format="default" target="RFC5511"/>. The use of RBNF is illustrative
        only and may omit certain important details; the normative
        specification of messages is found in the descriptive text. If there
        is any divergence between the RBNF and the descriptive text, the
        descriptive text is considered authoritative.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Procedures" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Procedures for the Vendor Information Object</name>

      <t>A Path Computation LSP State Report message (also referred to as
      PCRpt message; see <xref format="default" section="6.1"
      sectionFormat="of" target="RFC8231"/>) is a PCEP message sent by a
      PCC to a PCE to report the current state of an LSP. A PCC that wants to
      convey proprietary or vendor-specific information or metrics to a PCE
      does so by including a Vendor Information object in the PCRpt message.
      The contents and format of the object, including the VENDOR-INFORMATION
      object and the VENDOR-INFORMATION-TLV, are described in
      <xref section="4" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC7470"/>. The PCE determines how to
      interpret the information in the Vendor Information object by examining
      the Enterprise Number it contains.</t>
<!-- DNE: Text from [RFC7470] is correct. -->
      <t><xref format="default" target="RFC7470"/> stated that:</t>
      <blockquote>
        <t>Enterprise Numbers are assigned by IANA and managed through an IANA
        registry <xref format="default" target="RFC2578"/>.</t>
      </blockquote>

      <t>This document updates <xref format="default" target="RFC7470"/> and replaces this text with:</t>
      <blockquote>
        <t>Enterprise Numbers are assigned by IANA and managed
        through the "Private Enterprise Numbers (PENs)" registry as 
        described in <xref format="default" target="RFC9371"/>.</t>
      </blockquote>

      <t>The Vendor Information object is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> in a PCRpt message.
      Multiple instances of the object <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be contained in a single PCRpt
      message. Different instances of the object <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> have different Enterprise
      Numbers.</t>

      <t>The format of the PCRpt message (with <xref format="default"
      section="6.1" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC8231"/> as the base) is
      updated as follows:</t>

      <sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
      <PCRpt Message> ::= <Common Header>
                          <state-report-list>
]]></sourcecode>

   <t>Where:</t>
      <sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
      <state-report-list> ::= <state-report>[<state-report-list>]

      <state-report> ::= [<SRP>]
                         <LSP>
                         <path>
                         [<vendor-info-list>]
]]></sourcecode>

    <t>Where:</t>
      <sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
      <vendor-info-list> ::= <VENDOR-INFORMATION>
                             [<vendor-info-list>]

      <path> is defined in [RFC8231].
]]></sourcecode>

      <t>A Path Computation LSP Update Request message (also referred to as
      PCUpd message; see <xref format="default" section="6.2"
      sectionFormat="of" target="RFC8231"/>) is a PCEP message sent by a
      PCE to a PCC to update the attributes of an LSP. The Vendor Information
      object can be included in a PCUpd message to convey proprietary or
      vendor-specific information.</t>

      <t>The format of the PCUpd message (using the format described in <xref format="default"
      section="6.2" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC8231"/> as the base) is
      updated as follows:</t>

      <sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
      <PCUpd Message> ::= <Common Header>
                          <update-request-list>
]]></sourcecode>

   <t>Where:</t>
      <sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
      <update-request-list> ::= <update-request>
                          [<update-request-list>]

      <update-request> ::= <SRP>
                           <LSP>
                           <path>
                           [<vendor-info-list>]
]]></sourcecode>

   <t>Where:</t>
      <sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
      <vendor-info-list> ::= <VENDOR-INFORMATION>
                             [<vendor-info-list>]

      <path> is defined in [RFC8231].
]]></sourcecode>

      <t>A Path Computation LSP Initiate Message (also referred to as
      PCInitiate message; see <xref format="default" section="5.1"
      sectionFormat="of" target="RFC8281"/>) is a PCEP message sent by a
      PCE to a PCC to trigger an LSP instantiation or deletion. The Vendor
      Information object can be included in a PCInitiate message to convey
      proprietary or vendor-specific information.</t>

      <t>The format of the PCInitiate message (using the format described in <xref format="default"
      section="5.1" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC8281"/> as the base) is
      updated as follows:</t>

      <sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
     <PCInitiate Message> ::= <Common Header>
                              <PCE-initiated-lsp-list>
]]></sourcecode>

  <t>Where:</t>
      <sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
     <PCE-initiated-lsp-list> ::= <PCE-initiated-lsp-request>
                                  [<PCE-initiated-lsp-list>]

     <PCE-initiated-lsp-request> ::=
                          (<PCE-initiated-lsp-instantiation>|
                           <PCE-initiated-lsp-deletion>)

     <PCE-initiated-lsp-instantiation> ::= <SRP>
                                           <LSP>
                                           [<END-POINTS>]
                                           <ERO>
                                           [<attribute-list>]
                                           [<vendor-info-list>]
]]></sourcecode>

     <t>Where:</t>
      <sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
     <vendor-info-list> ::= <VENDOR-INFORMATION>
                            [<vendor-info-list>]
]]></sourcecode>

<t>     &lt;PCE-initiated-lsp-deletion&gt; and &lt;attribute-list&gt; are as defined in
     <xref target="RFC8281"/>.</t>


      <t>A legacy implementation that does not recognize the Vendor
      Information object will act according to the procedures set out in <xref
      format="default" target="RFC8231"/> and <xref format="default"
      target="RFC8281"/>. An implementation that supports the Vendor
      Information object, but receives one carrying an Enterprise Number that
      it does not support, <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ignore the object in the same way as described
      in <xref format="default" section="2" sectionFormat="of"
      target="RFC7470"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="TLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Procedures for the Vendor Information TLV</name>

      <t>The Vendor Information TLV can be used to carry vendor-specific
      information that applies to a specific PCEP object by including the TLV
      in the object. This includes objects used in Stateful PCE extensions
      such as Stateful PCE Request Parameter (SRP) and LSP objects. All of the
      procedures are as described in <xref section="3" sectionFormat="of"
      target="RFC7470"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Manageability Considerations</name>

      <t>All manageability requirements and considerations listed in <xref
      format="default" target="RFC5440"/>, <xref format="default"
      target="RFC7470"/>, <xref format="default" target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref
      format="default" target="RFC8281"/> apply to the PCEP protocol extensions
      defined in this document. In addition, the requirements and
      considerations listed in this section apply.</t>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Control of Function and Policy</name>

        <t>The requirements for control of function and policy for
        vendor-specific information as set out in [RFC7470] continue to apply
        to Stateful PCEP extensions specified in this document.</t>
      </section>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Information and Data Models</name>

        <t>The PCEP YANG module is specified in <xref format="default"
        target="PCEP-YANG"/>. Any standard YANG module will not
        include details of vendor-specific information. However, 
        a standard YANG module could be extended to report the use of the 
        Vendor Information object or TLV and the Enterprise Numbers that the 
        objects and TLVs contain.</t>
      </section>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Liveness Detection and Monitoring</name>

        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new liveness
        detection and monitoring requirements in addition to those already
        listed in <xref format="default" target="RFC5440"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Verifying Correct Operations</name>

        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new operation
        verification requirements in addition to those already listed in <xref
        format="default" target="RFC5440"/> and <xref format="default"
        target="RFC8231"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements On Other Protocols</name>

        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new
        requirements on other protocols.</t>
      </section>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Impact on Network Operations</name>

        <t>Mechanisms defined in <xref format="default" target="RFC5440"/> and
        <xref format="default" target="RFC8231"/> also apply to PCEP
        extensions defined in this document.</t>

        <t><xref section="6.6" sectionFormat="of" target="RFC7470"/> highlights
        how the presence of additional vendor-specific information in PCEP
        messages may congest the operations and how to detect and handle it.
        This also applies to stateful PCEP messages as outlined in <xref target="Procedures"/>.
        Specifically, a PCEP speaker <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> include vendor information in
        stateful PCEP message if it believes the recipient does not support
        that information.</t>

        <t>Encoding optimization for the Vendor Information object, for
        example, in case the object has the same content encoded for
        multiple LSPs, is considered out of the scope of this document and may
        be proposed in the future as a separate document applicable to other
        PCEP objects.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>

<t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>

      <t>The protocol extensions defined in this document do not change the
      nature of PCEP. Therefore, the security considerations set out in <xref
      format="default" target="RFC5440"/>, <xref format="default"
      target="RFC7470"/>, <xref format="default" target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref
      format="default" target="RFC8281"/> apply unchanged.</t>

      <t>Per <xref format="default" target="RFC8231"/>, it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>
      that these PCEP extensions only be activated on authenticated and
      encrypted sessions across PCEs and PCCs using Transport Layer Security
      (TLS) <xref format="default" target="RFC8253"/>.  See the
      recommendations and best current practices for using TLS in RFC 9325 <xref
      derivedContent="BCP195" format="default" target="BCP195"/>.</t>

      <t>The use of vendor-specific information as defined in <xref
      format="default" target="RFC7470"/> and in this document may provide a
      covert channel that could be misused by PCEP speaker implementations or
      by malicious software at PCEP speakers. While there is limited protection
      against this, an operator monitoring the PCEP sessions can detect the
      use of vendor-specific information, be aware of the decoding mechanism
      for this data, and inspect it accordingly. It is crucial for the
      operator to remain vigilant and monitor for any potential misuse of this
      object. Appropriate steps need to be taken to prevent the installation of
      malicious software at the PCEP speaker by implementing robust integrity,
      authentication, and authorization techniques for installation and
      updating, which are out of scope of this document.</t>
    </section>


  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>

      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5440.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5511.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7470.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8231.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8281.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml9/reference.BCP.195.xml"/>


      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2578.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9371.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8051.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8253.xml"/>


<!-- [I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang] draft-ietf-pce-pcep-yang-30
IESG State: RFC Ed Queue as of 02/10/25. Used long way for WiP since
it was missing editor role for Dhruv Dhody. -->

<reference anchor="PCEP-YANG" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-ietf-pce-pcep-yang-30">
   <front>
      <title>A YANG Data Model for Path Computation Element Communications Protocol (PCEP)</title>
      <author initials="D." surname="Dhody" fullname="Dhruv Dhody" role="editor">
         <organization>Huawei</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="V. P." surname="Beeram" fullname="Vishnu Pavan Beeram">
         <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="J." surname="Hardwick" fullname="Jonathan Hardwick">
         </author>
      <author initials="J." surname="Tantsura" fullname="Jeff Tantsura">
         <organization>Nvidia</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="January" day="26" year="2025" />
   </front>
   <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-pce-pcep-yang-30" />   
</reference>



      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgments" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>

      <t>Thanks to <contact fullname="Dhruv Dhody"/> for shepherding the document and for their significant contributions and suggestions.</t>

      <t>Thanks to <contact fullname="Adrian Farrel"/>, <contact fullname="Avantika"/>, 
	  <contact fullname="Deb Cooley"/>, <contact fullname="Éric Vyncke"/>,
	  <contact fullname="Gunter Van de Velde"/>, <contact fullname="John Scudder"/>,
	  <contact fullname="Mahendra Singh Negi"/>, <contact fullname="Mahesh Jethanandani"/>,
	  <contact fullname="Mike McBride"/>, <contact fullname="Murray Kucherawy"/>,
	  <contact fullname="Orie Steele"/>, <contact fullname="Paul Wouters"/>,
	  <contact fullname="Roman Danyliw"/>, <contact fullname="Susan Hares"/>,
	  <contact fullname="Swapna K"/>, <contact fullname="Udayasree Palle"/>,
	  <contact fullname="Warren Kumari"/>, <contact fullname="Wassim Haddad"/>, and
	  <contact fullname="Xiao Min"/> for their reviews, comments, and suggestions.</t>
    </section>

    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Contributors</name>

    <contact fullname="Dhruv Dhody">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <country>India</country>
	</postal>
        <email>dhruv.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </contact>
    <contact fullname="Mike Koldychev">
      <organization>Ciena</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mkoldych@proton.me</email>
      </address>
    </contact>

    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
