<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" submissionType="IETF" category="exp" consensus="true" docName="draft-ietf-lsr-isis-flood-reflection-12" number="9377" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="3" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">

  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.9.1 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IS-IS Flood Reflection">
            IS-IS Flood Reflection
    </title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9377"/>
    <author fullname="Tony Przygienda" initials="T." surname="Przygienda" role="editor">
      <organization>Juniper</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1137 Innovation Way</street>
          <city>Sunnyvale</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code/>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <phone/>
        <email>prz@juniper.net</email>
        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Chris Bowers" initials="C." surname="Bowers">
      <organization>Individual</organization>
      <address>
        <email>chrisbowers.ietf@gmail.com
        </email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Yiu Lee" initials="Y" surname="Lee">
      <organization>Comcast</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1800 Bishops Gate Blvd</street>
          <city>Mount Laurel</city>
          <region>NJ</region>
          <code>08054</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Yiu_Lee@comcast.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Alankar Sharma" initials="A" surname="Sharma">
      <organization>Individual</organization>
        <address>
            <email>as3957@gmail.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Russ White" initials="R." surname="White">
      <organization>Akamai</organization>
        <address>
            <email>russ@riw.us</email>
        </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2023" month="April"/>

    <area>rtg</area>
    <workgroup>lsr</workgroup>
    
    <keyword>scalability</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a backward-compatible, optional IS-IS
      extension that allows the creation of IS-IS flood reflection topologies.
      Flood reflection permits topologies in which IS&nbhy;IS&nbsp;Level&nbsp;1 (L1) areas
      provide transit-forwarding for IS&nbhy;IS&nbsp;Level&nbsp;2 (L2) areas using all
      available L1 nodes internally.  It accomplishes this by
      creating L2 flood reflection adjacencies within each L1 area. Those
      adjacencies are used to flood L2 Link State Protocol Data Units (LSPs) and are used in the L2 Shortest Path First (SPF)
      computation.  However, they are not ordinarily utilized for forwarding
      within the flood reflection cluster.

          <!--
                not utilized for forwarding within the flood reflection cluster except
                in pathological cases mentioned in <xref target="patholody"/>.

                -->

                This arrangement gives
				the L2 topology significantly better scaling properties than prevalently used
                flat designs.  As an additional benefit,
                only those routers directly participating
				in flood reflection are required to support the feature.  This allows for
				incremental deployment of scalable L1 transit areas in an existing, previously
          flat network design, without
				the necessity of upgrading all routers in the network.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

    <section toc="default" numbered="true">
      <name>Introduction</name>
        <t> This section introduces the problem space and outlines the solution. Some of the terms
            may be unfamiliar to readers without extensive IS-IS background; for such readers,
            the terminology is provided in <xref target="terminology"/>.
        </t>
      <t>Due to the inherent properties of link-state protocols, the number of
      IS-IS routers within a flooding domain is limited by processing and
      flooding overhead on each node. While that number can be maximized by
      well-written implementations and techniques such as exponential
      backoffs, IS-IS will still reach a saturation point where no further
      routers can be added to a single flooding domain.  In some L2 backbone
      deployment scenarios, this limit presents a significant challenge.
      </t>
      <t>
				The standard approach to increasing the scale of an IS-IS deployment is
				to break it up into multiple L1 flooding domains and a single L2
				backbone. This works well for designs where an L2 backbone connects L1
                access topologies, but it is limiting where a single, flat L2 domain is supposed to span
                large number of routers. In such scenarios, an alternative approach could be to
                consider multiple
				L2 flooding domains that are connected together via L1 flooding domains.
                In other words, L2 flooding domains are connected by "L1/L2 lanes" through
				the L1 areas to form a single L2 backbone again. Unfortunately, in its
				simplest implementation, this requires the inclusion of most, or all, of
				the transit L1 routers as L1/L2 to allow traffic to flow along optimal
				paths through those transit areas. Consequently, such an approach
				fails to reduce the number of L2 routers involved and, with that,
          fails to increase the
				scalability of the L2 backbone as well.
      </t>

        <t>
            <xref target="f1" format="default"/> is an example of a network where a topologically rich L1 area
            is used to provide transit between six different L2-only routers (R1-R6).  Note that
            the six L2-only routers do not have connectivity to one another over L2 links.
            To take advantage of the abundance of paths in the L1 transit area,
            all the intermediate systems could be placed into both L1 and L2, but this
            essentially combines the separate L2 flooding domains into a single one,
            again triggering the maximum L2 scale limitation we were trying to address in first place.
        </t>

      <figure anchor="f1">
        <name>Example Topology of L1 with L2 Borders</name>
        <artwork align="left" alt="" name="" type=""><![CDATA[
+====+  +=======+             +=======+               +======-+  +====+
I R1 I  I  R10  +-------------+  R20  +---------------+  R30  I  I R4 I
I L2 +--+ L1/L2 I             I  L1   I               I L1/L2 +--+ L2 I
I    I  I       +          +--+       I  +------------+       I  I    I
+====+  ++====+=+          |  +===+===+  |            +=+==+=++  +====+
         |    |            |      |      |              |    |
         |    |            |      |      |  +-----------+    |
         |    +-------+    |      |      |  |                |
         |            |    |      |      |  |                |
         |            |    |      |      |  |                |
         |            |    |      |      |  |                |
+====+  ++=====-+     |    |  +===+===+--+  |         +======++  +====+
I R2 I  I  R11  I     |    |  I  R21  I     |         I  R31  I  I R5 I
I L2 +--+ L1/L2 +-------------+  L1   +---------------+ L1/L2 +--+ L2 I
I    I  I       I     |    |  I       I     | +-------+       I  I    I
+====+  ++=====-+     |    |  ++==+==++     | |       +======++  +====+
         |            |    |   |  |  |      | |              |
         | +---------------+   |  |  |      | |              |
         | |          |        |  |  |      | |              |
         | |  +----------------+  |  +-----------------+     |
         | |  |       |           |         | |        |     |
+====+  ++=+==+=+     +-------+===+===+-----+ |       ++=====++  +====+
I R3 I  I  R12  I             I  R22  I       |       +  R32  I  I R6 I
I L2 +--+ L1/L2 I             I  L1   +-------+       I L1/L2 +--+ L2 I
I    I  I       +-------------+       +---------------+       I  I    I
+====+  +=======+             +=======+               +=======+  +====+
    ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t> A more effective solution would allow the reduction of the number of links and routers exposed
                in L2, while still utilizing
                the full L1 topology when forwarding through the network.
</t>
      <t> <xref target="RFC8099" format="default"/> describes Topology Transparent Zones (TTZ) for OSPF.
			    The TTZ mechanism represents a group of OSPF routers as a full mesh of adjacencies
				between the routers at the edge of the group.  A similar mechanism
                could be applied to IS-IS as well.  However, a full mesh of adjacencies between edge routers
				(or L1/L2 nodes) significantly limits the practically achievable scale of the
          resulting topology.
				The topology in <xref target="f1" format="default"/> has six L1/L2 nodes.   <xref target="f2" format="default"/> illustrates
				a full mesh of L2 adjacencies between the six L1/L2 nodes, resulting in
				(5 * 6)/2 = 15 L2 adjacencies. In a somewhat larger topology containing 20 L1/L2 nodes,
				the number of L2 adjacencies in a full mesh rises to 190.
      </t>
      <figure anchor="f2">
        <name>Example Topology Represented in L2 with a Full Mesh of L2 Adjacencies between L1/L2 Nodes</name>
        <artwork align="left" alt="" name="" type=""><![CDATA[
+----+  +-------+    +-------------------------------+-------+  +----+
| R1 |  |  R10  |    |                               |  R30  |  | R4 |
| L2 +--+ L1/L2 +------------------------------------+ L1/L2 +--+ L2 |
|    |  |       |    |                               |       |  |    |
+----+  ++-+-+--+-+  |                             +-+--+---++  +----+
         | | |    |  |                             |    |   |
         | +----------------------------------------------+ |
         |   |    |  |                             |    | | |
         |   +-----------------------------------+ |    | | |
         |        |  |                           | |    | | |
         |     +----------------------------------------+ | |
         |     |  |  |                           | |      | |
+----+  ++-----+- |  |                           | | -----+-++  +----+
| R2 |  |  R11  | |  |                           | | |  R31  |  | R5 |
| L2 +--+ L1/L2 +------------------------------------+ L1/L2 +--+ L2 |
|    |  |       | |  |                           | | |       |  |    |
+----+  ++------+------------------------------+ | | +----+-++  +----+
         |        |  |                         | | |      | |
         |        |  |                         | | |      | |
         |    +-------------------------------------------+ |
         |    |   |  |                         | | |        |
         |    |   |  |                         +----------+ |
         |    |   |  |                           | |      | |
         |    |   |  |                           +-----+  | |
         |    |   |  |                             |   |  | |
+----+  ++----+-+-+  |                             +-+-+--+-++  +----+
| R3 |  |  R12  |    |      L2 adjacency             |  R32  |  | R6 |
| L2 +--+ L1/L2 +------------------------------------+ L1/L2 +--+ L2 |
|    |  |       |    |                               |       |  |    |
+----+  +-------+----+                               +-------+  +----+
    ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
                BGP, as specified in <xref target="RFC4271" format="default"/>, faced a similar scaling problem, which
                has been
                solved in many networks by deploying BGP route reflectors <xref target="RFC4456" format="default"/>.
                We note that BGP route reflectors do not necessarily have to be in the
                forwarding path of the traffic. This non-congruity of forwarding and control path for BGP
				route reflectors allows the control plane to scale independently of the forwarding plane and
          represents an interesting degree of freedom in network architecture.
      </t>
      <t>
                We propose in this document a similar solution for IS-IS and call it "flood reflection"
          in a fashion analogous to "route reflection". A simple example of what a flood
                reflector control plane approach would look like
                is shown in <xref target="f3" format="default"/>, where router R21 plays the role of a flood reflector. Each
                L1/L2 ingress/egress router builds a tunnel to the flood reflector, and an L2 adjacency is built
				over each tunnel.  In this solution, we need only six L2 adjacencies,
				instead of the 15 needed for a full mesh.  In a somewhat larger topology containing 20 L1/L2 nodes,
				this solution requires only 20 L2 adjacencies, instead of the 190 needed for a full mesh.
                Multiple flood reflectors can be used, allowing the network operator to balance between
                resilience, path utilization, and state in the control plane. The resulting
                L2 adjacency scale is R*n, where R is the number of flood reflectors used and n is the number of
				L1/L2 nodes.  This compares quite favorably with n*(n-1)/2 L2 adjacencies
				required in a topologically fully meshed L2 solution.
      </t>
      <figure anchor="f3">
        <name>Example Topology Represented in L2 with L2 Adjacencies from Each L1/L2 Node to a Single Flood Reflector</name>
        <artwork align="left" alt="" name="" type=""><![CDATA[
+----+  +-------+                                    +-------+  +----+
| R1 |  |  R10  |                                    |  R30  |  | R4 |
| L2 +--+ L1/L2 +--------------+   +-----------------+ L1/L2 +--+ L2 |
|    |  |       |  L2 adj      |   |      L2 adj     |       |  |    |
+----+  +-------+  over        |   |      over       +-------+  +----+
                   tunnel      |   |      tunnel
+----+  +-------+           +--+---+--+              +-------+  +----+
| R2 |  |  R11  |           |   R21   |              |  R31  |  | R5 |
| L2 +--+ L1/L2 +-----------+  L1/L2  +--------------+ L1/L2 +--+ L2 |
|    |  |       |  L2 adj   |  flood  |   L2 adj     |       |  |    |
+----+  +-------+  over     |reflector|   over       +-------+  +----+
                   tunnel   +--+---+--+   tunnel
+----+  +-------+              |   |                 +-------+  +----+
| R3 |  |  R12  +--------------+   +-----------------+  R32  |  | R6 |
| L2 +--+ L1/L2 |  L2 adj                 L2 adj     | L1/L2 +--+ L2 |
|    |  |       |  over                   over       |       |  |    |
+----+  +-------+  tunnel                 tunnel     +-------+  +----+
    ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>As illustrated in <xref target="f3" format="default"/>, when R21
      plays the role of flood reflector, it provides L2 connectivity among all
      of the previously disconnected L2 islands by reflooding all L2 Link State Protocol Data Unit (LSPs).
      At the same time, R20 and R22 in <xref target="f1"/> remain L1-only
      routers.  L1-only routers and L1-only links are not visible in L2.  In
      this manner, the flood reflector allows us to provide L2 control plane
      connectivity in a manner more scalable than a flat L2 domain.
      </t>
      <t>
                As described so far, the solution illustrated in  <xref target="f3" format="default"/> relies
				only on currently standardized IS-IS functionality. Without new functionality, however,
                the data traffic will traverse only R21.  This will unnecessarily create a bottleneck
				at R21 since there is still available capacity in the paths crossing the L1-only
				routers R20 and R22 in <xref target="f1"/>.
      </t>
      <t>Hence, additional functionality is compulsory to allow the L1/L2 edge
      nodes (R10-12 and R30-32 in <xref target="f3" format="default"/>) to
      recognize that the L2 adjacency to R21 should not be used for
      forwarding. The L1/L2 edge nodes should forward traffic that would
      normally be forwarded over the L2 adjacency to R21 over L1 links
      instead.  This would allow the forwarding within the L1 area to use the
      L1-only nodes and links shown in <xref target="f1" format="default"/> as
      well.  
   It allows networks that use                                      
   the entire forwarding capacity of the L1 areas to be built, while 
   at the same time it introduces control plane scaling benefits that 
   are provided by L2 flood reflectors.
      </t>
      <t>
   It is expected that deployment at scale, and suitable time in 
   operation, will provide sufficient evidence to either put this 
   extension into a Standards Track document or suggest necessary 
   modifications to accomplish that.
        </t>

      <t> The remainder of this document defines the remaining extensions necessary
          for a complete flood reflection solution:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
            It defines a special "flood reflector adjacency"
            built for the purpose of reflecting flooding
            information.  These adjacencies allow "flood reflectors" to
            participate in the IS-IS control plane without necessarily being
            used in the forwarding plane.  Maintenance of such adjacencies is
            a purely local operation on the L1/L2 ingress and flood
            reflectors; it does not require replacing or modifying any routers
            not involved in the reflection process.  In practical deployments, it is
            far less tricky to just upgrade the routers involved in flood
            reflection rather than have a flag day for the whole IS-IS domain.
                    </li>
        <li>
            It specifies an (optional) full mesh of tunnels between the L1/L2
            ingress routers, ideally load-balancing across all available L1
            links.  This harnesses all forwarding paths between the L1/L2 edge
            nodes without injecting unneeded state into the L2 flooding domain
            or creating "choke points" at the "flood reflectors" themselves.
            The specification is agnostic as to the tunneling technology used but
            provides enough information for automatic establishment of such
            tunnels if desired.  The discussion of IS-IS adjacency formation and/or
            liveness discovery on such tunnels is outside the scope of this
            specification and is largely a choice of the underlying implementation.  A
            solution without tunnels is also possible by introducing the correct
            scoping of reachability information between the levels. This is
            described in more detail later.

                    </li>
        <li>
            Finally, this document defines support of reflector redundancy
            and an (optional) way to auto-discover and annotate flood
            reflector adjacencies on advertisements.  Such additional
            information in link advertisements allows L2 nodes outside the L1
            area to recognize a flood reflection cluster and its adjacencies.

                    </li>
      </ul>
    </section>

<section anchor="conv">
<name>Conventions Used in This Document</name>

      <section anchor="terminology" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Terminology</name>
          <t>
              The following terms are used in this document.
          </t>
          <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">

              <dt>IS-IS Level 1 and Level 2 areas (mostly abbreviated as L1 and
              L2):</dt>
              <dd>IS-IS concepts where a routing domain has two
              "levels" with a single L2 area being the "backbone" that
              connects multiple L1 areas for scaling and reliability
              purposes. 

      IS-IS architecture prescribes a routing domain with two
      "levels" where a single L2 area functions as the "backbone" that connects
      multiple L1 areas amongst themselves for scaling and reliability purposes. 
      In such architecture, L2 can be used as transit for traffic carried from one L1 area to another, but
      L1 areas themselves cannot be used for that purpose because the L2 level must
      be a single "connected" entity, and all traffic exiting an L1 area flows along L2 routers until the
      traffic arrives at the destination L1 area itself.
              </dd>
              <dt>Flood Reflector:</dt>
              <dd>Node configured to connect in L2 only to flood reflector
              clients and to reflect (reflood) IS-IS L2 LSPs amongst them.</dd>
              <dt>Flood Reflector Client:</dt>
      <dd>Node configured to build Flood Reflector Adjacencies to Flood
      Reflectors and to build normal adjacencies to other clients and 
      L2 nodes not participating in flood reflection.</dd>

              <dt>Flood Reflector Adjacency:</dt>
              <dd>IS-IS L2 adjacency where one end is a Flood Reflector Client,
              and the other, a Flood Reflector. Both have the same Flood
              Reflector Cluster ID.
              </dd>
              <dt>Flood Reflector Cluster:</dt>
              <dd>Collection of clients and flood reflectors configured with the same cluster identifier.</dd>
              <dt>
                  Tunnel-Based Deployment:
              </dt>
              <dd>Deployment where Flood Reflector Clients build a partial or full mesh of tunnels in L1  to "shortcut"
                  forwarding of L2 traffic through the cluster.</dd>
              <dt>
                  No-Tunnel Deployment:
              </dt>
              <dd>
                  Deployment where Flood Reflector Clients redistribute L2 reachability into L1 to allow
                  forwarding through the cluster without underlying tunnels.
              </dd>
              <dt>
                  Tunnel Endpoint:
              </dt>
              <dd>An endpoint that allows the establishment of a
              bidirectional tunnel carrying IS-IS control traffic or,
              alternately, serves as the origin of such a tunnel.
              </dd>
              <dt>L1 shortcut:</dt>
              <dd>A tunnel established between two clients that is visible in L1
              only and is used as a next hop, i.e., to carry data traffic
              in tunnel-based deployment mode.
              </dd>
              <dt>Hot-Potato Routing:</dt>
              <dd>In the context of this document, a routing paradigm where
              L2->L1 routes are less preferred than L2 routes <xref
              target="RFC5302" format="default"/>.
              </dd>
          </dl>
	</section>

	  <section numbered="true" toc="default">
	    <name>Requirements Language</name>
	    <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
	  </section>
      </section>

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Further Details</name>
      <t>
                Several considerations should be noted in relation to such a flood reflection mechanism.
      </t>

      <t>
   First, the flood reflection mechanism allows multi-area IS-IS deployments 
   to scale without any major modifications in the IS-IS implementation on 
   most of the nodes deployed in the network.
    Unmodified (standard) L2 routers will
                compute reachability across the transit L1 area using the flood reflector
                adjacencies.  (In this document, the term "standard" refers to IS-IS as specified in <xref target="ISO10589"/>.) 
      </t>
      <t>
                Second, the flood reflectors are not required to participate in forwarding
                traffic through the L1 transit area. These flood reflectors can
                be hosted on virtual devices outside the forwarding topology.
</t>
      <t> Third, astute readers will realize that flooding reflection may
      cause the use of suboptimal paths. This is similar to the BGP route
      reflection suboptimal routing problem described in <xref
      target="RFC9107" format="default"/>. 

   The L2
   computation determines the egress L1/L2 and, with that, can create
   illusions of ECMP where there is none; and in certain scenarios,
   the L2 computation can lead to an L1/L2 egress that is not globally 
   optimal. 
 
 This represents a straightforward
 instance of the trade-off between the amount of control plane state and the
 optimal use of paths through the network that are often encountered when
 aggregating routing information.
      </t>
      <t>One possible solution to this problem is to expose additional
      topology information into the L2 flooding domains. In the example
      network given, links from router R10 to router R11 can be exposed into
      L2 even when R10 and R11 are participating in flood reflection.  This
      information would allow the L2 nodes to build "shortcuts" when the L2
      flood-reflected part of the topology looks more expensive to cross
      distance-wise.
      </t>
      <t>Another possible variation is for an implementation to use the tunnel
      cost to approximate the cost of the underlying topology.  </t>
      <t>Redundancy can be achieved by configuring multiple flood reflectors
      in an L1 area.  Multiple flood reflectors do not need any synchronization
      mechanisms amongst themselves, except standard IS-IS flooding and
      database maintenance procedures.
      </t>

    </section>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Encodings</name>

    <section anchor="sec_flood_reflection_tlv" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Flood Reflection TLV</name>
      <t>The Flood Reflection TLV is a top-level TLV that <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
      appear in L2 IIHs (IS-IS Hello) on all Flood Reflection Adjacencies.  The Flood
      Reflection TLV indicates the flood reflector cluster (based on Flood
      Reflection Cluster ID) that a given router is configured to participate
      in. It also indicates whether the router is configured to play the role
      of either flood reflector or flood reflector client. The Flood
      Reflection Cluster ID and flood reflector roles advertised in the IIHs
      are used to ensure that flood reflector adjacencies are only formed
      between a flood reflector and flood reflector client and that the Flood
      Reflection Cluster IDs match. The Flood Reflection TLV has the following
      format:
      </t>

      <artwork align="left" alt="" name="" type=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |    Length     |C|  Reserved   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                    Flood Reflection Cluster ID                |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Sub-TLVs ...
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>Type:</dt>
        <dd>161</dd>
        <dt>Length:</dt>
        <dd>The length, in octets, of the following fields.</dd>
        <dt>C (Client):</dt>
        <dd>This bit is set to indicate that the router acts as a flood
        reflector client.  When this bit is NOT set, the router acts as a
        flood reflector. On a given router, the same value of the C-bit
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be advertised across all interfaces advertising
        the Flood Reflection TLV in IIHs.
                    </dd>
        <dt>Reserved:</dt>
        <dd>
					    This field is reserved for future use.  It <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to 0 when sent
						and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored when received.
                    </dd>

        <dt>Flood Reflection Cluster ID:</dt>
        <dd>
            The&nbsp;same arbitrary 32-bit value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be assigned to
            all of the flood reflectors and flood reflector clients in the
            same L1 area. The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be unique across
            different L1 areas within the IGP domain. In case of violation of
            those rules, multiple L1 areas may become a single cluster, or a
            single area may split in flood reflection sense, and several
            mechanisms, such as auto-discovery of tunnels, may not work
            correctly.

            On a given router, the same value of the Flood Reflection Cluster
            ID <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be advertised across all interfaces
            advertising the Flood Reflection TLV in IIHs. When a router
            discovers that a node is using more than a single Cluster IDs
            based on its advertised TLVs and IIHs, the node <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>
            log such violations subject to rate-limiting.  This implies that a
            flood reflector <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> participate in more than a
            single L1 area. In case of Cluster ID value of 0, the TLV
            containing it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored.
                    </dd>
        <dt>Sub-TLVs (Optional Sub-TLVs):</dt>
        <dd>For future extensibility, the format of the Flood Reflection TLV
        allows for the possibility of including optional sub-TLVs.  No
        sub-TLVs of the Flood Reflection TLV are defined in this document.
                    </dd>
      </dl>
      <t>The Flood Reflection TLV <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> appear more than
      once in an IIH.  A router receiving one or more Flood Reflection TLVs in
      the same IIH <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the values in the first TLV, and it
      <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> log such violations subject to rate-limiting.
      </t>

    </section>
    <section anchor="sec_flood_reflection_discovery_subtlv" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Flood Reflection Discovery Sub-TLV</name>
      <t>
				The Flood Reflection Discovery sub-TLV is advertised as a sub-TLV of the
				IS-IS Router Capability TLV 242, defined in <xref target="RFC7981" format="default"/>.
				The Flood Reflection Discovery sub-TLV is advertised in L1 and L2 LSPs with
				area flooding scope in order to enable the auto-discovery of flood
				reflection capabilities. The Flood Reflection Discovery sub-TLV has
				the following format:
      </t>
      <artwork align="left" alt="" name="" type=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |    Length     |C|  Reserved   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                    Flood Reflection Cluster ID                |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>Type:</dt>
        <dd>161</dd>
        <dt>Length:</dt>
        <dd>The length, in octets, of the following fields.</dd>
        <dt>C (Client):</dt>
        <dd>
					    This bit is set to indicate that the router acts as a flood reflector client.
						When this bit is NOT set, the router acts as a flood reflector.
                    </dd>
        <dt>Reserved:</dt>
        <dd>
					    This field is reserved for future use.  It <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to 0 when sent
						and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored when received.
                    </dd>
        <dt>Flood Reflection Cluster ID:</dt>
  <dd>The Flood Reflection Cluster Identifier
      is the same as that defined in the Flood Reflection TLV in <xref target="sec_flood_reflection_tlv"/> and obeys the same rules.
        </dd>
      </dl>
      <t>
				The Flood Reflection Discovery sub-TLV <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> appear more than once in TLV 242.  A router
				receiving one or more Flood Reflection Discovery sub-TLVs in TLV 242 <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the values in the
				first sub-TLV of the lowest numbered fragment, and it <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> log such violations subject to rate-limiting.
      </t>
    </section>


      <section anchor="sec_flood_reflection_discovery_tunnel_subtlv" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Flood Reflection Discovery Tunnel Type Sub-Sub-TLV</name>
          <t>
              Flood Reflection Discovery Tunnel Type sub-sub-TLV is advertised optionally as a sub-sub-TLV of the
              Flood Reflection Discovery Sub-TLV, defined in <xref target="sec_flood_reflection_discovery_subtlv"/>.
              It allows the automatic creation of L2 tunnels to be used as
              flood reflector adjacencies and L1 shortcut tunnels. The Flood Reflection Tunnel Type sub-sub-TLV has
              the following format:
          </t>
          <artwork align="left" alt="" name="" type=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-------------+-+
|     Type      |    Length     | Reserved    |F|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute                 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
              <dt>Type:</dt>
              <dd>161</dd>
              <dt>Length:</dt>
              <dd>The length, in octets, of zero or more of the following fields.</dd>
              <dt>Reserved:</dt>
              <dd>
              <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be 0 on transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on reception.</dd>
              <dt>F Flag:</dt>
              <dd>When set, indicates flood reflection tunnel endpoint. When
              clear, indicates possible L1 shortcut tunnel endpoint.
              </dd>
              <dt>Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute:</dt>
              <dd>
                  Carries encapsulation type and further attributes necessary
                  for tunnel establishment as defined in <xref
                  target="RFC9012"/>. In context of this attribute, the
                  protocol Type sub-TLV as defined in <xref target="RFC9012"/>
                  <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be included to ensure proper
                  encapsulation of IS-IS frames. In case such a sub-TLV is
                  included and the F flag is set (i.e., the resulting tunnel is
                  a flood reflector adjacency), this sub-TLV
                  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include a type that allows to carry
                  encapsulated IS-IS frames. Furthermore, such tunnel type
                  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be able to transport IS-IS frames of
                  size up to "originatingL2LSPBufferSize".
              </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>A flood reflector
              receiving Flood Reflection Discovery Tunnel Type sub-sub-TLVs in Flood Reflection Discovery
              sub-TLV with F flag set (i.e., the resulting tunnel is a flood reflector adjacency)
              <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> use one or more of the specified tunnel endpoints to automatically establish one or more
              tunnels that will serve as a flood reflection adjacency and/or adjacencies to the clients advertising the endpoints.
              </t>
          <t>
              A flood reflection client
              receiving one or more Flood Reflection Discovery Tunnel Type sub-sub-TLVs in Flood Reflection Discovery
              sub-TLV with F flag clear (i.e., the resulting tunnel is used to support tunnel-based mode)
              from other leaves
              <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> use one or more of the specified tunnel endpoints to automatically establish one or more
              tunnels that will serve as L1 tunnel shortcuts to the clients advertising the endpoints.
          </t>
          <t>
              In case of automatic flood reflection adjacency tunnels and in case IS-IS adjacencies are being formed across
              L1 shortcuts, all the aforementioned rules in <xref target="sec_discovery"/> apply as well.
          </t>
          <t>
              Optional address validation procedures
              as defined in <xref target="RFC9012"/> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be disregarded.
          </t>
          <t>
              It remains to be observed that automatic tunnel discovery is an optional part of the specification
              and can be replaced or mixed with
              statically configured tunnels for flood reflector adjacencies and tunnel-based shortcuts.
              Specific implementation details how both mechanisms interact are specific to an implementation and
              mode of operation and are outside the scope of this document.
          </t>

          <!--
          <t>
              Once the tunnels are established based on auto discovery procedures, the "withdrawal" of previously
              seen
              Flood Reflection Discovery sub-TLV SHOULD NOT be used to tear down an already
              established tunnel.
          </t>

          -->

          <t>
              Flood reflector adjacencies rely on IS-IS L2 liveliness
              procedures. In case of L1 shortcuts, the mechanism used to
              ensure liveliness and tunnel integrity are outside the scope of
              this document.
          </t>
      </section>

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Flood Reflection Adjacency Sub-TLV</name>

      <t>The Flood Reflection Adjacency sub-TLV is advertised as a sub-TLV of
      TLVs 22, 23, 25, 141, 222, and 223 (the "TLVs Advertising Neighbor
      Information").  Its presence indicates that a given adjacency is a flood
      reflector adjacency.  It is included in L2 area scope flooded LSPs. The
      Flood Reflection Adjacency sub-TLV has the following format:
      </t>
      <artwork align="left" alt="" name="" type=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |    Length     |C|  Reserved   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                    Flood Reflection Cluster ID                |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>Type:</dt>
        <dd>161</dd>
        <dt>Length:</dt>
        <dd>The length, in octets, of the following fields.</dd>
        <dt>C (Client):</dt>
        <dd>This bit is set to indicate that the router advertising this
        adjacency is a flood reflector client. When this bit is NOT set, the
        router advertising this adjacency is a flood reflector.
                    </dd>
        <dt>Reserved:</dt>
        <dd>This field is reserved for future use.  It <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
        set to 0 when sent and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored when received.</dd>
        <dt>Flood Reflection Cluster ID:</dt>
        <dd>The Flood Reflection Cluster Identifier is the same as that
        defined in the Flood Reflection TLV in <xref target="sec_flood_reflection_tlv"/> and obeys the same rules.
          </dd>
      </dl>
      <t>The Flood Reflection Adjacency sub-TLV <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>
      appear more than once in a given TLV.  A router receiving one or more
      Flood Reflection Adjacency sub-TLVs in a TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the
      values in the first sub-TLV of the lowest numbered fragment, and it
      <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> log such violations subject to rate-limiting.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec_discovery" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Flood Reflection Discovery</name>
      <t>A router participating in flood reflection as client or reflector
      <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be configured as an L1/L2 router.  It
      <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> originate the Flood Reflection Discovery sub-TLV with
      area flooding scope in L1 and L2.  Normally, all routers on the edge of
      the L1 area (those having standard L2 adjacencies) will advertise
      themselves as flood reflector clients. Therefore, a flood reflector
      client will have both standard L2 adjacencies and flood reflector L2
      adjacencies.
      </t>
      <t>A router acting as a flood reflector <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> form any
      standard L2 adjacencies except with flood reflector clients.  It will
      be an L1/L2 router only by virtue of having flood reflector L2
      adjacencies.  A router desiring to act as a flood reflector
      <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> advertise itself as such using the Flood Reflection
      Discovery sub-TLV in L1 and L2.
      </t>
      <t>A given flood reflector or flood reflector client can only
      participate in a single cluster, as determined by the value of its Flood
      Reflection Cluster ID and should disregard other routers' TLVs for flood
      reflection purposes if the cluster ID is not matching.
      </t>
      <t>Upon reception of Flood Reflection Discovery sub-TLVs, a router
      acting as flood reflector <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> initiate a tunnel
      towards each flood reflector client with which it shares a Flood
      Reflection Cluster ID, using one or more of the tunnel encapsulations
      provided with F flag is set.  The L2 adjacencies formed over such
      tunnels <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be marked as flood reflector adjacencies.
      If the client or reflector has a direct L2 adjacency with the according
      remote side, it <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> use it instead of instantiating a
      tunnel.
          </t>
      <t>In case the optional auto-discovery mechanism is not implemented or
      enabled, a deployment <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> use statically configured
      tunnels to create flood reflection adjacencies.
      </t>
      <t>The IS-IS metrics for all flood reflection adjacencies in a cluster
      <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be identical.
        </t>
      <t>Upon reception of Flood Reflection Discovery TLVs, a router acting as
      a flood reflector client <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> initiate tunnels with
      L1-only adjacencies towards any of the other flood reflector clients
      with lower router IDs in its cluster using encapsulations with F flag
      clear. These tunnels <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be used for forwarding to
      improve the load-balancing characteristics of the L1 area.  If the
      clients have a direct L2 adjacency, they <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> use it
      instead of instantiating a new tunnel.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec_adj" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Flood Reflection Adjacency Formation</name>
      <t>
			In order to simplify implementation complexity, this document does not
			allow the formation of complex hierarchies of flood reflectors and clients or allow
            multiple clusters in a single L1 area.

          Consequently, all flood reflectors and flood reflector clients in the same L1 area <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> share the same
			Flood Reflector Cluster ID. Deployment of multiple cluster IDs in the same L1 area are outside the scope
            of this document.
        </t>
        <t>
                A flood reflector <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> form flood reflection adjacencies with flood reflector clients
                with a different Cluster ID.
                A flood reflector <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> form any standard L2 adjacencies.
        </t>
        <t>
                Flood reflector clients <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> form flood reflection adjacencies with flood reflectors
                with a different Cluster ID.
        </t>
        <t>
                Flood reflector clients <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> form standard L2 adjacencies with flood reflector clients
                or nodes not participating in flood reflection. When two flood reflector
                clients form a standard L2
                adjacency, the Cluster IDs are disregarded.
      </t>
      <t>
			The Flood Reflector Cluster ID and flood reflector
			roles advertised in the Flood Reflection TLVs in IIHs are used to ensure
			that flood reflection adjacencies that are established meet the above criteria.
      </t>
        <t>
                On change in either flood reflection role or cluster ID on IIH on the local or remote side,
            the adjacency has to be
                reset. It is then re-established if possible.
        </t>
      <t>
			Once a flood reflection adjacency is established, the flood reflector and the flood
			reflector client <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> advertise the adjacency by including the Flood Reflection Adjacency
			Sub-TLV in the Extended IS reachability TLV or Multi-Topology Intermediate System Neighbor (MT-ISN) TLV.</t>
    </section>
      </section>

    <section anchor="sec_route_comp" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Route Computation</name>
      <t>
			To ensure loop-free routing, the flood reflection client <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> follow the normal L2 computation
			to determine L2 routes. This is because nodes outside the L1 area will generally
			not be aware that flood reflection is being performed. The flood reflection clients
			need to produce the same result for the L2 route computation as a router not participating in
			flood reflection.
          </t>

        <section  numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Tunnel-Based Deployment</name>
       <t>
           In the tunnel-based option, the reflection client, after L2 and L1
           computation, <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> examine all L2 routes with flood reflector next-hop adjacencies.
           Such next hops must
           be replaced by the corresponding
           tunnel next hops to the correct egress nodes of the flood reflection cluster.
      </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="no_tunnels"  numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>No-Tunnel Deployment</name>

            <t>In case of deployment without underlying tunnels, the necessary
            L2 routes are distributed into the area, normally as L2->L1
            routes.  

   Due
   to the rules in <xref target="sec_adj"/>, the computation in the resulting topology
   is relatively simple: the L2 SPF from a flood reflector client is
   guaranteed to reach the Flood Reflector within a single hop, and in
   the following hop, it is guaranteed to reach the L2 egress to which
   it has a forwarding tunnel.

 All the flood reflector tunnel next hops in the according
            L2 route can hence be removed, and if the L2 route has no other
            ECMP L2 next hops, the L2 route <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be suppressed
            in the RIB by some means to allow the less preferred L2->L1 route
            to be used to forward traffic towards the advertising egress.
                </t>
            <t>In the particular case the client has L2 routes which are not
            flood reflected, those will be naturally preferred (such routes
            normally "hot-potato" packets out of the L1 area). However, in the
            case the L2 route through the flood reflector egress is "shorter"
            than such present L2 routes that are not flood reflected, the node
            <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> ensure that such routes are suppressed so
            the L2->L1 towards the egress still takes preference. Observe that
            operationally this can be resolved in a relatively simple way by
            configuring flood reflector adjacencies to have a high metric,
            i.e., the flood reflector topology becomes "last resort," and the
            leaves will try to "hot-potato" out the area as fast as possible,
            which is normally the desirable behavior.</t>

            <t>In no-tunnel deployment, all L1/L2 edge nodes <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
                flood reflection
                clients.</t>

          <t></t>
    </section>
    </section>

      <section anchor="sec_prefixes" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Redistribution of Prefixes</name>
          <t>
              In case of no-tunnel deployment per <xref target="no_tunnels"/>, a client that  does not
              have
              any L2 flood reflector adjacencies <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> redistribute L2 routes into
              the cluster.
</t>
          <t>
              The L2 prefix advertisements redistributed into an L1 that contains flood reflectors
              <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be normally limited to L2 intra-area routes (as defined in <xref target="RFC7775" format="default"/>)
              if the information exists to distinguish them from other L2 prefix advertisements.
          </t>
          <t>
              On the other hand, in topologies that make use of flood reflection to hide the structure of L1 areas
              while still providing transit-forwarding across them using tunnels, we generally do not need to
              redistribute L1 prefix advertisements into L2.
          </t>

      </section>

    <section anchor="patholody" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Special Considerations</name>
      <t>In pathological cases, setting the overload bit in L1 (but not in L2)
      can partition L1 forwarding, while allowing L2 reachability through
      flood reflector adjacencies to exist. In such a case, a node cannot
      replace a route through a flood reflector adjacency with an L1 shortcut,
      and the client <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> use the L2 tunnel to the flood
      reflector for forwarding. In all those cases, the node
      <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> initiate an alarm and declare misconfiguration.
      </t>
      <t>A flood reflector with directly L2 attached prefixes should advertise
      those in L1 as well since, based on preference of L1 routes, the clients
      will not try to use the L2 flood reflector adjacency to route the packet
      towards them. A very unlikely corner case can occur when the flood
      reflector is reachable via L2 flood reflector adjacency (due to
      underlying L1 partition) exclusively. In this instance, the client can use
      the L2 tunnel to the flood reflector for forwarding towards those
      prefixes while it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> initiate an alarm and declare
      misconfiguration.
      </t>
      <t>A flood reflector <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> set the attached bit on its
      LSPs.
      </t>
      <t>In certain cases where reflectors are attached to the same broadcast
      medium, and where some other L2 router that is neither a flood
      reflector nor a flood reflector client (a "non-FR router", i.e., a router not participating in flood reflection) attaches to
      the same broadcast medium, flooding between the reflectors in question
      might not succeed, potentially partitioning the flood reflection
      domain. This could happen specifically in the event that the non-FR
      router is chosen as the Designated Intermediate System (DIS) -- the
      designated router.  Since, per <xref target="sec_adj"/>, a flood
      reflector <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> form an adjacency with a non-FR
      router, the flood reflector(s) will not be represented in the
      pseudo-node.

          </t>
        <t>
          To avoid this situation, it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that flood reflectors not be deployed on the same broadcast
          medium as non-FR routers.

            </t>
        <t>
          A router discovering such condition
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> initiate an alarm and declare misconfiguration.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" toc="default" numbered="true">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>IANA has assigned the following IS-IS TLVs and sub-TLVs and has created a new registry.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>New IS-IS TLV Codepoint</name>
        <t>The following IS-IS TLV has been registered in the
            "IS-IS Top-Level TLV Codepoints" registry:</t>
<table anchor="is-is-tlv-codepoint" align="center">
  <name>Flood Reflection IS-IS TLV Codepoint</name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Value</th>
      <th>Name</th>
      <th>IIH</th>
      <th>LSP</th>
      <th>SNP</th>
      <th>Purge</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>161</td>
      <td>Flood Reflection</td>
      <td>y</td>
      <td>n</td>
      <td>n</td>
      <td>n</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
         </section>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Sub-TLVs for IS-IS Router CAPABILITY TLV</name>
        <t>The following has been registered in the "IS-IS Sub-TLVs
        for IS-IS Router CAPABILITY TLV" registry:</t>

<table anchor="is-is-router-capability" align="center">
  <name>IS-IS Router CAPABILITY TLV</name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Type</th>
      <th>Description</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>161</td>
      <td>Flood Reflection Discovery</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
         </section>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Sub-Sub-TLVs for Flood Reflection Discovery Sub-TLV</name>
            <t>IANA has created a new registry named
            "IS-IS Sub-Sub-TLVs for Flood Reflection Discovery Sub-TLV" under the
            "IS-IS TLV Codepoints" grouping.  The registration procedure for
            this registry is Expert Review <xref target="RFC8126"/>, following the common expert
            review guidance given for the grouping.
            </t>
            <t>The range of values in this registry is 0-255. The registry
            contains the following initial registration:</t>
<table anchor="sub-sub-tlv-flood-reflection" align="center">
  <name>IS-IS Sub-Sub-TLVs for Flood Reflection Discovery Sub-TLV</name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Type</th>
      <th>Description</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>161</td>
      <td>Flood Reflection Discovery Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
             </section>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Sub-TLVs for TLVs Advertising Neighbor Information</name>
        <t>The following has been registered in the "IS-IS
            Sub-TLVs for TLVs Advertising Neighbor Information" registry;

            </t>
<table anchor="sub-tlv-advertising-neighbor-info" align="center">
  <name>IS-IS Sub-TLVs for TLVs Advertising Neighbor Information</name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Type</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>22</th>
      <th>23</th>
      <th>25</th>
      <th>141</th>
      <th>222</th>
      <th>223</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>161</td>
      <td>Flood Reflector Adjacency</td>
      <td>y</td>
      <td>y</td>
      <td>n</td>
      <td>y</td>
      <td>y</td>
      <td>y</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document uses flood reflection tunnels to carry IS-IS control traffic.
          If an attacker can inject traffic into such a tunnel, the consequences could
          be (in the most extreme case) the complete subversion of the IS-IS Level 2 information.
          Therefore, a mechanism inherent to the tunnel technology should be used to prevent such injection.
          Since the available security procedures will vary by deployment and tunnel type,
          the details of securing tunnels are beyond the scope of this document.
</t>

        <t>
            This document specifies information used to form dynamically discovered shortcut tunnels.
            If an attacker were able to hijack the endpoint of such a tunnel and form an adjacency, it could divert
            shortcut traffic to itself,
            placing itself on-path and facilitating on-path attacks, or it could even completely subvert the IS-IS Level 2
            routing.
            Therefore, steps should be taken to prevent such capture by using mechanism inherent to the
            tunnel type used.
          Since the available security procedures will vary by deployment and tunnel type,
          the details of securing tunnels are beyond the scope of this document.
            </t>

<t>
   Additionally, the usual IS-IS security mechanisms <xref target="RFC5304"/> <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
   deployed to prevent misrepresentation of routing information by an
   attacker in case a tunnel is compromised and the tunnel itself does
   not provide mechanisms strong enough to guarantee the integrity of
   the messages exchanged.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5302.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5304.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7775.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7981.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9012.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="ISO10589">
          <front>
            <title>Information technology - Telecommunications and information
            exchange between systems - Intermediate System to Intermediate
            System intra-domain routeing information exchange protocol for use
            in conjunction with the protocol for providing the
            connectionless-mode network service (ISO 8473)</title>
            <author>
              <organization abbrev="ISO">International Organization for
            Standardization</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="November" year="2002"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="10589:2002"/>
          <refcontent>Second Edition</refcontent>
        </reference>
      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4456.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8099.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9107.xml"/>
</references> 
</references> 

<section numbered="false" toc="default">
<name>Acknowledgements</name> 

<t>The authors thank <contact fullname="Shraddha Hegde"/>, <contact
fullname="Peter Psenak"/>, <contact fullname="Acee Lindem"/>, <contact
fullname="Robert Raszuk"/>, and <contact fullname="Les Ginsberg"/> for their
thorough review and detailed discussions. Thanks are also extended to <contact
fullname="Michael Richardson"/> for an excellent routing directorate
review. <contact fullname="John Scudder"/> ultimately spent significant time
helping to make the document more comprehensible and coherent.  </t>
</section> 
</back>

</rfc>
