<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)
     by Daniel M Kohn (private) -->

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" docName="draft-ietf-alto-performance-metrics-28" number="9439" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="true" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">

  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.12.2 -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="ALTO Performance Cost Metrics">Application-Layer Traffic Optimization (ALTO) Performance Cost
    Metrics</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9439"/>
    <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
	  <extaddr>Yuhua District</extaddr>
          <street>101 Software Avenue</street>
          <city>Nanjing</city>
          <region>Jiangsu</region>
          <code>210012</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>bill.wu@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Y. Richard Yang" initials="Y." surname="Yang">
      <organization>Yale University</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>51 Prospect St.</street>
          <city>New Haven</city>
          <region>CT</region>
          <code>06520</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>yry@cs.yale.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Young Lee" initials="Y." surname="Lee">
      <organization>Samsung</organization>
      <address>
        <email>younglee.tx@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Dhruv Dhody" initials="D." surname="Dhody">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>dhruv.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Sabine Randriamasy" initials="S." surname="Randriamasy">
      <organization>Nokia Networks France</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sabine.randriamasy@nokia-bell-labs.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Luis Miguel Contreras Murillo" initials="L." surname="Contreras">
      <organization>Telefonica</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Madrid</city>
          <region/>
          <code/>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <email>luismiguel.contrerasmurillo@telefonica.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2023" month="August" />
    <area>tsv</area>
    <workgroup>alto</workgroup>
    <keyword>JavaScript Object Notation</keyword>
    <keyword>Application-Layer Traffic Optimization</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>The cost metric is a basic concept in Application-Layer Traffic
      Optimization (ALTO), and different applications may use different types
      of cost metrics. Since the ALTO base protocol (RFC 7285) defines only a
      single cost metric (namely, the generic "routingcost" metric), if an
      application wants to issue a cost map or an endpoint cost request in
      order to identify a resource provider that offers better performance
      metrics (e.g., lower delay or loss rate), the base protocol does not
      define the cost metric to be used.</t>
      <t>This document addresses this issue by extending the specification to
      provide a variety of network performance metrics, including network
      delay, delay variation (a.k.a.&nbsp;jitter), packet loss rate, hop count, and
      bandwidth.</t>
      <t>There are multiple sources (e.g., estimations based on measurements or
      a Service Level Agreement) available for deriving a performance metric. This document
      introduces an additional "cost-context" field to the ALTO "cost-type"
      field to convey the source of a performance metric.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="secintro" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Application-Layer Traffic Optimization (ALTO) provides a means for
      network applications to obtain network information so that the
      applications can identify efficient application-layer traffic patterns
      using the networks. Cost metrics are used in both the ALTO cost map
      service and the ALTO endpoint cost service in the ALTO base protocol
      <xref target="RFC7285" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>Since different applications may use different cost metrics, the ALTO
      base protocol introduced the "ALTO Cost Metrics" registry (<xref target="RFC7285" section="14.2" sectionFormat="of"/>) as a systematic mechanism to allow
      different metrics to be specified. For example, a delay-sensitive
      application may want to use latency-related metrics, and a
      bandwidth-sensitive application may want to use bandwidth-related
      metrics. However, the ALTO base protocol has registered only a single
      cost metric, i.e., the generic "routingcost" metric (<xref target="RFC7285" section="14.2" sectionFormat="of"/>); no latency- or bandwidth-related metrics
      are defined in the base protocol.</t>
      <t>This document registers a set of new cost metrics (<xref target="costmetric" sectionFormat="bare"/>) to allow
      applications to determine where to connect based on network
      performance criteria, including delay- and bandwidth-related metrics.</t>

      <table anchor="costmetric">
	<name>Cost Metrics Defined in This Document</name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Metric</th>
      <th>Definition in This Document</th>
      <th>Semantics Based On</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
<tr>
  <td>One-Way Delay</td>
  <td><xref target="oneway" sectionFormat="bare"/></td>
  <td>Base: <xref target="RFC7471"/> <xref target="RFC8570"/> <xref target="RFC8571"/>
  sum of Unidirectional Delay of links along the path</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Round-Trip Delay</td>
<td><xref target="delayrt" sectionFormat="bare"/></td>
<td>Base: Sum of two directions of Unidirectional Delay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>Delay Variation</td>
  <td><xref target="delayvar" sectionFormat="bare"/></td>
  <td>Base: <xref target="RFC7471"/> <xref target="RFC8570"/> <xref target="RFC8571"/>
  Sum of Unidirectional Delay Variation of links along the path</td> 
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>Loss Rate</td>
  <td><xref target="lossrate" sectionFormat="bare"/></td>
  <td>Base: <xref target="RFC7471"/> <xref target="RFC8570"/> <xref target="RFC8571"/>
  aggr Unidirectional Link Loss</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>Residual Bandwidth</td>
  <td><xref target="bwresidual" sectionFormat="bare"/></td>
  <td>Base: <xref target="RFC7471"/> <xref target="RFC8570"/> <xref target="RFC8571"/>
  min Unidirectional Residual BW</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>Available Bandwidth</td>
  <td><xref target="bwavailable" sectionFormat="bare"/></td>
  <td>Base: <xref target="RFC7471"/> <xref target="RFC8570"/> <xref target="RFC8571"/>
  min Unidirectional Available BW</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>TCP Throughput</td>
  <td><xref target="tput" sectionFormat="bare"/></td>
  <td><xref target="RFC9438"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>Hop Count</td>
  <td><xref target="hopcount" sectionFormat="bare"/></td>
  <td><xref target="RFC7285"/></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
      <t>The first six metrics listed in <xref target="costmetric" sectionFormat="bare"/> (i.e., one-way delay,
      round-trip delay, delay variation, loss rate, residual bandwidth, and
      available bandwidth) are derived from the set of Traffic Engineering (TE)
      performance metrics commonly defined in OSPF <xref target="RFC3630" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC7471" format="default"/>, IS-IS <xref target="RFC5305" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC8570" format="default"/>, and BGP - Link State (BGP-LS)
      <xref target="RFC8571" format="default"/>. Deriving ALTO cost performance metrics
      from existing network-layer TE performance metrics, and making it exposed to ALTO, can be a typical
      mechanism used by network operators to deploy ALTO <xref target="RFC7971" format="default"/> <xref target="FlowDirector" format="default"/>. This
      document defines the base semantics of these metrics by extending them
      from link metrics to end-to-end metrics for ALTO. The "Semantics Based
      On" column specifies at a high level how the end-to-end metrics are
      computed from link metrics; details will be specified in the
      following sections.</t>
      <t>The Min/Max Unidirectional Link Delay metric as defined in
      <xref target="RFC8570"/> and <xref target="RFC8571"/>, and Maximum (Link) Bandwidth as defined in <xref target="RFC3630"/> and <xref target="RFC5305"/>,
      are not listed in <xref target="costmetric" sectionFormat="bare"/> because they can be handled by applying the
      statistical operators defined in this document. The metrics related to
      utilized bandwidth and reservable bandwidth (i.e., Maximum Reservable (Link) Bandwidth and Unreserved Bandwidth as defined in <xref target="RFC3630"/> and <xref target="RFC5305"/>) are outside the scope of
      this document.</t>
      <t>The seventh metric in <xref target="costmetric"         
sectionFormat="bare"/> (the estimated TCP-flow throughput metric) provides an
      estimation of the bandwidth of a TCP flow, using TCP throughput
      modeling, to support use cases of adaptive applications <xref target="Prophet" format="default"/> <xref target="G2" format="default"/>. Note that other
      transport-specific metrics can be defined in the future. For example,
      QUIC-related metrics <xref target="RFC9000" format="default"/> can be considered
      when the methodology for measuring such metrics is more mature (e.g., see <xref target="I-D.corre-quic-throughput-testing" format="default"/>).</t>
      <t>The eighth metric in <xref target="costmetric"         
sectionFormat="bare"/> (the hop count metric) is mentioned, but not defined, in the
      ALTO base protocol <xref target="RFC7285"/>; this document provides a definition for it.</t>
      <t>These eight performance metrics can be classified into two categories:
      those derived from the performance of individual packets (i.e., one-way
      delay, round-trip delay, delay variation, loss rate, and hop count) and
      those related to bandwidth/throughput (residual bandwidth, available
      bandwidth, and TCP throughput). These two categories are defined in
      Sections&nbsp;<xref format="counter" target="secpktmetrics"/> and <xref format="counter" target="secbwmetrics"/>, respectively. Note that
      all metrics except round-trip delay are unidirectional. An ALTO client
      will need to query both directions if needed.</t>
      <t>The purpose of this document is to ensure proper usage of these eight
      performance metrics in the context of ALTO. This document follows the
      guidelines defined in <xref target="RFC7285" sectionFormat="of" section="14.2"/>
on registering ALTO cost metrics. Hence, it
      specifies the identifier, the intended semantics, and the security
      considerations of each one of the metrics specified in <xref target="costmetric" sectionFormat="bare"/>.</t>
      <t>The definitions of the intended semantics of the metrics tend to be
      coarse grained and are for guidance only, and they may work well for ALTO. On
      the other hand, a performance measurement framework, such as the IP
      Performance Metrics (IPPM) framework, may provide more details for
      defining a performance metric. This document introduces a mechanism
      called "cost-context" to provide additional details, when they are
      available; see <xref target="sec3" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>Following the ALTO base protocol, this document uses JSON to specify
      the value type of each defined metric. See <xref target="RFC8259" format="default"/> for JSON data type specifications. In
      particular, <xref target="RFC7285" format="default"/> specifies that cost values
      should be assumed by default to be 'JSONNumber'. When defining the value
      representation of each metric in <xref target="costmetric" sectionFormat="bare"/>, this document conforms to
      <xref target="RFC7285"/> but specifies additional, generic constraints on valid
      JSONNumbers for each metric. For example, each new metric in <xref target="costmetric" sectionFormat="bare"/>
      will be specified as non-negative (&gt;= 0); Hop Count is specified to
      be an integer.</t>
      <t>An ALTO server may provide only a subset of the metrics described in
      this document. For example, those that are subject to privacy concerns
      should not be provided to unauthorized ALTO clients. Hence, all cost
      metrics defined in this document are optional; not all of them need to
      be exposed to a given application. When an ALTO server supports a cost
      metric defined in this document, it announces the metric in its
      information resource directory (IRD) as defined in <xref target="RFC7285" section="9.2" sectionFormat="of"/>.</t>
      <t>An ALTO server introducing these metrics should consider related
      security issues. As a generic security consideration regarding reliability
      and trust in the exposed metric values, applications <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> 
      promptly stop using ALTO-based guidance if they detect that the exposed information
      does not preserve their performance level or even degrades it. <xref target="secsecconsider" format="default"/> discusses security considerations in
      more detail.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Requirements Language</name>
       <t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
       "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>",
       "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>",
       "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
       "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
       "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document
       are to be interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14
       <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
       when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec3" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Performance Metric Attributes</name>
      <t>The definitions of the metrics in this document are coarse grained,
      based on network-layer TE performance metrics, and for
      guidance only. A fine-grained framework as specified in <xref target="RFC6390" format="default"/> requires that the fine-grained specification of
      a network performance metric include six components: (1) Metric Name, (2)
      Metric Description, (3) Method of Measurement or Calculation, (4)
      Units of Measurement, (5) Measurement Points, and (6) Measurement
      Timing. Requiring that an ALTO server provide precise, fine-grained
      values for all six components for each metric that it exposes may not be
      feasible or necessary for all ALTO use cases. For example, an ALTO
      server computing its metrics from network-layer TE
      performance metrics may not have information about the method of
      measurement or calculation (e.g., measured traffic patterns).</t>
      <t>To address the issue and realize ALTO use cases for the metrics listed in <xref target="costmetric" sectionFormat="bare"/>, this document defines performance metric identifiers that can be
      used in the ALTO Protocol with the following well-defined items: (1) Metric Name, (2) Metric
      Description, (3) Units of Measurement, and (4) Measurement Points,
      which are always specified by the specific ALTO services; for example,
      the endpoint cost service is between the two endpoints. Hence, the ALTO
      performance metric identifiers provide basic metric attributes.</t>
      <t>To allow the flexibility of allowing an ALTO server to provide
      fine-grained information such as Method of Measurement or Calculation
      according to its policy and use cases, this document introduces context
      information so that the server can provide these additional details.</t>
      <section anchor="meta" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Performance Metric Context: "cost-context"</name>
        <t>The core additional details of a performance metric specify how
        the metric is obtained. This is referred to as the source of the
        metric. Specifically, this document defines three types of
        coarse-grained metric information sources: "nominal", "sla", and "estimation".</t>
        <t>For a given type of source, precise interpretation of a performance
        metric value can depend on specific measurement and computation
        parameters.</t>
        <t>To make it possible to specify the source and the aforementioned
        parameters, this document introduces an optional "cost-context" field
        to the "cost-type" field defined by the ALTO base protocol (<xref target="RFC7285" section="10.7" sectionFormat="of"/>) as follows:</t>
        <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[    object {
      CostMetric   cost-metric;
      CostMode     cost-mode;
      [CostContext cost-context;]
      [JSONString  description;]
    } CostType;

    object {
      JSONString    cost-source;
      [JSONValue    parameters;]
    } CostContext;                   
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>"cost-context" will not be used as a key to distinguish among
        performance metrics. Hence, an ALTO information resource <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>
        announce multiple CostType entries with the same "cost-metric", "cost-mode",
        and "cost-context". They must be placed into different information
        resources.</t>
        <t>The "cost-source" field of the "cost-context" field is defined as a
        string consisting of only ASCII alphanumeric characters
        (U+0030-U+0039, U+0041-U+005A, and U+0061-U+007A). The "cost-source" field is
        used in this document to indicate a string of this format.</t>
        <t>As mentioned above, this document defines three values for
        "cost-source": "nominal", "sla", and "estimation". The "cost-source"
        field of the "cost-context" field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one that is registered in the "ALTO Cost
        Source Types" registry (<xref target="ianaconsider"/>).</t>
        <t>The "nominal" category indicates that the metric value is
        statically configured by the underlying devices. Not all metrics have
        reasonable "nominal" values. For example, throughput can have a
        nominal value, which indicates the configured transmission rate of the
        involved devices; latency typically does not have a nominal value.</t>
        <t>The "sla" category indicates that the metric value is derived from
        some commitment, which this document refers to as a Service Level Agreement (SLA). Some operators also use terms such as "target" or
        "committed" values. For an "sla" metric, it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that the
        "parameters" field provide a link to the SLA definition.</t>
        <t>The "estimation" category indicates that the metric value is
        computed through an estimation process. An ALTO server may compute
        "estimation" values by retrieving and/or aggregating information from
        routing protocols (e.g., see <xref target="RFC7471" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC8570" format="default"/>, and <xref target="RFC8571" format="default"/>), traffic
        measurement management tools (e.g., the Two-Way Active Measurement Protocol (TWAMP) <xref target="RFC5357" format="default"/>), and measurement frameworks (e.g., IPPM),
        with corresponding operational issues. An illustration of potential
        information flows used for estimating these metrics is shown in <xref target="fig1"/>. <xref target="secopconsider" format="default"/> discusses in more detail the
        operational issues and how a network may address them. </t>
	<figure anchor="fig1">
	  <name>A Framework to Compute Estimation of Performance Metrics</name>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
  +--------+   +--------+  +--------+
  | Client |   | Client |  | Client |
  +----^---+   +---^----+  +---^----+
       |           |           |
       +-----------|-----------+
                   |ALTO Protocol
                   |
                   |
                +--+-----+  retrieval      +-----------+
                |  ALTO  |<----------------| Routing   |
                | Server |  and aggregation| Protocols |
                |        |<-------------+  |           |
                +--------+              |  +-----------+
                                        |
                                        |  +------------+
                                        |  |Performance |
                                        ---| Monitoring |
                                           |  Tools     |
                                           +------------+
]]></artwork>
	</figure>
        <t>There can be multiple options available when choosing the "cost-source" category; the operator of an ALTO server will make that choice. If a
        metric does not include a "cost-source" value, the application <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
        assume that the value of "cost-source" is the most generic source,
        i.e., "estimation".</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="percentile" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Performance Metric Statistics</name>
        <t>The measurement of a performance metric often yields a set of
        samples from an observation distribution <xref target="Prometheus" format="default"/>, instead of a single value. A statistical
        operator is applied to the samples to obtain a value to be reported to
        the client. Multiple statistical operators (e.g., min, median, and
        max) are commonly being used.</t>
        <t>Hence, this document extends the general ASCII alphanumeric cost
        metric strings, formally specified as the CostMetric type defined in
        <xref target="RFC7285" sectionFormat="of" section="10.6"/>, as follows:</t>
          <t indent="3">A cost metric string consists of a base metric identifier (or
            base identifier for short) string, followed by an optional
            statistical operator string, connected by the ASCII 
            colon character (':', U+003A), if the statistical operator string exists.
            The total length of the cost metric string <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> exceed 32, as
            required by <xref target="RFC7285"/>.</t>
        <t>The statistical operator string <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of the following:</t>
        <dl>
          <dt>cur:</dt>
          <dd>The instantaneous
            observation value of the metric from the most recent sample (i.e.,
            the current value).</dd>
          <dt>percentile, with the letter 'p' followed by a number:</dt>
          <dd>Gives the percentile specified by the number
            following the letter 'p'. The number <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a non-negative JSON
            number in the range [0, 100] (i.e., greater than or equal to 0 and
            less than or equal to 100), followed by an optional decimal part,
            if higher precision is needed. The decimal part should start
            with the '.' separator (U+002E) and be followed by a sequence of one
            or more ASCII numbers between '0' and '9'. Assume that this number is y,
            and consider the case where the samples are coming from a random variable X. The
            metric then returns x, such that the probability of X is less than or
            equal to x, i.e., Prob(X &lt;= x), = y/100. For example,
            delay-ow:p99 gives the 99th percentile of observed one-way delay;
            delay-ow:p99.9 gives the 99.9th percentile. Note that some systems
            use quantile, which is in the range [0, 1]. When there is a more
            common form for a given percentile, it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that the
            common form be used; that is, instead of p0, use min; instead of
            p50, use median; instead of p100, use max.</dd>
          <dt>min:</dt>
          <dd>The minimal value of
            the observations.</dd>
          <dt>max:</dt>
          <dd>The maximal value of
            the observations.</dd>
          <dt>median:</dt>
          <dd>The midpoint
            (i.e., p50) of the observations.</dd>
          <dt>mean:</dt>
          <dd>The arithmetic mean
            value of the observations.</dd>
          <dt>stddev:</dt>
          <dd>The standard
            deviation of the observations.</dd>
          <dt>stdvar:</dt>
          <dd>The standard
            variance of the observations.</dd>
        </dl>
        <t>Examples of cost metric strings then include "delay-ow",
        "delay-ow:min", and "delay-ow:p99", where "delay-ow" is the base metric
        identifier string; "min" and "p99" are example statistical operator
        strings.</t>
        <t>If a cost metric string does not have the optional statistical
        operator string, the statistical operator <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be interpreted as the
        default statistical operator in the definition of the base metric. If
        the definition of the base metric does not provide a definition for
        the default statistical operator, the metric <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be considered the
        median value.</t>
        <t>Note that <xref target="RFC7285"/> limits the overall cost metric identifier to 32
        characters. The cost metric variants with statistical operator
        suffixes defined by this document are also subject to the same overall
        32-character limit, so certain combinations of (long) base metric
        identifiers and statistical operators will not be representable. If such
        a situation arises, it could be addressed by defining a new base
        metric identifier that is an "alias" of the desired base metric, with
        identical semantics and just a shorter name.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="secpktmetrics" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Packet Performance Metrics</name>
      <t>This section introduces ALTO network performance metrics on one-way
      delay, round-trip delay, delay variation, packet loss rate, and hop
      count. They measure the "quality of experience" of the stream of packets
      sent from a resource provider to a resource consumer. The measurements of
      each individual packet (pkt) can include the delay from the time when
      the packet enters the network to the time when the packet leaves the
      network (pkt.delay), whether the packet is dropped before reaching the
      destination (pkt.dropped), and the number of network hops that the packet
      traverses (pkt.hopcount). The semantics of the performance metrics
      defined in this section are that they are statistics computed from these
      measurements; for example, the x-percentile of the one-way delay is the
      x-percentile of the set of delays {pkt.delay} for the packets in the
      stream.</t>
      <section anchor="oneway" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Cost Metric: One-Way Delay (delay-ow)</name>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Base Identifier</name>
          <t>The base identifier for this performance metric is
          "delay-ow".</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Value Representation</name>
          <t>The metric value type is a single 'JSONNumber' type value
          conforming to the number specifications provided in <xref target="RFC8259" sectionFormat="of" section="6"/>.
          The unit is expressed in microseconds. Hence, the number can be a
          floating-point number to express delay that is smaller than
          microseconds. The number <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be non-negative.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Intended Semantics and Use</name>
      <dl>
          <dt>Intended Semantics:</dt><dd>To specify the temporal and spatial
          aggregated delay of a stream of packets from the specified source to
          the specified destination. The base semantics of the metric is the
          Unidirectional Delay metric as defined in <xref target="RFC8571"/>, <xref target="RFC8570"/>, and <xref target="RFC7471"/>,
          but instead of specifying the delay for a link, it is the (temporal)
          aggregation of the link delays from the source to the destination. A
          non-normative reference definition of the end-to-end one-way delay metric is provided in
          <xref target="RFC7679" format="default"/>. The spatial aggregation level is
          specified in the query context, e.g., provider-defined identifier
          (PID) to PID, or endpoint to endpoint, where the PID is as defined in
          <xref target="RFC7285" sectionFormat="of" section="5.1"/>.</dd>
          <dt>Use:</dt>
          <dd>This metric could be used as a cost metric constraint
          attribute or as a returned cost metric in the response.</dd>
      </dl>
      <figure anchor="example-1">
        <name>Delay Value on Source-Destination Endpoint Pairs (Example 1)</name>
          <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
POST /endpointcost/lookup HTTP/1.1
Host: alto.example.com
Content-Length: 239
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcostparams+json
Accept: 
  application/alto-endpointcost+json,application/alto-error+json

{
  "cost-type": {
    "cost-mode":   "numerical",
    "cost-metric": "delay-ow"
  },
  "endpoints": {
    "srcs": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.2"
    ],
    "dsts": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89",
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34"
    ]
  }
}

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Length: 247
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcost+json

{
  "meta": {
    "cost-type": {
      "cost-mode":   "numerical",
      "cost-metric": "delay-ow"
    }
  },
  "endpoint-cost-map": {
    "ipv4:192.0.2.2": {
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89":    10,
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34": 20
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
      </figure>
          <t>Note that since the "cost-type" does not include the
          "cost-source" field, the values are based on "estimation". Since the
          identifier does not include the statistical operator string
          component, the values will represent median values.</t>
          <t><xref target="example-1a"/> shows an example that is similar to Example 1 (<xref target="example-1"/>), but for IPv6.</t>
      <figure anchor="example-1a">
        <name>Delay Value on Source-Destination Endpoint Pairs for IPv6 (Example 1a)</name>
          <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
POST /endpointcost/lookup HTTP/1.1
Host: alto.example.com
Content-Length: 252
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcostparams+json
Accept: 
  application/alto-endpointcost+json,application/alto-error+json

{
  "cost-type": {
    "cost-mode":   "numerical",
    "cost-metric": "delay-ow"
  },
  "endpoints": {
    "srcs": [
      "ipv6:2001:db8:100::1"
    ],
    "dsts": [
      "ipv6:2001:db8:100::2",
      "ipv6:2001:db8:100::3"
    ]
  }
}

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Length: 257
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcost+json

{
  "meta": {
    "cost-type": {
      "cost-mode":   "numerical",
      "cost-metric": "delay-ow"
    }
  },
  "endpoint-cost-map": {
    "ipv6:2001:db8:100::1": {
      "ipv6:2001:db8:100::2": 10,
      "ipv6:2001:db8:100::3": 20
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
      </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="ccspec-ow" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Cost-Context Specification Considerations</name>
	  <dl>
          <dt>"nominal":</dt><dd>Typically, network one-way delay does not have a
          nominal value.</dd>
          <dt>"sla":</dt><dd>Many networks provide delay-related parameters in their
          application-level SLAs. It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that the "parameters"
          field of an "sla" one-way delay metric include a link (i.e., a field
          named "link") providing a URI for the specification of SLA details,
          if available. Such a specification can be either (1)&nbsp;free text for
          possible presentation to the user or (2)&nbsp;a formal specification. The
          format of the specification is outside the scope of this
          document.</dd>
          <dt>"estimation":</dt><dd>The exact estimation method is outside the scope of
          this document. There can be multiple sources for estimating one-way
          delay. For example, the ALTO server may estimate the end-to-end
          delay by aggregation of routing protocol link metrics; the server
          may also estimate the delay using active, end-to-end measurements --
          for example, using the IPPM framework <xref target="RFC2330" format="default"/>.</dd>
	  </dl>
          <t>If the estimation is computed by aggregation of routing protocol
          link metrics (e.g., Unidirectional Link Delay metrics for OSPF <xref target="RFC7471" format="default"/>, IS-IS <xref target="RFC8570" format="default"/>, or BGP-LS <xref target="RFC8571" format="default"/>), it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that the
          "parameters" field of an "estimation" one-way delay metric include
          the following information: (1) the RFC defining the routing protocol
          metrics (e.g., see <xref target="RFC7471"/> for
          derived metrics), (2) configurations of the routing link metrics
          such as configured intervals, and (3) the aggregation method from
          link metrics to end-to-end metrics. During aggregation from link
          metrics to end-to-end metrics, the server should be cognizant of
          potential issues when computing an end-to-end summary statistic from
          link statistics. The default end-to-end average one-way delay is the
          sum of average link one-way delays. If an ALTO server provides the
          min and max statistical operators for the one-way delay metric, the
          values can be computed directly from the routing link metrics, as
          <xref target="RFC7471"/>, <xref target="RFC8570"/>, and <xref target="RFC8571"/> provide Min/Max Unidirectional Link
          Delay.</t>
          <t>If the estimation is from the IPPM measurement framework, it is
          <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that the "parameters" field of an "estimation" one-way
          delay metric include the URI in the "URI"
          field of the IPPM metric defined in the IPPM "Performance Metrics" registry
          <xref target="IANA-IPPM" format="default"/> (e.g.,
<eref target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/performance-metrics/OWDelay_Active_IP-UDP-Poisson-Payload250B_RFC8912sec7_Seconds_95Percentile" brackets="angle"/>).
          The IPPM metric <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one-way delay (i.e., IPPM OWDelay* metrics).
          The statistical operator of the ALTO metric <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be consistent with
          the IPPM statistical property (e.g., 95th percentile).</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="delayrt" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Cost Metric: Round-Trip Delay (delay-rt)</name>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Base Identifier</name>
          <t>The base identifier for this performance metric is
          "delay-rt".</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Value Representation</name>
          <t>The metric value type is a single 'JSONNumber' type value
          conforming to the number specifications provided in <xref target="RFC8259" sectionFormat="of" section="6"/>.
          The number <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be non-negative. The unit is expressed in
          microseconds.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Intended Semantics and Use</name>
      <dl>
          <dt>Intended Semantics:</dt><dd><t>To specify temporal and spatial aggregated
          round-trip delay between the specified source and specified
          destination. The base semantics is that it is the sum of the one-way
          delay from the source to the destination and the one-way delay from
          the destination back to the source, where the one-way delay is as
          defined in <xref target="oneway"/>. A non-normative reference definition of the
          end-to-end round-trip delay metric is provided in <xref target="RFC2681" format="default"/>. The
          spatial aggregation level is specified in the query context (e.g.,
          PID to PID, or endpoint to endpoint).</t>
          <t>Note that it is possible for a client to query two one-way delay
          (delay-ow) items and then compute the round-trip delay. The server should
          be cognizant of the consistency of values.</t></dd>
          <dt>Use:</dt>
          <dd>This metric could be used as a cost metric constraint
          attribute or as a returned cost metric in the response.</dd>
      </dl>
     <figure anchor="example-2">
       <name>Round-Trip Delay of Source-Destination Endpoint Pairs (Example 2)</name>
          <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
POST /endpointcost/lookup HTTP/1.1
Host: alto.example.com
Content-Length: 238
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcostparams+json
Accept: 
  application/alto-endpointcost+json,application/alto-error+json

{
  "cost-type": {
    "cost-mode":   "numerical",
    "cost-metric": "delay-rt"
  },
  "endpoints": {
    "srcs": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.2"
    ],
    "dsts": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89",
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34"
    ]
  }
}

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Length: 245
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcost+json

{
  "meta": {
    "cost-type": {
      "cost-mode":   "numerical",
      "cost-metric": "delay-rt"
    }
  },
  "endpoint-cost-map": {
    "ipv4:192.0.2.2": {
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89":    4,
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34": 3
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
     </figure>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Cost-Context Specification Considerations</name>
        <dl>
          <dt>"nominal":</dt><dd>Typically, network round-trip delay does not have a
          nominal value.</dd>
          <dt>"sla":</dt><dd>See the "sla" entry in <xref target="ccspec-ow" format="default"/>.</dd>
          <dt>"estimation":</dt><dd>See the "estimation" entry in <xref target="ccspec-ow" format="default"/>. For estimation by aggregation of routing
          protocol link metrics, the aggregation should include all links from
          the source to the destination and then back to the source; for
          estimation using IPPM, the IPPM metric <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be round-trip delay
          (i.e., IPPM RTDelay* metrics). The statistical operator of the ALTO
          metric <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be consistent with the IPPM statistical property (e.g.,
          95th percentile).</dd>
	</dl>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="delayvar" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Cost Metric: Delay Variation (delay-variation)</name>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Base Identifier</name>
          <t>The base identifier for this performance metric is
          "delay-variation".</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Value Representation</name>
          <t>The metric value type is a single 'JSONNumber' type value
          conforming to the number specifications provided in <xref target="RFC8259" sectionFormat="of" section="6"/>.
          The number <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be non-negative. The unit is expressed in
          microseconds.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Intended Semantics and Use</name>
	  <dl>
          <dt>Intended Semantics:</dt><dd><t>To specify temporal and spatial aggregated
          delay variation (also called delay jitter) with respect to the
          minimum delay observed on the stream over the one-way delay from the
          specified source and destination, where the one-way delay is as defined
          in <xref target="oneway"/>. A non-normative reference definition of the end-to-end
          one-way delay variation metric is provided in <xref target="RFC3393" format="default"/>. Note that
          <xref target="RFC3393" format="default"/> allows the specification of a generic
          selection function F to unambiguously define the two packets
          selected to compute delay variations. This document defines the
          specific case where F selects the packet with the smallest one-way
          delay as the "first" packet. The spatial aggregation level is specified
          in the query context (e.g., PID to PID, or endpoint to
          endpoint).</t>
          <t>Note that in statistics, variation is typically evaluated by
          the distance from samples relative to the mean. In the context of networking, it is more commonly defined from samples relative to the
          min. This definition follows the networking convention.</t>
</dd>         
	      <dt>Use:</dt>
              <dd>This metric could be used as a cost metric constraint
              attribute or as a returned cost metric in the response.</dd>
	    </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-3">
           <name>Delay Variation Value on Source-Destination Endpoint Pairs (Example 3)</name>
          <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
POST /endpointcost/lookup HTTP/1.1
Host: alto.example.com
Content-Length: 245
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcostparams+json
Accept: 
   application/alto-endpointcost+json,application/alto-error+json

{
  "cost-type": {
    "cost-mode":   "numerical",
    "cost-metric": "delay-variation"
  },
  "endpoints": {
    "srcs": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.2"
    ],
    "dsts": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89",
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34"
    ]
  }
}

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Length: 252
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcost+json

{
  "meta": {
    "cost-type": {
      "cost-mode":   "numerical",
      "cost-metric": "delay-variation"
    }
  },
  "endpoint-cost-map": {
    "ipv4:192.0.2.2": {
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89":    0,
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34": 1
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
	  </figure>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Cost-Context Specification Considerations</name>
          <dl>
          <dt>"nominal":</dt><dd>Typically, network delay variation does not have a
          nominal value.</dd>
          <dt>"sla":</dt><dd>See the "sla" entry in <xref target="ccspec-ow" format="default"/>.</dd>
          <dt>"estimation":</dt><dd>See the "estimation" entry in <xref target="ccspec-ow" format="default"/>. For estimation by aggregation of routing
          protocol link metrics, the default aggregation of the average of
          delay variations is the sum of the link delay variations; for
          estimation using IPPM, the IPPM metric <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be delay variation
          (i.e., IPPM OWPDV* metrics). The statistical operator of the ALTO
          metric <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be consistent with the IPPM statistical property (e.g.,
          95th percentile).</dd>
	  </dl>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="lossrate" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Cost Metric: Loss Rate (lossrate)</name>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Base Identifier</name>
          <t>The base identifier for this performance metric is
          "lossrate".</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Value Representation</name>
          <t>The metric value type is a single 'JSONNumber' type value
          conforming to the number specifications provided in <xref target="RFC8259" sectionFormat="of" section="6"/>.
          The number <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be non-negative. The value represents the percentage
          of packet losses.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Intended Semantics and Use</name>
	  <dl>
          <dt>Intended Semantics:</dt><dd>To specify the temporal and spatial aggregated
          one-way packet loss rate from the specified source and the specified
          destination. The base semantics of the metric is the Unidirectional
          Link Loss metric as defined in <xref target="RFC8571"/>, <xref target="RFC8570"/>, and <xref target="RFC7471"/>, but instead
          of specifying the loss for a link, it is the aggregated loss of all
          links from the source to the destination. The spatial aggregation
          level is specified in the query context (e.g., PID to PID, or
          endpoint to endpoint).</dd>
    <dt>Use:</dt>
     <dd>This metric could be used as a cost metric constraint
              attribute or as a returned cost metric in the response.</dd>
	    </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-4">
           <name>Loss Rate Value on Source-Destination Endpoint Pairs (Example 4)</name>
          <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
POST /endpointcost/lookup HTTP/1.1
Host: alto.example.com
Content-Length: 238
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcostparams+json
Accept: 
  application/alto-endpointcost+json,application/alto-error+json

{
  "cost-type": {
    "cost-mode":   "numerical",
    "cost-metric": "lossrate"
  },
  "endpoints": {
    "srcs": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.2"
    ],
    "dsts": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89",
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34"
    ]
  }
}

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Length: 248
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcost+json

{
  "meta": {
    "cost-type": {
      "cost-mode":   "numerical",
      "cost-metric": "lossrate"
    }
  },
  "endpoint-cost-map": {
    "ipv4:192.0.2.2": {
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89":    0,
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34": 0.01
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode></figure>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Cost-Context Specification Considerations</name>
	  <dl>
            <dt>"nominal":</dt>
	    <dd>Typically, the packet loss rate does not have a nominal
          value, although some networks may specify zero losses.</dd>
          <dt>"sla":</dt>
	  <dd>See the "sla" entry in <xref target="ccspec-ow" format="default"/>.</dd>
          <dt>"estimation":</dt>
	  <dd>See the "estimation" entry in
          <xref target="ccspec-ow" format="default"/>. For estimation
          by aggregation of routing protocol link metrics, the default
          aggregation of the average loss rate is the sum of the
          link loss rates. But this default aggregation is valid
          only if two conditions are met: (1) link loss rates are low and (2) one assumes that each link's
          loss events are uncorrelated with every other link's loss
          events. When loss rates at the links are high but
          independent, the general formula for aggregating loss,
          assuming that each link is independent, is to compute end-to-end
          loss as one minus the product of the success rate for each
          link. Aggregation when losses at links are correlated can be
          more complex, and the ALTO server should be cognizant of
          correlated loss rates. For estimation using IPPM, the IPPM
          metric <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be packet loss (i.e., IPPM
          OWLoss* metrics). The statistical operator of the ALTO
          metric <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be consistent with the IPPM
          statistical property (e.g., 95th percentile).</dd>
	</dl>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="hopcount" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Cost Metric: Hop Count (hopcount)</name>
        <t>The hop count (hopcount) metric is mentioned in <xref target="RFC7285" sectionFormat="of" section="9.2.3"/>
as an example. This section further clarifies
        its properties.</t>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Base Identifier</name>
          <t>The base identifier for this performance metric is
          "hopcount".</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Value Representation</name>
          <t>The metric value type is a single 'JSONNumber' type value
          conforming to the number specifications provided in <xref target="RFC8259" sectionFormat="of" section="6"/>.
          The number <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a non-negative integer (greater than or equal to
          0). The value represents the number of hops.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Intended Semantics and Use</name>
          <dl>
          <dt>Intended Semantics:</dt>
	  <dd>To specify the number of hops in the path
          from the specified source to the specified destination. The hop
          count is a basic measurement of distance in a network and can be
          exposed as the number of router hops computed from the routing
          protocols originating this information. A hop, however, may
          represent other units. The spatial aggregation level is specified in
          the query context (e.g., PID to PID, or endpoint to endpoint).</dd>
         
	      <dt>Use:</dt>
              <dd>This metric could be used as a cost metric constraint
              attribute or as a returned cost metric in the response.</dd>
	    </dl>
	  <figure anchor="example-5">
           <name>Hop Count Value on Source-Destination Endpoint Pairs (Example 5)</name>
          <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
POST /endpointcost/lookup HTTP/1.1
Host: alto.example.com
Content-Length: 238
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcostparams+json
Accept: 
  application/alto-endpointcost+json,application/alto-error+json

{
  "cost-type": {
    "cost-mode":   "numerical",
    "cost-metric": "hopcount"
  },
  "endpoints": {
    "srcs": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.2"
    ],
    "dsts": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89",
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34"
    ]
  }
}

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Length: 245
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcost+json

{
  "meta": {
    "cost-type": {
      "cost-mode":   "numerical",
      "cost-metric": "hopcount"
    }
  },
  "endpoint-cost-map": {
    "ipv4:192.0.2.2": {
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89":    5,
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34": 3
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode></figure>
       </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Cost-Context Specification Considerations</name>
          <dl>
          <dt>"nominal":</dt><dd>Typically, the hop count does not have a nominal value.</dd>
          <dt>"sla":</dt><dd>Typically, the hop count does not have an SLA value.</dd>
          <dt>"estimation":</dt><dd>The exact estimation method is outside the scope of
          this document. An example of estimating hop count values is by importing
          from IGP routing protocols. It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that the "parameters"
          field of an "estimation" hop count define the meaning of a hop.</dd>
	  </dl>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="secbwmetrics" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Throughput/Bandwidth Performance Metrics</name>
      <t>This section introduces three metrics related to throughput and bandwidth.
      Given a specified source and a specified destination, these metrics
      reflect the volume of traffic that the network can carry from the source
      to the destination.</t>
      <section anchor="tput" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Cost Metric: TCP Throughput (tput)</name>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Base Identifier</name>
          <t>The base identifier for this performance metric is "tput".</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Value Representation</name>
          <t>The metric value type is a single 'JSONNumber' type value
          conforming to the number specifications provided in <xref target="RFC8259" sectionFormat="of" section="6"/>.
          The number <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be non-negative. The unit is bytes per second.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Intended Semantics and Use</name>
	  <dl>
          <dt>Intended Semantics:</dt><dd>To give the throughput of a
          congestion control conforming TCP flow from the specified source to the
          specified destination. The throughput <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be interpreted as only
          an estimation, and the estimation is designed only for bulk
          flows.</dd>
         
	    
	      <dt>Use:</dt>
	      <dd>This metric could be used as a cost metric constraint
              attribute or as a returned cost metric in the response.</dd>
	    </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-6">
           <name>TCP Throughput Value on Source-Destination Endpoint Pairs (Example 6)</name>
          <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
POST /endpointcost/lookup HTTP/1.1
Host: alto.example.com
Content-Length: 234
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcostparams+json
Accept: 
  application/alto-endpointcost+json,application/alto-error+json

{
  "cost-type": {
    "cost-mode":   "numerical",
    "cost-metric": "tput"
  },
  "endpoints": {
    "srcs": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.2"
    ],
    "dsts": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89",
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34"
    ]
  }
}

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Length: 251
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcost+json

{
  "meta": {
    "cost-type": {
      "cost-mode":   "numerical",
      "cost-metric": "tput"
    }
  },
  "endpoint-cost-map": {
    "ipv4:192.0.2.2": {
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89":    256000,
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34": 128000
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode></figure>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Cost-Context Specification Considerations</name>
          <dl>
          <dt>"nominal":</dt><dd>Typically, TCP throughput does not have a nominal
          value and <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be generated.</dd>
          <dt>"sla":</dt><dd>Typically, TCP throughput does not have an SLA value and
          <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be generated.</dd>
          <dt>"estimation":</dt><dd>The exact estimation method is outside the scope of
          this document. It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that the "parameters" field of an
          "estimation" TCP throughput metric include the following
          information: (1) the congestion control algorithm and (2) the
          estimation methodology. To specify (1), it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that the
          "parameters" field (object) include a field named
          "congestion-control-algorithm", which provides a URI for the
          specification of the algorithm; for example, for an ALTO server to
          provide estimation of the throughput of a CUBIC congestion control
          flow, its "parameters" field includes the
          "congestion-control-algorithm" field, with value being set to the URI for <xref target="RFC9438" format="default"/>; for an ongoing congestion control algorithm such as BBR, a link to its specification can be added. To
          specify (2), the "parameters" field includes as many details as possible;
          for example, for the TCP Cubic throughout estimation, the "parameters"
          field specifies that the throughput is estimated by setting _C_ to
          0.4, and the equation in <xref target="RFC9438" sectionFormat="comma" section="5.1"/>, Figure 8 is applied; as an
          alternative, the methodology may be based on the NUM model <xref target="Prophet" format="default"/> or the model described in <xref target="G2" format="default"/>.
          The exact specification of the "parameters" field is outside the scope
          of this document.</dd>
	  </dl>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="bwresidual" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Cost Metric: Residual Bandwidth (bw-residual)</name>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Base Identifier</name>
          <t>The base identifier for this performance metric is
          "bw-residual".</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Value Representation</name>
          <t>The metric value type is a single 'JSONNumber' type value that is
          non-negative. The unit of measurement is bytes per second.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Intended Semantics and Use</name>
	  <dl>
          <dt>Intended Semantics:</dt><dd><t>To specify temporal and spatial residual
          bandwidth from the specified source to the specified destination.
          The base semantics of the metric is the Unidirectional Residual
          Bandwidth metric as defined in <xref target="RFC8571"/>, <xref target="RFC8570"/>, and <xref target="RFC7471"/>, but instead
          of specifying the residual bandwidth for a link, it is the residual
          bandwidth of the path from the source to the destination. Hence, it
          is the minimal residual bandwidth among all links from the source to
          the destination. When the max statistical operator is defined for
          the metric, it typically provides the minimum of the link capacities
          along the path, as the default value of the residual bandwidth of a
          link is its link capacity <xref target="RFC8571"/> <xref target="RFC8570"/> <xref target="RFC7471"/>. The spatial
          aggregation unit is specified in the query context (e.g., PID to
          PID, or endpoint to endpoint).</t>
          <t>The default statistical operator for residual bandwidth is the
          current instantaneous sample; that is, the default is assumed to be
          "cur".</t>
         </dd>
	      <dt>Use:</dt>
	      <dd>This metric could be used as a cost metric constraint
              attribute or as a returned cost metric in the response.</dd>
	    </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-7">
           <name>Residual Bandwidth Value on Source-Destination Endpoint Pairs (Example 7)</name>
          <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
POST /endpointcost/lookup HTTP/1.1
Host: alto.example.com
Content-Length: 241
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcostparams+json
Accept: 
  application/alto-endpointcost+json,application/alto-error+json

{
  "cost-type": {
    "cost-mode":   "numerical",
    "cost-metric": "bw-residual"
  },
  "endpoints": {
    "srcs": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.2"
    ],
    "dsts": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89",
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34"
    ]
  }
}

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Length: 255
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcost+json

{
  "meta": {
    "cost-type": {
      "cost-mode":   "numerical",
      "cost-metric": "bw-residual"
    }
  },
  "endpoint-cost-map": {
    "ipv4:192.0.2.2":  {
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89":       0,
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34": 2000
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode></figure>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Cost-Context Specification Considerations</name>
         <dl>
          <dt>"nominal":</dt><dd>Typically, residual bandwidth does not have a nominal
          value.</dd>
          <dt>"sla":</dt><dd>Typically, residual bandwidth does not have an SLA
          value.</dd>
          <dt>"estimation":</dt><dd>See the "estimation" entry in <xref target="ccspec-ow"/>. The current ("cur")
          residual bandwidth of a path is the minimal residual
          bandwidth of all links on the path.</dd>
	 </dl>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="bwavailable" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Cost Metric: Available Bandwidth (bw-available)</name>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Base Identifier</name>
          <t>The base identifier for this performance metric is
          "bw-available".</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Value Representation</name>
          <t>The metric value type is a single 'JSONNumber' type value that is
          non-negative. The unit of measurement is bytes per second.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Intended Semantics and Use</name>
	  <dl>
          <dt>Intended Semantics:</dt><dd><t>To specify temporal and spatial available
          bandwidth from the specified source to the specified destination.
          The base semantics of the metric is the Unidirectional Available
          Bandwidth metric as defined in <xref target="RFC8571"/>, <xref target="RFC8570"/>, and <xref target="RFC7471"/>, but instead
          of specifying the available bandwidth for a link, it is the
          available bandwidth of the path from the source to the destination.
          Hence, it is the minimal available bandwidth among all links from
          the source to the destination. The spatial aggregation unit is
          specified in the query context (e.g., PID to PID, or endpoint to
          endpoint).</t>
          <t>The default statistical operator for available bandwidth is the
          current instantaneous sample; that is, the default is assumed to be
          "cur".</t>
        </dd>
	      <dt>Use:</dt><dd>This metric could be used as a cost metric constraint
              attribute or as a returned cost metric in the response.</dd>
	    </dl>
          <figure anchor="example-8">
           <name>Available Bandwidth Value on Source-Destination Endpoint Pairs (Example 8)</name>
          <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
POST /endpointcost/lookup HTTP/1.1
Host: alto.example.com
Content-Length: 244
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcostparams+json
Accept: 
  application/alto-endpointcost+json,application/alto-error+json

{
  "cost-type": { 
    "cost-mode":   "numerical",
    "cost-metric": "bw-available"
  },
  "endpoints": {
    "srcs": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.2"
    ],
    "dsts": [
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89",
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34"
    ]
  }
}

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Length: 255
Content-Type: application/alto-endpointcost+json

{
  "meta": {
    "cost-type": {
      "cost-mode":   "numerical",
      "cost-metric": "bw-available"
    }
  },
  "endpoint-cost-map": {
    "ipv4:192.0.2.2": {
      "ipv4:192.0.2.89":       0,
      "ipv4:198.51.100.34": 2000
    }
  }
}
]]></sourcecode></figure>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Cost-Context Specification Considerations</name>
         <dl>
          <dt>"nominal":</dt><dd>Typically, available bandwidth does not have a nominal
          value.</dd>
          <dt>"sla":</dt><dd>Typically, available bandwidth does not have an SLA
          value.</dd>
          <dt>"estimation":</dt><dd>See the "estimation" entry in <xref target="ccspec-ow"/>. The current ("cur")
          available bandwidth of a path is the minimum of the available
          bandwidth of all links on the path.</dd>
	 </dl>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="secopconsider" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Operational Considerations</name>
      <t>The exact measurement infrastructure, measurement conditions, and
      computation algorithms can vary between different networks and are outside
      the scope of this document. Both the ALTO server and the ALTO clients,
      however, need to be cognizant of the operational issues discussed in the
      following subsections.</t>
      <t>Also, the performance metrics specified in this document are similar
      in that they may use similar data sources and have similar issues in
      their calculation. Hence, this document specifies issues that the
      performance metrics might have in common and also discusses challenges
      regarding the computation of ALTO performance metrics (<xref target="comp-consider"/>).</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Source Considerations</name>
        <t>The addition of the "cost-source" field solves a key issue: an
        ALTO server needs data sources to compute the cost metrics described
        in this document, and an ALTO client needs to know the data sources to
        better interpret the values.</t>
        <t>To avoid information that is too fine grained, this document introduces
        "cost-source" to indicate only the high-level types of data sources:
        "estimation", "nominal", or "sla", where "estimation" is a type of
        measurement data source, "nominal" is a type of static configuration,
        and "sla" is a type that is based more on policy.</t>
        <t>For example, for "estimation", the ALTO server may use log servers or
        the Operations, Administration, and Maintenance (OAM) system as its data source, as recommended by <xref target="RFC7971" format="default"/>. In particular, the cost metrics defined in
        this document can be computed using routing systems as the data
        sources.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Metric Timestamp Considerations</name>
        <t>Despite the introduction of the additional "cost-context"
        information, the metrics do not have a field to indicate the
        timestamps of the data used to compute the metrics. To indicate this
        attribute, the ALTO server <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> return an HTTP Last-Modified value to
        indicate the freshness of the data used to compute the performance
        metrics.</t>
        <t>If the ALTO client obtains updates through an incremental update
        mechanism <xref target="RFC8895" format="default"/>, the client <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> assume
        that the metric is computed using a snapshot at the time that is
        approximated by the receiving time.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Backward-Compatibility Considerations</name>
        <t>One potential issue introduced by the optional "cost-source" field
        is backward compatibility. Consider the case where an IRD defines two
        "cost-type" entries with the same "cost-mode" and "cost-metric", but one with
        "cost-source" being "estimation" and the other being "sla". In such a case, an
        ALTO client that is not aware of the extension will not be able to
        distinguish between these two types. A similar issue can arise even
        with a single "cost-type" whose "cost-source" is "sla": an ALTO client
        that is not aware of this extension will ignore this field and instead
        consider the metric estimation.</t>
        <t>To address the backward-compatibility issue, if a "cost-metric" is
        "routingcost" and the metric contains a "cost-context" field, then it
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "estimation"; if it is not, the client <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> reject the
        information as invalid.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="comp-consider" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Computation Considerations</name>
        <t>The metric values exposed by an ALTO server may result from
        additional processing of measurements from data sources to compute
        exposed metrics. This may involve data processing tasks such as
        aggregating the results across multiple systems, removing outliers,
        and creating additional statistics. The computation of ALTO performance metrics can present two challenges.</t>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Configuration Parameter Considerations</name>
          <t>Performance metrics often depend on configuration parameters, and
          exposing such configuration parameters can help an ALTO client to
          better understand the exposed metrics. In particular, an ALTO server
          may be configured to compute a TE metric (e.g., packet loss rate) at
          fixed intervals, say every T seconds. To expose this information,
          the ALTO server may provide the client with two pieces of additional
          information: (1) when the metrics were last computed and (2) when
          the metrics will be updated (i.e., the validity period of the
          exposed metric values). The ALTO server can expose these two pieces
          of information by using the HTTP response headers Last-Modified and
          Expires.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Aggregation Computation Considerations</name>
          <t>An ALTO server may not be able to measure the performance metrics
          to be exposed. The basic issue is that the "source" information can
          often be link-level information. For example, routing protocols often measure
          and report only per-link loss and not end-to-end loss; similarly,
          routing protocols report link-level available bandwidth and not
          end-to-end available bandwidth. The ALTO server then needs to
          aggregate these data to provide an abstract and unified view that
          can be more useful to applications. The server should be aware that
          different metrics may use different aggregation computations. For
          example, the end-to-end latency of a path is the sum of the latencies
          of the links on the path; the end-to-end available bandwidth of a
          path is the minimum of the available bandwidth of the links on the
          path; in contrast, aggregating loss values is complicated by the
          potential for correlated loss events on different links in the
          path.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="secsecconsider" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The properties defined in this document present no security
      considerations beyond those in Section <xref target="RFC7285"
      section="15" sectionFormat="bare"/> of the base ALTO
      specification <xref target="RFC7285" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>However, concerns addressed in Sections&nbsp;<xref target="RFC7285" section="15.1" sectionFormat="bare"/>, <xref target="RFC7285" section="15.2" sectionFormat="bare"/>, and <xref target="RFC7285" section="15.3" sectionFormat="bare"/> of <xref target="RFC7285" format="default"/> remain of utmost importance. Indeed,
      TE performance is highly sensitive ISP information;
      therefore, sharing TE metric values in numerical mode requires full
      mutual confidence between the entities managing the ALTO server and the
      ALTO client. ALTO servers will most likely distribute numerical TE
      performance to ALTO clients under strict and formal mutual trust
      agreements. On the other hand, ALTO clients must be cognizant of the
      risks attached to such information that they would have acquired outside
      formal conditions of mutual trust.</t>
      <t>To mitigate confidentiality risks during information transport of TE
      performance metrics, the operator should address the risk of ALTO
      information being leaked to malicious clients or third parties through
      such attacks as person-in-the-middle (PITM) attacks. As specified in
      Section&nbsp;<xref target="RFC7285" section="15.3.2"
sectionFormat="bare">"Protection Strategies"</xref> of <xref target="RFC7285"/>,
the ALTO server should authenticate ALTO
      clients when transmitting an ALTO information resource containing
      sensitive TE performance metrics. Section&nbsp;<xref target="RFC7285" section="8.3.5" sectionFormat="bare">"Authentication and Encryption"</xref> of <xref target="RFC7285"/> specifies that ALTO
      server implementations as well as ALTO client implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
      support the "https" URI scheme <xref target="RFC9110" format="default"/> and
      Transport Layer Security (TLS) <xref target="RFC8446" format="default"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ianaconsider" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <section>
	 <name>ALTO Cost Metrics Registry</name>
      <t>IANA created and now maintains the "ALTO Cost Metrics" registry, as
      listed in <xref target="RFC7285" section="14.2" sectionFormat="comma"/>, Table 3. This registry is located at
<eref target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/alto-protocol/" brackets="angle"/>.
      IANA has added the following entries to the "ALTO
      Cost Metrics" registry.</t>
      <table>
	<name>ALTO Cost Metrics Registry</name>
	<thead>
	  <tr>
	    <th>Identifier</th>
	    <th>Intended Semantics</th>
	    <th>Reference</th>
	  </tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <tr>
	    <td>delay-ow</td>
	    <td>See <xref target="oneway"/></td>
	    <td>RFC 9439</td>
	    </tr><tr>  
	    <td>delay-rt</td>
	    <td>See <xref target="delayrt"/></td>
	    <td>RFC 9439</td>
	    </tr><tr>    
	    <td>delay-variation</td>
	    <td>See <xref target="delayvar"/></td>
	    <td>RFC 9439</td>
	    </tr><tr> 
	    <td>lossrate</td>
	    <td>See <xref target="lossrate"/></td>
	    <td>RFC 9439</td>
	    </tr><tr>  
	    <td>hopcount</td>
	    <td>See <xref target="hopcount"/></td>
	    <td>RFC 9439</td>
	    </tr><tr>
	    <td>tput</td>
	    <td>See <xref target="tput"/></td>
	    <td>RFC 9439</td>
	    </tr><tr> 
	    <td>bw-residual</td>
	    <td>See <xref target="bwresidual"/></td>
	    <td>RFC 9439</td>
	    </tr><tr> 
	    <td>bw-available</td>
	    <td>See <xref target="bwavailable"/></td>
	    <td>RFC 9439</td>
	  </tr>
</tbody>
      </table>
</section>
<section>
   <name>ALTO Cost Source Types Registry</name>
      <t>IANA has created the "ALTO Cost Source Types"
      registry. This registry serves two purposes. First, it ensures the
      uniqueness of identifiers referring to ALTO cost source types. Second,
      it provides references to particular semantics of allocated cost source
      types to be applied by both ALTO servers and applications utilizing ALTO
      clients.</t>
      <t>A new ALTO cost source type can be added after IETF Review <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>, to ensure that proper documentation regarding
      the new ALTO cost source type and its security considerations has been
      provided. The RFC(s) documenting the new cost source type should be detailed
      enough to provide guidance to both ALTO service providers and
      applications utilizing ALTO clients as to how values of the registered
      ALTO cost source type should be interpreted. Updates and deletions of ALTO
      cost source types follow the same procedure.</t>
      <t>Registered ALTO address type identifiers <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> conform to the
      syntactical requirements specified in <xref target="meta" sectionFormat="bare"/>. Identifiers are to be
      recorded and displayed as strings.</t>
      <t>Requests to add a new value to the registry <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include the
      following information: </t>
      <dl>
        <dt>Identifier:</dt><dd>The name of the desired ALTO cost source type.</dd>
        <dt>Intended Semantics:</dt><dd> ALTO cost source types carry with them
          semantics to guide their usage by ALTO clients. Hence, a document
          defining a new type should provide guidance to both ALTO service
          providers and applications utilizing ALTO clients as to how values
          of the registered ALTO endpoint property should be interpreted.</dd>
        <dt>Security Considerations:</dt><dd> ALTO cost source types expose
          information to ALTO clients. ALTO service providers should be made
          aware of the security ramifications related to the exposure of a
          cost source type.</dd>
      </dl>
      <t>IANA has registered the identifiers
      "nominal", "sla", and "estimation" as listed in the table below.</t>
      <table>
	<name>ALTO Cost Source Types Registry</name>
	<thead>
	  <tr>
	  <th>Identifier</th>
	  <th>Intended Semantics</th>
          <th>Security Considerations</th>
          <th>Reference</th>
	  </tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <tr>
	    <td>nominal</td>
	    <td>Values in nominal cases (<xref target="meta"/>)</td>
            <td><xref target="secsecconsider"/></td>
            <td>RFC 9439</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td>sla</td>
	    <td>Values reflecting Service Level Agreement (<xref  target="meta"/>)</td>
	    <td><xref target="secsecconsider"/></td>
            <td>RFC 9439</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	 <td>estimation</td>
	 <td>Values by estimation (<xref target="meta"/>)</td>
	 <td><xref target="secsecconsider"/></td>
         <td>RFC 9439</td>
	  </tr>
	</tbody>
      </table>
     </section>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
<displayreference target="I-D.corre-quic-throughput-testing" to="QUIC-THROUGHPUT-TESTING"/>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3630.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5305.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6390.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7285.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7471.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8259.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8570.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8571.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8895.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9110.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="IANA-IPPM" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/performance-metrics/">
          <front>
            <title>Performance Metrics</title>
            <author>
             <organization>IANA</organization>
	    </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-tcpm-rfc8312bis (RFC 9438) (AUTH48-DONE) -->
<reference anchor='RFC9438' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9438'>
<front>
<title>CUBIC for Fast and Long-Distance Networks</title>
<author fullname="Lisong Xu">
</author>
<author fullname="Sangtae Ha">
</author>
<author fullname="Injong Rhee">
</author>
<author fullname="Vidhi Goel">
</author>
<author fullname="Lars Eggert" role="editor">
</author>
<date month="August" year="2023"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9438"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9438"/>
</reference>

      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2330.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2681.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3393.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5357.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7679.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7971.xml"/>

<!-- draft-corre-quic-throughput-testing (Expired) -->
        <xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.corre-quic-throughput-testing.xml"/>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9000.xml"/>

      <reference anchor="G2" target="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3366707">
          <front>
            <title>On the Bottleneck Structure of Congestion-Controlled
          Networks</title>
            <author initials="J" surname="Ros-Giralt"/>
            <author initials="A" surname="Bohara"/>
            <author initials="S" surname="Yellamraju"/>
            <author initials="M" surname="Harper Langston"/>
            <author initials="R" surname="Lethin"/>
            <author initials="Y" surname="Jiang"/>
            <author initials="L" surname="Tassiulas"/>
            <author initials="J" surname="Li"/>
            <author initials="Y" surname="Tan"/>
            <author initials="M" surname="Veeraraghavan"/>
            <date month="December" year="2019"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>Proceedings of the ACM on Measurement and Analysis of Computing Systems, Vol. 3, No. 3, Article No. 59, pp. 1-31</refcontent>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/3366707"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="FlowDirector" target="">
          <front>
            <title>Steering Hyper-Giants' Traffic at Scale</title>
            <author initials="E" surname="Pujol"/>
            <author initials="I" surname="Poese"/>
            <author initials="J" surname="Zerwas"/>
            <author initials="G" surname="Smaragdakis"/>
            <author initials="A" surname="Feldmann"/>
            <date month="December" year="2019"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>ACM CoNEXT '19</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="Prometheus" target="">
          <front>
            <title>Prometheus: A Next-Generation Monitoring System (Talk)</title>
            <author initials="J" surname="Volz"/>
            <author initials="B" surname="Rabenstein"/>
            <date month="May" year="2015"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>SREcon15 Europe</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="Prophet" target="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1109/TNET.2020.3016838">
          <front>
            <title>Prophet: Toward Fast, Error-Tolerant Model-Based Throughput Prediction for Reactive Flows in DC Networks</title>
            <author initials="J" surname="Zhang"/>
            <author initials="K" surname="Gao"/>
            <author initials="YR" surname="Yang"/>
            <author initials="J" surname="Bi"/>
            <date month="December" year="2020"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking, Volume 28, Issue 601, pp. 2475-2488</refcontent>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>The authors of this document would like to thank <contact fullname="Martin Duke"/> for
      the highly informative, thorough AD reviews and comments. We thank <contact fullname="Christian Amsss"/>, <contact fullname="Elwyn Davies"/>, <contact fullname="Haizhou Du"/>, <contact fullname="Kai Gao"/>, <contact fullname="Geng Li"/>, <contact fullname="Lili Liu"/>, <contact fullname="Danny Alex Lachos Perez"/>, and <contact fullname="Brian Trammell"/> for their reviews and comments. We thank <contact fullname="Benjamin Kaduk"/>, <contact fullname="Erik Kline"/>, <contact fullname="Francesca Palombini"/>, <contact fullname="Lars Eggert"/>, <contact fullname="Martin Vigoureux"/>, <contact fullname="Murray Kucherawy"/>, <contact fullname="Roman Danyliw"/>, <contact fullname="Zaheduzzaman Sarker"/>, and <contact fullname="ric Vyncke"/> for discussions and comments that improved
      this document.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
