<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!-- pre-edited by ST 08/07/24 -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" number="9660" consensus="true" xml:lang="en" ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-dnsop-zoneversion-11" tocInclude="true" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3" submissionType="IETF" updates="" obsoletes="">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="DNS ZONEVERSION Option">The DNS Zone Version (ZONEVERSION) Option</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9660"/>
    <author fullname="Hugo Salgado" initials="H." surname="Salgado">
      <organization>NIC Chile</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Miraflores 222, piso 14</street>
          <city>Santiago</city>
          <code>CP 8320198</code>
          <country>Chile</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+56 2 29407700</phone>
        <email>hsalgado@nic.cl</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Mauricio Vergara Ereche" initials="M." surname="Vergara">
      <organization>DigitalOcean</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 6th Ave</street>
          <city>New York</city>
	  <region>NY</region>
          <code>10013</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mvergara@digitalocean.com</email>
       </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Duane Wessels" initials="D." surname="Wessels">
      <organization>Verisign</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12061 Bluemont Way</street>
          <city>Reston</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <code>20190</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 703 948-3200</phone>
        <email>dwessels@verisign.com</email>
        <uri>https://verisign.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2024" month="October"/>
    <area>OPS</area>
    <workgroup>dnsop</workgroup>

    <keyword>zoneversion</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The DNS ZONEVERSION option is a way for DNS clients to request,
        and for authoritative DNS servers to provide, information
        regarding the version of the zone from which a response is
        generated.  The SERIAL field from the Start of Authority (SOA)
        resource record (RR) is a good example of a zone's version, and it is the
        only one defined by this specification.  Additional version
        types may be defined by future specifications.</t>

      <t>Including zone version data in a response simplifies and improves
        the quality of debugging and diagnostics since the version
        and the DNS answer are provided atomically.  This can be especially
        useful for zones and DNS providers that leverage IP anycast or
        multiple backend systems.  It functions similarly to the
        DNS Name Server Identifier (NSID) option described in RFC 5001.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>The ZONEVERSION option
        allows DNS queriers to request, and authoritative DNS servers to provide,
        a
        token representing the version of the zone from which a DNS response was generated. It is similar
        to the NSID option <xref target="RFC5001"/>, which can be used to convey the identification
        of a name server that generates a response.</t>

      <t>The Domain Name System allows data to be loosely coherent
        <xref target="RFC3254"/>, because synchronization can never
        be instantaneous, and some uses of DNS do not require strong
        coherency anyway.  This means that a record obtained by
        one response could be out of sync with other authoritative
        sources of the same data at the same point in time.  This can
        make it difficult to debug some problems when there is a need
        to couple the data with the version of the zone it came from.
        Furthermore, in today's Internet, it is common for high volume and
        important DNS zones to utilize IP anycast (<xref target="RFC4786" sectionFormat="of" section="4.9"/>) and/or load-balanced backend
        servers.  In general, there is no way to ensure that two separate
        queries are delivered to the same server.  The ZONEVERSION option both
        simplifies and improves DNS monitoring and debugging by
        directly associating the data and the version together in a
        single response.</t>

      <t>The SOA SERIAL field (<xref target="RFC1034" sectionFormat="of" section="4.3.5"/>) is one example of zone versioning.  Its purpose
        is to facilitate the distribution of zone data between primary
        and secondary name servers.  It is also often useful in DNS
        monitoring and debugging.  This document specifies the SOA SERIAL
        as one type of ZONEVERSION data.</t>

      <t>Some DNS zones may use other distribution and synchronization
        mechanisms that are not based on the SOA SERIAL number, such as relational
        databases or other proprietary methods.  In those cases, the SOA
        SERIAL field may not be relevant with respect to the versioning
        of its content.  To accommodate these use cases, new ZONEVERSION
        types could be defined in future specifications.  Alternatively,
        zone operators may use one of the Private Use ZONEVERSION code
        points allocated by this specification.</t>

      <t>The ZONEVERSION option is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> to implement by DNS clients and name servers.
        It is designed for use only when a name server provides
        authoritative response data.  It is intended only for hop-to-hop
        communication and is not transitive.</t>

      <section>
	<name>Requirements Language</name>
              <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be
    interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref
    target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as
    shown here.
        </t>

      </section>

      <section>
	<name>Terminology</name>
        <t>In this document, "original QNAME" is used to mean what the
        DNS terminology document <xref target="RFC9499"/> calls "QNAME
        (original)":</t>
        <blockquote>The name actually sent in the Question section
        in the original query, which is always echoed in the (final)
        reply in the Question section when the QR bit is set to 1.</blockquote>

        <t>In this document, an "enclosing zone" of a domain name means
          a zone in which the domain name is present as an owner name
          or any parent of that zone.  For example, if B.C.EXAMPLE and
          EXAMPLE are zones but C.EXAMPLE is not, the domain name
          A.B.C.EXAMPLE has B.C.EXAMPLE, EXAMPLE, and the root as
          enclosing zones.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="theoption">
      <name>The ZONEVERSION Option</name>
      
      <t>This document specifies a new EDNS(0) <xref target="RFC6891"/> option, ZONEVERSION, which can be used by DNS
        clients and servers to provide information regarding the version
        of the zone from which a response is generated.</t>

      <section>
	<name>Wire Format</name>

        <t>The ZONEVERSION option is encoded as follows:</t>

        <t>OPTION-CODE for the ZONEVERSION option is 19.</t>

        <t>OPTION-LENGTH for the ZONEVERSION option <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have a value of 0 for queries
          and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have the value of the length (in octets) of the OPTION-DATA for responses.</t>

        <t>OPTION-DATA for the ZONEVERSION option is omitted in queries.  For responses, it is composed of three fields:</t>

          <ul>
            <li>an unsigned 1-octet Label Count (LABELCOUNT)
              indicating the number of labels for the name of the zone that VERSION value refers to</li>

            <li>an unsigned 1-octet type number (TYPE) distinguishing the format and meaning of VERSION</li>

            <li>an opaque octet string conveying the zone version data (VERSION)</li>
          </ul>

      <figure>
        <name>Diagram with the OPTION-DATA Format for the ZONEVERSION Option</name>
        <artset>
          <artwork type="ascii-art" name="zoneversion.txt">
<![CDATA[
                +0 (MSB)                       +1 (LSB)
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
0: |           LABELCOUNT          |            TYPE               |
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
2: |                            VERSION                            |
   /                                                               /
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
]]></artwork>
        </artset>
      </figure>


      <t>
        The LABELCOUNT field indicates the name of the zone that the ZONEVERSION option refers to, by means of taking the last LABELCOUNT labels of the original QNAME.
        For example, an answer with QNAME "a.b.c.example.com" and a ZONEVERSION option with a LABELCOUNT of value 2 indicates that the zone name in which this ZONEVERSION refers to is "example.com.".</t>
	
      <t>In the case of a downward referral response, the LABELCOUNT number helps to differentiate between the parent and child zones, where the parent is authoritative for some portion of the QNAME above a zone cut.  Also, if the ANSWER section has more than one RR set with different zones (like a CNAME and a target name in another zone), the number of labels in the QNAME disambiguates such a situation.</t>

      <t>The value of the LABELCOUNT field <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> count the null (root) label that terminates the original QNAME. The value of the LABELCOUNT field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be less than or equal to the number of labels in the original QNAME.
        The Root zone (".") has a LABELCOUNT field value of 0.</t>


      </section>

        <section anchor="optionpresentation">
	  <name>Presentation Format</name>
          <t>The presentation format of the ZONEVERSION option is as follows:</t>

          <t>The OPTION-CODE field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be represented as the mnemonic value ZONEVERSION.</t>

          <t>The OPTION-LENGTH field <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be omitted,
            but if present, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be represented as an unsigned decimal integer.</t>

          <t>The LABELCOUNT value of the OPTION-DATA field <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be omitted,
            but if present, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be represented as an unsigned decimal integer.
            The corresponding zone name <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be displayed (i.e., LABELCOUNT labels of the original QNAME)
            for easier human consumption.</t>

          <t>The TYPE and VERSION fields of the option <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be represented according to each specific TYPE.</t>

        </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>ZONEVERSION Processing</name>
      <section>
	<name>Initiators</name>
        <t>A DNS client <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> signal its support and desire for zone version information by
          including an empty ZONEVERSION option in the EDNS(0) OPT pseudo-RR of a query to an authoritative
          name server.  An empty ZONEVERSION option has OPTION-LENGTH set to zero.</t>
        <t>A DNS client <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> send the ZONEVERSION option to non-authoritative name servers.</t>
        <t>A DNS client <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> include more than one ZONEVERSION option in the OPT pseudo-RR of a DNS query.</t>
      </section>

      <section>
	<name>Responders</name>
          <t>A name server that (a) understands the ZONEVERSION option, (b) receives a
          query with the ZONEVERSION option, (c) is
          authoritative for one or more enclosing zones of the original QNAME, and (d) chooses to honor a
          particular ZONEVERSION request responds by including a TYPE and
          corresponding VERSION value in a ZONEVERSION option in an EDNS(0)
          OPT pseudo-RR in the response message.</t>

        <t>Otherwise,
          a server <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> include a ZONEVERSION option in the response.</t>

        <t>A name server <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> include more than one ZONEVERSION option in
           the response if it supports multiple TYPEs. A name server <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>
           also include more than one ZONEVERSION option in the response
           if it is authoritative for more than one enclosing zone of the original
           QNAME. A name server <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> include more than one ZONEVERSION
        option for a given TYPE and LABELCOUNT.</t>

        <t>Note: the ZONEVERSION option should be included for any response
          satisfying the criteria above including, but not limited to, the following:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>Downward referral
            (see "Referrals" in <xref target="RFC9499" section="4"/>),
            even though the response's Authoritative Answer bit is not set.
            In this case, the ZONEVERSION data <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> correspond to the version of the referring zone.</li>
          <li>Name error (NXDOMAIN), even though the response
            does not include any Answer section RRs.</li>
          <li>NODATA (<xref target="RFC9499" section="3"/>),
            even though the response does not include any Answer
            section RRs.</li>
          <li>Server failure (SERVFAIL) when the server is authoritative for the original QNAME.</li>
        </ul>

        <section>
	  <name>Responding to Invalid ZONEVERSION Queries</name>

          <t>A name server that understands the ZONEVERSION option <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
             return a FORMERR response when:</t>
          <ul>
            <li>The ZONEVERSION OPTION-LENGTH is not zero.</li>
            <li>More than one ZONEVERSION option is present.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>

        <section>
	  <name>ZONEVERSION Is Not Transitive</name>

          <t>The ZONEVERSION option is not transitive.  A name server
            (recursive or otherwise) <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> blindly copy the ZONEVERSION
            option from a query it receives into a subsequent query that
            it sends onward to another server.  A name server <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>
            send a ZONEVERSION option back to a client that did not
            request it.</t>

        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>The SOA-SERIAL ZONEVERSION Type</name>

      <t>The first and only ZONEVERSION option TYPE defined in this document is a zone's serial number as found in the Start of Authority (SOA) RR.</t>

      <t>As mentioned previously, some DNS zones may use alternative
        distribution and synchronization mechanisms that are not based on the SOA
        SERIAL number, and the SERIAL field may not be relevant with
        respect to the versioning of zone content.  In those cases, a
        name server <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> include a ZONEVERSION option with type
        SOA-SERIAL in a reply.</t>

      <t>The value for this type is "0".</t>

      <t>The mnemonic for this type is "SOA-SERIAL".</t>

      <t>The EDNS(0) OPTION-LENGTH for this type <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to "6" in responses.</t>

      <t>The VERSION value for the SOA-SERIAL type <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a copy of the unsigned 32-bit 
        SERIAL field of the SOA RR, as defined in <xref target="RFC1035" section="3.3.13"/>.</t>

        <section anchor="typepresentation">
	  <name>Type SOA-SERIAL Presentation Format</name>
          <t>The presentation format of this type content is as follows:</t>
	  <ul empty="true">
          <li>The TYPE field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be represented as the mnemonic value "SOA-SERIAL".</li>
          <li>The VERSION field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be represented as an unsigned decimal integer.</li>
	  </ul>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="usage">
      <name>Example Usage</name>
      <t>A name server that (a) implements this specification, (b)
      receives a query with the ZONEVERSION option, (c) is authoritative
      for the zone of the original QNAME, and (d) utilizes the SOA SERIAL field for
      versioning of said zone should include a ZONEVERSION option in
      its response.  In the response's ZONEVERSION option, the EDNS(0) OPTION-LENGTH
      would be set to 6 and the OPTION-DATA would consist of the 1-octet LABELCOUNT,
      the 1-octet TYPE with value 0, and the 4-octet SOA-SERIAL value.</t>

      <t>The example below demonstrates expected output of a diagnostic tool that implements the ZONEVERSION option, displaying a response from a compliant authoritative DNS server:</t>
      <figure>
	
          <name>Example Usage and Dig Output</name>	  
          <sourcecode type="dns-rr">
<![CDATA[
  $ dig @ns.example.com www.example.com aaaa +zoneversion \
  +norecurse +nocmd

  ;; Got answer:
  ;; ->>HEADER<<- opcode: QUERY, status: NOERROR, id: 7077
  ;; flags: qr aa; QUERY: 1, ANSWER: 1, AUTHORITY: 1, ADDITIONAL: 2

  ;; OPT PSEUDOSECTION:
  ; EDNS: version: 0, flags:; udp: 1232
  ; ZONEVERSION: 02 00 78 95 a4 e9 ("SOA-SERIAL: 2023073001 \
  ; (example.com.)")
  ;; QUESTION SECTION:
  ;www.example.com.    IN  AAAA

  ;; ANSWER SECTION:
  www.example.com.  43200  IN  AAAA  2001:db8::80

  ;; AUTHORITY SECTION:
  example.com.    43200  IN  NS  ns.example.com.

  ;; ADDITIONAL SECTION:
  ns.example.com.    43200  IN  AAAA  2001:db8::53

  ;; Query time: 15 msec
  ;; SERVER: 2001:db8::53#53(2001:db8::53) (UDP)
  ;; WHEN: dom jul 30 19:51:04 -04 2023
  ;; MSG SIZE  rcvd: 129
]]>
          </sourcecode>
        </figure>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <section>
	<name>DNS EDNS(0) Option Code Registration</name>
        <t>This document defines a new EDNS(0) option,
          entitled "ZONEVERSION" (see <xref target="theoption"/>), with the 
          assigned value of 19 from the "DNS EDNS0 Option Codes (OPT)" registry:</t>

        <table>
            <name>DNS EDNS0 Option Codes (OPT) Registry</name>
          <thead>
            <tr><th>Value</th>
	    <th>Name</th><th>Status</th><th>Reference</th></tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr><th>19</th>
	    <th>ZONEVERSION</th><th>Standard</th><th>RFC 9660</th></tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>

      </section>

      <section>
	<name>ZONEVERSION TYPE Values Registry</name>
	  
<t>
	  IANA has created and will maintain a new registry called "ZONEVERSION TYPE Values" in the "Domain Name System (DNS) Parameters" registry group as follows:</t>
   <table>
          <name>Registration Procedures for the ZONEVERSION TYPE Values Registry</name>
          <thead>
            <tr><th>Range</th><th>Registration Procedures</th></tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr><th>0-245</th><th>Specification Required</th></tr>
            <tr><th>246-254</th><th>Private Use</th></tr>
            <tr><th>255</th><th>Reserved</th></tr>
          </tbody>
   </table>

   <t>
          Initial values for the "ZONEVERSION TYPE Values" registry are given below;
          future assignments in the 1-245 values range are to be made through
	  Specification Required <xref target="RFC8126"/>.
          Assignments consist of a TYPE value as an unsigned 8-bit integer recorded in decimal,
          a Mnemonic name as an uppercase ASCII string with a maximum length of 15 characters,
          and the required document reference.</t>

        <table>
           <name>ZONEVERSION TYPE Values Registry</name>
          <thead>
            <tr><th>ZONEVERSION TYPE</th><th>Mnemonic</th><th>Reference</th></tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr><th>0</th><th>SOA-SERIAL</th><th>RFC 9660</th></tr>
            <tr><th>1-245</th><th>Unassigned</th><th/></tr>
            <tr><th>246-254</th><th>Reserved for Private Use</th><th>RFC 9660</th></tr>
            <tr><th>255</th><th>Reserved</th><th>RFC 9660</th></tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>

        <t>The change controller for this registry is IETF.</t>

        <section>
	  <name>Designated Expert Review Directives</name>

	  
          <t>The allocation procedure for new code points in the "ZONEVERSION TYPE Values" registry is Specification Required, thus review is required by a designated expert as stated in <xref target="RFC8126"/>.</t>

          <t>When evaluating requests, the expert should consider the following:</t>
            <ul>
              <li>Duplication of code point allocations should be avoided.</li>
              <li>A Presentation Format section should be provided
                with a clear code point mnemonic.</li>
              <li>The referenced document and stated use of the new code point should be appropriate for the intended use of a ZONEVERSION TYPE assignment.
                In particular, the reference should state clear instructions for implementers about the syntax and semantic of the data.
                Also, the length of the data must have proper limits.</li>
            </ul>

          <t>The expert reviewing the request <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> respond within 10 business days.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The EDNS extension data is not covered by RRSIG records,
        so there's no way to verify its authenticity nor integrity using DNSSEC,
        and it could theoretically be tampered with by a person in the middle if the transport is made by insecure means.
      Caution should be taken to use the EDNS ZONEVERSION data for any means besides troubleshooting and debugging.</t>

      <t>If there's a need to certify the trustworthiness of ZONEVERSION,
        it will be necessary to use an encrypted and authenticated DNS transport,
        a transaction signature (TSIG) <xref target="RFC8945"/>, or SIG(0) <xref target="RFC2931"/>.</t>
	
      <t>If there's a need to authenticate the data origin for the ZONEVERSION value,
        an answer with the SOA-SERIAL type as defined above could be compared to a separate regular SOA query with a DO flag,
        whose answer shall be DNSSEC signed.
        Since these are separate queries, the caveats about loose coherency already stated in
        the <xref target="intro" format="title"/> (<xref target="intro"/>) would apply.</t>

      <t>With the SOA-SERIAL type defined above, there's no risk on disclosure of private information,
        as the SERIAL of the SOA record is already publicly available.</t>

      <t>Please note that the ZONEVERSION option cannot be used for checking the correctness of an entire zone in a server.
        For such cases,
        the ZONEMD record <xref target="RFC8976"/> might be better suited for such a task.
        ZONEVERSION can help identify and correlate a specific answer with a version of a zone,
        but it has no special integrity or verification function besides a normal field value inside a zone,
        as stated above.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>

    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6891.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
       <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
    </references>
    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3254.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4786.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5001.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2931.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8945.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8976.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9499.xml"/>

      <reference anchor="ImplRef" target="https://github.com/huguei/rrserial">
          <front>
            <title>Zoneversion Implementations</title>
            <author>
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="August" year="2023"/>
          </front>
	  <refcontent>commit f5f68a0</refcontent>
        </reference>

    </references>
    <section anchor="implementationcons">
      <name>Implementation Considerations</name>
      <t>With very few
exceptions, EDNS(0) option values in a response
are independent of the queried name. This is not the case for ZONEVERSION, so
its implementation may be more or less difficult, depending on how EDNS(0)
options are handled in the name server.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="implementation">
      <name>Implementation References</name>
      <t>There is a patched NSD server (version 4.7.0) with support for ZONEVERSION as well as live test servers installed for compliance tests. Also, there is a client command "dig" with added zoneversion support, along with test libraries in Perl, Python, and Go. See <xref target="ImplRef"/> for more information.</t>
    </section>
      <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>The authors are thankful for all the support and comments made in the DNSOP Working Group mailing list,
        chats, and discussions.
        A special thanks for suggestions to generalize the option using a registry of types from
        <contact fullname="Petr Špaček"/> and <contact fullname="Florian Obser"/>,
        suggestions for implementation from
        <contact fullname="Stéphane Bortzmeyer"/>,
        clarifications on security from <contact fullname="George Michaelson"/>,
        zone name disambiguation from <contact fullname="Joe Abley"/> and <contact fullname="Brian Dickson"/>,
        and reviews from <contact fullname="Tim Wicinski"/> and <contact fullname="Peter Thomassen"/>.</t>
    </section>

</back>
</rfc>
